<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="154">
  <!-- This xml conforms to:  http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>Information obtained from ClinicalTrials.gov on October 20, 2011</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01212055</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>100201</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>10-C-0201</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01212055</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Apheresis of Patients With Immunodeficiency</brief_title>
  <official_title>Apheresis and CD34+ Selection of Mobilized Peripheral Blood CD34+ Cells From Patients With DOCK8 Deficiency, LAD-1, and MonoMAC</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      - Gene therapy is being investigated as a possible treatment for individuals with
      immunodeficiency diseases or other conditions that make it difficult to fight off infection.
      Gene therapy avoids problems with donor identification and possible rejection of bone marrow
      transplant by using the patient's own modified blood cells to help treat the disease.
      Researchers are interested in collecting stem cells from the blood of individuals with
      immunodeficiency diseases in order to use the cells to develop potential gene therapy
      treatments.

      Objectives:

      - To collect blood stem cells from patients with immunodeficiency diseases  tto  test our
      ability to correct the defects of these cells in the test tube. .

      Eligibility:

        -  Individuals between 18 and 40 years of age with immunodeficiency diseases.

        -  Individuals with human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) will not be able to participate in
           this study.

      Design:

        -  Participants will provide an initial blood sample for disease screening (such as
           hepatitis B and C, syphilis, or viruses like the Epstein-Barr virus, herpes simplex
           virus, or toxoplasmosis) and to check kidney and liver function.

        -  Starting 5 days before blood donation, participants will receive daily injections of a
           drug called G-CSF (granulocyte colony stimulating factor, or filgrastim), which pushes
           stem cells out of the bone marrow and into the bloodstream. Participants will receive
           the injections at the National Institutes of Health Clinical Center.

        -  On day 5, participants will have a single leukapheresis procedure to collect the stem
           cells from the blood.

        -  No additional treatment will be provided as part of this protocol. The cells that are
           collected will be used fore experiments in the lab and will not be used to treat
           individuals with these diseases.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      BACKGROUND:

      Primary immunodeficiency diseases (PID) represent candidate genetic disorders for new
      therapeutic approaches. Our laboratory is developing gene therapy for patients with PID
      using autologous CD34+ hematopoietic stem cells (HSC). Gene therapy may circumvent problems
      with allogeneic HSC transplantation, especially graft rejection and
      graft-versus-host-disease. We are particularly interested in three PID: Dedicator of
      CytoKinesis-8 (DOCK8) deficiency, Leukocyte Adhesion Deficiency type 1 (LAD-1), and MonoMAC.
      For DOCK8 deficiency, and LAD-1, the disease gene has been cloned. The genetic basis for
      MonoMAC has not been determined, however we anticipate that it will be due to a single gene
      defect due to the autosomal dominant nature of its inheritance. Testing new vector
      constructs and transduction conditions for gene therapy would be considerably enhanced by
      the acquisition of peripheral blood CD34+ cells from patients with these immunodeficiency
      diseases.

      OBJECTIVES:

      To provide a source of granulocyte colony stimulating factor (G-CSF) mobilized peripheral
      blood CD34+ hematopoietic stem cells (HSC) for laboratory research studies including
      optimization of vector and transduction conditions for gene therapy for DOCK8 deficiency,
      LAD-1, and MonoMAC.

      ELIGIBILITY:

      Patients 15-40 years old with DOCK8 deficiency, LAD-1, and MonoMAC who meet the eligibility
      requirements will be considered for this protocol.

      DESIGN:

      Patients 15-40 years old with DOCK8 deficiency, LAD-1, and MonoMAC will receive five days of
      G-CSF followed by a single apheresis. CD34+ cell will be selected and frozen in aliquots by
      the Cell Processing Section of the Department of Transfusion Medicine. No treatments, or
      investigational therapy will be administered on this protocol.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2010</start_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Time Perspective:  Prospective</study_design>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">6</enrollment>
  <condition>LAD-1</condition>
  <condition>DOCK8</condition>
  <condition>MonoMAC</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

               1. Patient age of 15-40 years.

               2. Diagnosis of DOCK8 deficiency, LAD-1, or MonoMAC:

        DOCK8 Deficiency

        Homozygous or compound heterozygous mutations in the DOCK8 gene.

        LAD-1

        Less than 10% CD18 expression on the neutrophil surface.

        MonoMAC

          1. Onset of immunodeficiency disease beyond infancy.

          2. Clinical history of at least two episodes of life-threatening infection with
             opportunistic organisms.

          3. Flow cytometry profile on peripheral blood leukocytes with:

               -  Absolute monocyte count less than the lower limit for normal (Note: Patients
                  with clonal chromosomal abnormalities, and those on G-CSF, are allowed to have a
                  normal or elevated monocyte count).

               -  NK+ cell count less than the lower limit for normal CD20+ cell count less than
                  the lower limit for normal CD3+ cell count &gt; 100

                  c) Serum creatinine &lt; 1.5 mg/dL.

                  d) Total Bilirubin &lt;  3mg/dl, ALT and AST &lt;  5 times upper limit of normal.

                  e) Ability to give informed consent.

                  f) Adequate venous access for peripheral apheresis, or consent to use a
                  temporary central venous catheter for apheresis.

                  g) Female patients of childbearing age must have a negative urine pregnancy test
                  within one week of beginning G-CSF administration.

                  h) A patient who is lactating must be willing and able to interrupt
                  breast-feeding or substitute formula feeding for her infant during the period of
                  filgrastim administration and for two days following the final dose. Filgrastim
                  may be secreted in human milk, although its bioavailability from this source is
                  not known. Limited clinical data suggest that short-term administration of
                  filgrastim or sargramostim to neonates is not associated with adverse outcomes

                  j) Potential patients must be screened by an apheresis nurse to check venous
                  access before protocol entry. Antecubital veins must be adequate for peripheral
                  access during leukapheresis, or the patient must give written consent for
                  placement of a temporary central venous access catheter.

             EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

               1. HIV infection.

               2. Chronic hepatitis B or hepatitis C virus infection.

               3. History of psychiatric disorder which may compromise compliance with protocol,
                  or which does not allow for appropriate informed consent.

               4. Active infection that is not responding to antimicrobial therapy.

             f) Pregnant. The effects on breast-milk are also unknown and may be harmful to the
             infant; therefore, women should not breast feed during the interval from study entry
             to collection.

             g) Sexually active individuals capable of becoming pregnant who are unable or
             unwilling to use effective form(s) of contraception during time enrolled on study.
             Effective forms of contraception include one or more of the following: intrauterine
             device (IUD), hormonal (birth control pills, injections, or implants), tubal
             ligation/hysterectomy, partner's vasectomy, barrier methods, (condom, diaphragm, or
             cervical cap), or abstinence. Males on the protocol must use an effective form of
             contraception at study entry.

             h) Presence of active malignancy in another organ system other than the hematopoietic
             system.

             i) History of hypertension that is not controlled by medication, stroke, or severe
             heart disease. Individuals with symptomatic angina will be considered to have severe
             heart disease and will not be eligible.

             j) Other medical contraindications to stem cell donation (i.e. severe
             atherosclerosis, autoimmune disease, iritis or episcleritis, deep venous thrombosis,
             cerebrovascular accident)

             k) Thrombocytopenia (platelets less than 50,000 per microL) at baseline evaluation.

             l) Patients receiving experimental therapy or investigational agents.

             m) Sensitivity to filgrastim or to E. coli-derived recombinant protein products.

             n) Patients must test negative for transfusion-transmissible infectious agents,
             including hepatitis B (HBsAg), hepatitis C (anti-HCV), HIV (anti-HIV-1/2).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>15 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>40 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>NCI Referral Office</last_name>
    <phone>1-888-NCI-1937</phone>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_2010-C-0201.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Anderlini P, Korbling M, Dale D, Gratwohl A, Schmitz N, Stroncek D, Howe C, Leitman S, Horowitz M, Gluckman E, Rowley S, Przepiorka D, Champlin R. Allogeneic blood stem cell transplantation: considerations for donors. Blood. 1997 Aug 1;90(3):903-8.</citation>
    <PMID>9242518</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bauer TR Jr, Hai M, Tuschong LM, Burkholder TH, Gu YC, Sokolic RA, Ferguson C, Dunbar CE, Hickstein DD. Correction of the disease phenotype in canine leukocyte adhesion deficiency using ex vivo hematopoietic stem cell gene therapy. Blood. 2006 Nov 15;108(10):3313-20. Epub 2006 Jul 25.</citation>
    <PMID>16868255</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Creevy KE, Bauer TR Jr, Tuschong LM, Embree LJ, Silverstone AM, Bacher JD, Romines C, Garnier J, Thomas ML 3rd, Colenda L, Hickstein DD. Mixed chimeric hematopoietic stem cell transplant reverses the disease phenotype in canine leukocyte adhesion deficiency. Vet Immunol Immunopathol. 2003 Oct 15;95(3-4):113-21.</citation>
    <PMID>12963272</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2011</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>August 30, 2011</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>September 29, 2010</firstreceived_date>
  <keyword>Immunodeficiency</keyword>
  <keyword>DOCK8</keyword>
  <keyword>LAD-1</keyword>
  <keyword>MonoMAC</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Immunologic Deficiency Syndromes</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
</clinical_study>
