<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="263">
  <!-- This xml conforms to:  http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>Information obtained from ClinicalTrials.gov on October 20, 2011</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01226940</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CDR0000687467</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-10-C-0219</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01226940</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Lenalidomide and Radiation Therapy in Treating Young Patients With Pontine Glioma or High-Grade Glioma</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I Trial of Lenalidomide and Radiotherapy in Children With Diffuse Intrinsic Pontine Gliomas and High-Grade Gliomas</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>NCI - Pediatric Oncology Branch</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Unspecified</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      RATIONALE: Lenalidomide, may stop the growth of gliomas by blocking blood flow to the tumor.
      Radiation therapy uses high-energy x-rays to kill tumor cells. Giving lenalidomide together
      with radiation therapy may kill more tumor cells.

      PURPOSE: This phase I trial is studying side effects and best dose of lenalidomide when
      given together with radiation therapy in treating young patients with pontine glioma or
      high-grade glioma.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      OBJECTIVES:

      Primary

        -  To determine the tolerability and toxicity profile of oral lenalidomide when
           administered to children with newly diagnosed HGG and DIPG with concurrent radiation at
           doses up to 116 mg/m^2/day.

        -  To evaluate long-term tolerability of lenalidomide in children with newly diagnosed HGG
           and DIPG.

      Secondary

        -  To evaluate MRI sequences for noninvasive monitoring of metabolic and biologic changes
           in malignant brain tumors with therapy.

        -  To estimate 6-month and 12-month PFS and OS in this patient population.

        -  To determine if angiogenic and/or immunomodulatory biomarkers in the blood and urine
           correlate with toxicity and disease response.

        -  To determine the rate of CNS metastatic disease in patients on antiangiogenic
           chemotherapy.

        -  To determine any correlation of steady-state pharmacokinetics of lenalidomide with time
           to progression, number and type of toxicities, and dose-limiting toxicities.

      OUTLINE: This is a dose-escalation study of lenalidomide.

        -  Radiation phase: Patients undergo radiotherapy 5 days per week for 6 weeks (for a total
           of 54-59.4 Gy) and receive oral lenalidomide once daily for 6 weeks.

        -  Maintenance phase: Beginning two weeks after completion of radiotherapy, patients
           receive oral lenalidomide once daily on days 1-21. Treatment repeats every 28 days for
           up to 24 courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.

      Blood and cerebrospinal fluid samples may be collected periodically for pharmacokinetic and
      biologic studies.

      After completion of study treatment, patients are followed up for 30 days and then every 3
      months for 2 years.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2010</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Masking:  Open Label, Primary Purpose:  Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum-tolerated dose of lenalidomide administered concurrently with radiotherapy</measure>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Long-term tolerability of lenalidomide (including the number of patients requiring 2 dose reductions, the number of patients requiring one dose reduction, the timing of the dose reductions, and specific toxicities [e.g., myelosuppression, myalgias, e ...</measure>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of steady-state pharmacokinetics</measure>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation of plasma steady-state concentration (and cerebrospinal fluid levels if available for other reasons) with toxicities (type and incidence), time to progression, and relapse</measure>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Brain and Central Nervous System Tumors</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>lenalidomide</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>laboratory biomarker analysis</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>pharmacological study</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>radiation therapy</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        DISEASE CHARACTERISTICS:

          -  Histological confirmation* of a high-grade malignant glioma is required; histologic
             diagnoses include, but are not limited to:

               -  Anaplastic astrocytoma

               -  Glioblastoma multiforme

          -  NOTE: Patients with DIPG are exempt from histologic verification if they have typical
             MRI findings of DIPG (i.e., hypo- or isointense on T1-weighted imaging, hyperintense
             on FLAIR or T2-weighted imaging, epicenter in the pons, &gt; 50% of pons involved) in
             the face of a typical clinical presentation.

          -  Inoperable tumor or residual disease after resection

               -  No patients with a HGG that was completely resected with good margins

          -  Patients identified as needing spinal radiation at diagnosis (e.g., spinal metastasis
             or malignant cells identified on CSF cytology) are excluded

        PATIENT CHARACTERISTICS:

          -  Patients should have a Karnofsky/Lansky score of greater than or equal to 60%

               -  Patients who require special assistance due to tumor-related paralysis, but who
                  are out of bed during the day, will be considered ambulatory for the purpose of
                  calculating the performance score

               -  Patients must be able to communicate any symptoms

          -  Absolute neutrophil count ≥ 1,000/mcL

          -  Platelets ≥ 100,000/mcL

          -  Total bilirubin &lt; 1.5 x upper limit of normal (ULN)

          -  AST (SGOT)/ALT (SGPT) ≤ 2.5 x institutional ULN

          -  Serum creatinine below age-adjusted maximum limits in the table below OR creatinine
             clearance ≥ 60 mL/min

               -  ≤ 0.8 mg/dL (for patients aged ≤ 5 years)

               -  ≤ 1.0 mg/dL (for patients aged 6 to ≤ 10 years)

               -  ≤ 1.2 mg/dL (for patients aged 11 to ≤ 15 years)

               -  ≤ 1.5 mg/dL (for patients aged &gt; 15 years)

          -  Not pregnant or nursing

          -  Negative pregnancy test

          -  Fertile female patients must use TWO reliable forms of contraception AT THE SAME TIME
             for ≥ 28 days before, during, and for ≥ 28 days after completion of study treatment

               -  The TWO methods of reliable contraception must include one highly effective
                  method (i.e., intrauterine device [IUD], hormonal [birth control pills,
                  injections, or implants], tubal ligation, or partner's vasectomy) and one
                  additional effective (barrier) method (i.e., latex condom, diaphragm, cervical
                  cap)

          -  Fertile male patients must use a latex condom during sexual contact with females of
             childbearing potential during and for ≥ 28 days after completion of study treatment
             even if he has undergone a successful vasectomy

          -  Able to swallow capsules whole

          -  No overt renal, hepatic, cardiac, or pulmonary disease

          -  Patients with a body surface area (BSA) ≤ 0.4 m^2 are excluded

          -  Patients with a known coagulation disorder are excluded

               -  Patients with a first-degree relative with a history of venous thrombosis before
                  age 50 yrs or an arterial thrombosis before age 40 yrs must have the following
                  testing performed prior to enrollment to exclude a heritable disorder:

                    -  PT, PTT, thrombin time, fibrinogen

                    -  Antithrombin

                    -  Protein C, protein S

                    -  Factor V Leiden

                    -  Prothrombin G20210A gene analysis

                    -  Fasting serum homocysteine

                    -  Lupus anticoagulant assays

                    -  Anticardiolipin level

                    -  LDL, HDL, triglycerides

               -  Patients with a suspected disorder will be excluded due to the potential
                  increased risk of thrombosis

          -  Patients who have had a thromboembolic event that is not line-related are excluded

          -  No patients with any significant medical illnesses that, in the investigator's
             opinion, cannot be adequately controlled with appropriate therapy, would compromise a
             patient's ability to tolerate this therapy, or result in inability to assess toxicity
             including, but not limited to:

               -  Uncontrolled intercurrent illness including ongoing or active infection

               -  Cardiac disease

               -  Renal impairment

               -  Psychiatric illness/social situations that would limit compliance with study
                  requirement

          -  Patients with a history of toxic epidermal necrolysis (TEN) or Stevens-Johnson
             syndrome are excluded

          -  No history of allergic reactions attributed to compounds of similar chemical or
             biologic composition to lenalidomide (i.e., thalidomide)

          -  No patients with known hypersensitivity to anhydrous lactose, microcrystalline
             cellulose, croscarmellose sodium, and magnesium stearate

          -  Known HIV-positive patients on combination antiretroviral therapy are ineligible

        PRIOR CONCURRENT THERAPY:

          -  See Disease Characteristics

          -  No prior chemotherapy or radiation therapy

          -  No patients receiving any other investigational agents
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>18 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Katherine Warren, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>NCI - Pediatric Oncology Branch</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>NCI - Pediatric Oncology Branch</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Katherine Warren, MD</last_name>
      <phone>301-435-4683</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://cancer.gov/clinicaltrials/NCI-10-C-0219</url>
    <description>Clinical trial summary from the National Cancer Institute's PDQ® database</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>October 2010</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>October 29, 2010</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 21, 2010</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Katherine Warren</name_title>
    <organization>NCI - Pediatric Oncology Branch</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>untreated childhood brain stem glioma</keyword>
  <keyword>childhood high-grade cerebellar astrocytoma</keyword>
  <keyword>childhood high-grade cerebral astrocytoma</keyword>
  <keyword>childhood mixed glioma</keyword>
  <keyword>childhood oligodendroglioma</keyword>
  <keyword>untreated childhood subependymal giant cell astrocytoma</keyword>
  <keyword>untreated childhood visual pathway and hypothalamic glioma</keyword>
  <keyword>untreated childhood visual pathway glioma</keyword>
  <keyword>childhood choroid plexus tumor</keyword>
  <keyword>childhood infratentorial ependymoma</keyword>
  <keyword>childhood supratentorial ependymoma</keyword>
  <keyword>newly diagnosed childhood ependymoma</keyword>
  <keyword>childhood grade III meningioma</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Glioma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Nervous System Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Central Nervous System Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pontine Glioma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lenalidomide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Thalidomide</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
</clinical_study>
