<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="206">
  <!-- This xml conforms to:  http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>Information obtained from ClinicalTrials.gov on October 20, 2011</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01220531</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Pro00025966</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2R01AI047040-11A2</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>5K12HD043494-09</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01220531</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Thymus Transplantation Safety-Efficacy</brief_title>
  <official_title>Safety and Efficacy of Thymus Transplantation in Complete DiGeorge Anomaly, IND#9836</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Duke University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institutes of Health (NIH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health and Human Development (NICHD)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Duke University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Complete DiGeorge anomaly (cDGA) is a disorder in which there is no thymus function.  With
      no thymus function, bone marrow stem cells do not develop into T cells, which fight
      infection.  Complete DiGeorge anomaly patients cannot fight infection and are
      immunodeficient. Without successful treatment, complete DiGeorge patients usually die by age
      2 years.

      Thymus transplantation with and without immunosuppression (drugs given before and after
      transplantation) has resulted in the development good T cell function in complete DiGeorge
      anomaly subjects.

      This Phase I/II study continues thymus transplantation safety and efficacy research for the
      treatment of complete DiGeorge anomaly.  Eligible participants undergo thymus
      transplantation and biopsy.  Immune function testing is continued for one year
      post-transplantation.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Complete DiGeorge anomaly (cDGA) is a congenital disorder characterized by athymia. Without
      successful treatment, children remain immunodeficient and usually die by age 2 years.  In
      complete DiGeorge subjects, thymus transplantation with and without immunosuppression has
      resulted in diverse T cell development and good T cell function. The purpose of this Phase
      I/II study is to continue thymus transplantation safety and efficacy research for the
      treatment of complete DiGeorge anomaly.  Until thymus transplantation is FDA approved as
      standard care for DiGeorge anomaly, research study participation is the only means by which
      a patient may have access to this potentially life-saving procedure.

      This protocol includes 4 groups: one for subjects who do not require immunosuppression; and
      3 immunosuppression groups for subjects with different T cell function levels to be
      suppressed adequately.

      Eligible subjects undergo thymus transplantation and an allograft biopsy. Protocol specified
      studies continue until approximately one year post-transplantation.

      Study participation lasts two years.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation:  Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification:  Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model:  Parallel Assignment, Masking:  Open Label, Primary Purpose:  Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Survival</measure>
    <time_frame>One-year post-transplantation</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Assess Survival at One Year Post Thymus Transplantation. The primary hypothesis is that greater than 50% of subjects will survive thymus transplantation.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Descriptive Study - Immune Outcomes</measure>
    <time_frame>6 Months &amp; 1 Year Post-Transplantation</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Total CD3, CD4, CD8, naïve CD8 TCRαβ, TCRγδ, total B cells and total NK cells at 6 months and 12 months post-transplantation.
TCR repertoire as assessed by flow cytometry 12 months post-transplantation.
PHA response to CD3 and tetanus toxoid at 12 months post-transplantation.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Naive CD 4 T Cell Count</measure>
    <time_frame>One Year Post-Transplantation</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Assess total naïve T cell count at 12 months post-thymus transplantation. The hypothesis is that greater than 50% of subjects will have &gt;100 naïve T cells at one year post-transplantation.  An additional hypothesis is that the dose of thymus tissue transplanted will affect the naïve CD4 count at one year.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Descriptive Study - GVHD</measure>
    <time_frame>1 Year Post-Transplantation</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Grade of skin GVHD in the first year post-transplantation.
Grades of upper &amp; lower intestinal GVHD in the first year post-transplantation.
Grade of liver GVHD in the first year post-transplantation.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Descriptive Study - Infections</measure>
    <time_frame>1 Year Post-Transplantation</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Recording and tabulation of infections during the first 12 months post-transplantation including the organism, infection site, and severity.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Descriptive Study - Autoimmune Disease</measure>
    <time_frame>1 Year Post-Transplantation</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Autoimmune disease will be recorded and tabulated in first year post-transplantation.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Descriptive Study - Persistent Rashes</measure>
    <time_frame>1 Year Post-Transplantation</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Description and location of any rashes persisting over 2 weeks will be recorded.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Descriptive Study - Thymus Donor T Cell Presence</measure>
    <time_frame>3 Months Post-Transplantation</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Tabulate the presence of donor T cells in the blood 3 months post-transplantation.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Descriptive Study - Other Adverse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>1 Year Post-Transplantation</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Other adverse events possibly, probably and/or definitely transplant-related will be recorded and tabulated.
For any cancer, the type of cancer, location and genetic identity.
For any granuloma, the location and description.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Complete DiGeorge Anomaly</condition>
  <condition>DiGeorge Syndrome</condition>
  <condition>DiGeorge Anomaly</condition>
  <condition>Complete DiGeorge Syndrome</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>#1: Typical cDGA No Immunosuppression</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects do not receive any pre or post-transplantation immunosuppression.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>#2:Typ &amp; Atyp cDGA Immunosuppression</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Group two will receive three doses of 2 mg/kg of rabbit anti-thymocyte globulin IV pre transplantation.
Medications (diphenhydramine, steroids, and acetaminophen) are given with rabbit anti-thymocyte globulin.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>#3: Atypical cDGA Immunosuppression</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Pre-transplant cyclosporine (Csa) as soon as complete DiGeorge anomaly is diagnosed. Csa continued with target trough levels of 180 to 220 ng/ml. When trough levels are outside of range, dosing is modified appropriately.  If subject cannot tolerate Csa, Csa may be changed to tacrolimus (FK506) with target trough level 7 to 10 ng/ml. When trough levels are outside of this target range, dosing will be modified appropriately. Pre-transplant steroids are used for atypical subjects if pre-transplant T cells &gt;4,000/mm3. Three doses of 2 mg/kg of rabbit anti-thymocyte globulin IV are given pre-transplantation. Medications (diphenhydramine, steroids, and acetaminophen) are given with rabbit anti-thymocyte globulin.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>#4: Atypical cDGA Additional Suppression</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Pre-transplant cyclosporine (Csa) and steroids are started after atypical complete DiGeorge anomaly is diagnosed.  After PHA response is documented &gt;40,000 cpm on suppression, peri-transplant Csa is maintained at target levels 250 to 300 ng/ml. (When levels outside of range, dose modified.) If subject cannot tolerate Csa then may be changed to tacrolimus (FK506) with target level 10 to 15 ng/ml. When levels are outside of range, dosing is modified. Three doses of 2 mg/kg rabbit anti-thymocyte globulin IV are given pre-transplantation. Medications (diphenhydramine, steroids, and acetaminophen) are given with rabbit anti-thymocyte globulin.  Additional immunosuppression: Basiliximab, 5 mg/kg single dose IV Mycophenylate Mofetil (MMF), 15 mg/kg/dose every 8 hours IV or enteral.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Thymus Transplantation</intervention_name>
    <description>Potential thymus recipient subjects are screened for eligibility.  Thymus tissue (unrelated donor), donor, &amp; donor's mother screened for safety.  Group 1 does not receive any immunosuppression. Groups 2, 3, and 4 receive pre-transplantation immunosuppression.  Thymus transplantation is done under general anesthesia in the operating room.  Thymus tissue is transplanted into the subject's quadriceps. Two to three months post-transplantation, if medically stable, the subject undergoes allograft biopsy. At the time of transplantation and biopsy, skin biopsy conducted.  For Groups 2, 3, 4, immunosuppression is weaned per protocol.  Subjects undergo laboratory testing for approximately one year post-transplantation.  At year 2 post-transplantation, subjects are contacted for data collection.</description>
    <arm_group_label>#1: Typical cDGA No Immunosuppression</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>#2:Typ &amp; Atyp cDGA Immunosuppression</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>#3: Atypical cDGA Immunosuppression</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>#4: Atypical cDGA Additional Suppression</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>IND 9836</other_name>
    <other_name>Thymus Tissue Transplant</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Blood Draw</intervention_name>
    <description>Biological Mothers of Thymus Recipients are asked to participate in the study and undergo phlebotomy to allow for testing of T cell identity in the complete DiGeorge subjects. If blood is not obtainable, then a buccal swab may be done.</description>
    <arm_group_label>#1: Typical cDGA No Immunosuppression</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>#2:Typ &amp; Atyp cDGA Immunosuppression</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>#3: Atypical cDGA Immunosuppression</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>#4: Atypical cDGA Additional Suppression</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Venipuncture</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Transplant Inclusion:

          -  Must have 1 of following: 22q11 or 10p13 hemizygosity; hypocalcemia requiring
             replacement; congenital heart disease; CHARGE association or CHD7 mutation

          -  Complete DiGeorge: &lt;50 CD3+ T cells/cumm or &lt;50 CD3+ T cells/cumm that are CD62L+
             CD45RA+, or &lt;5% of CD3+ cells are CD62L+ CD45RA+

          -  Atypical DiGeorge must have, or have had, a rash.

        Group 1

        •Typical cDGA whose T cells have a PHA response &lt; 5,000 cpm and &lt; 20 fold PHA response.

        Group 2

        •Typical cDGA whose T cells have a PHA response &gt;5,000 cpm and &lt;50,000 cpm and &gt;20 fold
        PHA response

        Group 3

          -  Typical cDGA whose T cells have PHA response &gt;50,000 cpm

          -  Typical cDGA with maternal engraftment

          -  Atypical cDGA whose T cells have PHA response &lt;40,000 cpm when on immunosuppression
             or &lt;75,000 cpm to PHA when not on immunosuppression

          -  Atypical cDGA with group 3 PHA response &amp; maternal engraftment

        Group 4

          -  Atypical cDGA with PHA responses &gt;75,000cpm while on no immunosuppression or PHA
             responses &gt;40,000cpm while on immunosuppression

          -  Atypical cDGA with maternal engraftment and group 4 PHA response

        Transplant Exclusion:

          -  Heart surgery &lt;4 wks pre-transplantation

          -  Heart surgery anticipated w/in 3 months after proposed transplantation

          -  Rejection by surgeon or anesthesiologist as surgical candidate

          -  Lack of sufficient muscle tissue to accept transplant of 4 grams/m2 body surface area

          -  HIV infection

          -  Prior attempts at immune reconstitution, such as bone marrow transplant or previous
             thymus transplant

          -  CMV on 2 tests for Groups 2, 3, and 4

        Biological Mother Inclusion/Exclusion:

        • Must be biological mother of thymus recipient
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>M. Louise Markert, M.D., Ph.D</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Duke University Medical Center, Pediatrics, Allergy &amp; Immunology</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>M. Louise Markert, M.D., Ph.D</last_name>
    <phone>919-684-6263</phone>
    <email>marke001@mc.duke.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Elizabeth A. McCarthy, R.N., M.S.N.</last_name>
    <phone>919-684-6828</phone>
    <email>mccar006@mc.duke.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Duke University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Durham</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27701</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>M. Louise Markert, M.D., Ph.D</last_name>
      <phone>919-684-6263</phone>
      <email>marke001@mc.duke.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>M. Louise Markert, M.D., Ph.D</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Markert ML, Devlin BH, Alexieff MJ, Li J, McCarthy EA, Gupton SE, Chinn IK, Hale LP, Kepler TB, He M, Sarzotti M, Skinner MA, Rice HE, Hoehner JC. Review of 54 patients with complete DiGeorge anomaly enrolled in protocols for thymus transplantation: outcome of 44 consecutive transplants. Blood. 2007 May 15;109(10):4539-47. Epub 2007 Feb 6.</citation>
    <PMID>17284531</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Markert ML, Devlin BH, McCarthy EA. Thymus transplantation. Clin Immunol. 2010 May;135(2):236-46. Epub 2010 Mar 16. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20236866</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Markert ML, Devlin BH, Chinn IK, McCarthy EA, Li YJ. Factors affecting success of thymus transplantation for complete DiGeorge anomaly. Am J Transplant. 2008 Aug;8(8):1729-36. Epub 2008 Jun 28.</citation>
    <PMID>18557726</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Markert ML, Alexieff MJ, Li J, Sarzotti M, Ozaki DA, Devlin BH, Sedlak DA, Sempowski GD, Hale LP, Rice HE, Mahaffey SM, Skinner MA. Postnatal thymus transplantation with immunosuppression as treatment for DiGeorge syndrome. Blood. 2004 Oct 15;104(8):2574-81. Epub 2004 Apr 20.</citation>
    <PMID>15100156</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Selim MA, Markert ML, Burchette JL, Herman CM, Turner JW. The cutaneous manifestations of atypical complete DiGeorge syndrome: a histopathologic and immunohistochemical study. J Cutan Pathol. 2008 Apr;35(4):380-5.</citation>
    <PMID>18333898</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chinn IK, Devlin BH, Li YJ, Markert ML. Long-term tolerance to allogeneic thymus transplants in complete DiGeorge anomaly. Clin Immunol. 2008 Mar;126(3):277-81. Epub 2007 Dec 26.</citation>
    <PMID>18155964</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Markert ML, Li J, Devlin BH, Hoehner JC, Rice HE, Skinner MA, Li YJ, Hale LP. Use of allograft biopsies to assess thymopoiesis after thymus transplantation. J Immunol. 2008 May 1;180(9):6354-64.</citation>
    <PMID>18424759</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hudson LL, Louise Markert M, Devlin BH, Haynes BF, Sempowski GD. Human T cell reconstitution in DiGeorge syndrome and HIV-1 infection. Semin Immunol. 2007 Oct;19(5):297-309. Epub 2007 Nov 26. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18035553</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Markert ML, Devlin BH, Chinn IK, McCarthy EA. Thymus transplantation in complete DiGeorge anomaly. Immunol Res. 2009;44(1-3):61-70.</citation>
    <PMID>19066739</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Markert ML, Alexieff MJ, Li J, Sarzotti M, Ozaki DA, Devlin BH, Sempowski GD, Rhein ME, Szabolcs P, Hale LP, Buckley RH, Coyne KE, Rice HE, Mahaffey SM, Skinner MA. Complete DiGeorge syndrome: development of rash, lymphadenopathy, and oligoclonal T cells in 5 cases. J Allergy Clin Immunol. 2004 Apr;113(4):734-41.</citation>
    <PMID>15100681</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Markert ML, Sarzotti M, Ozaki DA, Sempowski GD, Rhein ME, Hale LP, Le Deist F, Alexieff MJ, Li J, Hauser ER, Haynes BF, Rice HE, Skinner MA, Mahaffey SM, Jaggers J, Stein LD, Mill MR. Thymus transplantation in complete DiGeorge syndrome: immunologic and safety evaluations in 12 patients. Blood. 2003 Aug 1;102(3):1121-30. Epub 2003 Apr 17.</citation>
    <PMID>12702512</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2011</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>July 28, 2011</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>September 22, 2010</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>M. Louise Markert, MD, PhD, Associate Professor</name_title>
    <organization>Duke University Medical Center, Pediatric Allergy &amp; Immunology</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>DiGeorge Anomaly</keyword>
  <keyword>Thymus Transplantation</keyword>
  <keyword>DiGeorge Syndrome</keyword>
  <keyword>Athymia</keyword>
  <keyword>Low T cell numbers</keyword>
  <keyword>Immunoreconstitution</keyword>
  <keyword>Immunodeficiency</keyword>
  <keyword>Complete DiGeorge</keyword>
  <keyword>Typical DiGeorge</keyword>
  <keyword>Atypical DiGeorge</keyword>
  <keyword>Complete DiGeorge Anomaly</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Congenital Abnormalities</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>DiGeorge Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Chromosome Deletion</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
</clinical_study>
