<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="175">
  <!-- This xml conforms to:  http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>Information obtained from ClinicalTrials.gov on October 20, 2011</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01207076</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2010LS030</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01207076</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>AHN-12 Biodistribution in Advanced Leukemia</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase I Open Label, Single Arm, Dose Escalation Trial to Evaluate the Biodistribution and Safety of AHN-12 In Patients With Advanced Leukemia HM2010-05</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Masonic Cancer Center, University of Minnesota</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Masonic Cancer Center, University of Minnesota</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is a single institution phase I study for the treatment of patients with relapsed
      or refractory leukemia aged 12 years and older.  All patients must test negative for the
      human anti-mouse antibody (HAMA) and remain negative after each infusion to continue on
      study.  In addition, a source of allogeneic stem cells (sibling, unrelated donor or cord)
      must have been identified in event of severe myelosuppression.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      A dose escalation schema will be used with the initial patient receiving the current lowest
      dose of nonradiolabeled AHN-12 (from 0.20 mg/kg to 1.0 mg/kg).

      If a favorable biodistribution is not achieved and the patient remains negative for HAMA,
      the infusion may be repeated up to two more times (with a one level increase in
      nonradiolabeled AHN-12 each time) in an attempt of achieving favorable biodistribution.

      If favorable biodistribution is achieved, the patient will receive 90Y-AHN-12 in a dose
      escalated schema in cohorts of 3 patients to determine maximum tolerated dose (MTD) and
      dose-limiting toxicity.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Suspended</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Reviewing current processes to optimize dosimetry.
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>May 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation:  Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification:  Bio-availability Study, Intervention Model:  Single Group Assignment, Masking:  Open Label, Primary Purpose:  Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Optimal Dose of AHN-12 Non-radiolabeled Antibody</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 2</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>doses of nonradiolabeled antibody are specified: 0.20, 0.40, 0.60, 0.80 and 1.00 mg/kg.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum Tolerated Dose (MTD) of 90Y-AHN-12</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 14 days of achieving favorable biodistribution</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>•Determine the MTD of 90Y-AHN-12 for patients with a favorable biodistribution and a negative human anti-mouse antibody (HAMA). Doses of radiolabeled antibody are specified starting dose level with dose increment of 2 gray (Gy) to maximum of 22 Gy.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Human Anti-Mouse Antibody (HAMA) Response</measure>
    <time_frame>30 and 90 Days Post Therapy, Then Every 6 Months If Positive</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Event is whether or not the patient develops a HAMA response.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Anti-tumor Activity of 90Y-AHN-12</measure>
    <time_frame>30 and 90 Days Post Therapy</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Event is response to therapy: complete remission, partial remission, refractory or relapsed disease.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Acute Myelogenous Leukemia</condition>
  <condition>Myelodysplastic Syndrome</condition>
  <condition>Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia</condition>
  <condition>Chronic Myelogenous Leukemia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>AHN-12 Treated Patients</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receiving nonradiolabeled AHN-12 (.20 mg/kg to 1.0 mg/kg) of at least one dose and up to a total of 3 dosimetry infusions (intervals no sooner than 8 days and up to 21 days).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>90Y-AHN-12</intervention_name>
    <description>A dose escalation schema will be used with the initial patient receiving the current lowest dose of nonradiolabeled AHN-12.  If a favorable biodistribution is not achieved and the patient remains negative for HAMA, the infusion may be repeated up to two more times (with a one level increase in nonradiolabeled AHN-12 each time) in an attempt of achieving favorable biodistribution.
Dose escalation of nonradiolabeled AHN-12:
Dose level 1 0.20 mg/kg, Dose level 2 0.40 mg/kg, Dose level 3 0.60 mg/kg, Dose level 4 0.80 mg/kg, Dose level 5 1.00 mg/kg, to two more times (with a one level increase in nonradiolabeled AHN-12 each time) in an attempt of achieving favorable biodistribution.</description>
    <arm_group_label>AHN-12 Treated Patients</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients must have one of the following histologically confirmed CD45+ diseases.  If
             possible, AHN-12 positivity will be confirmed by flow cytometry on a recent bone
             marrow or a peripheral blood sample, if circulating blasts are present.  Peripheral
             leukemic blasts must be &lt;10,000/uL at time of enrollment; however, hydroxyurea may be
             given to control the peripheral blast count.

               -  Acute myelogenous leukemia (AML), primary refractory or relapsed disease -
                  Primary refractory disease is defined as persistent disease following a minimum
                  of two different standard chemotherapy induction attempts at time of diagnosis.
                  At time of relapse, patients must have failed one salvage chemotherapy regimen.

               -  Refractory myelodysplastic syndrome (MDS) - defined as persistent disease
                  following a minimum of one standard chemotherapy induction attempt.

               -  AML arising from pre-existing MDS, refractory - defined as persistent disease
                  following a minimum of one standard chemotherapy induction attempt.

               -  Acute lymphoblastic leukemia (ALL), primary refractory or relapsed disease -
                  Primary refractory disease is defined as persistent disease following a minimum
                  of two different standard chemotherapy induction attempts at time of diagnosis.
                  At time of relapse, patients must have failed one salvage chemotherapy regimen.

               -  Chronic myelogenous leukemia (CML) following blast crisis -  defined as
                  persistent accelerated phase or blast phase of disease following a minimum of
                  one standard chemotherapy induction attempt.

          -  Age ≥ 12 years Because these are investigational new agents and have never before
             been used in humans, children less than 12 years of age are not eligible for this
             phase I protocol but will be eligible for future pediatric phase I trials.

          -  Karnofsky Performance Status ≥ 60% (16 years and older) or Lansky Play Score ≥ 60
             (&lt;16 years)

          -  Life expectancy of &gt; 12 weeks in the opinion of the enrolling medical provider

          -  Patients must have normal organ function as defined below within 14 days of first
             AHN-12 infusion:

               -  Total bilirubin, aspartate aminotransferase (AST) and alanine aminotransferase
                  (ALT)  ≤ 2.5 X upper limit of normal

               -  Creatinine ≤ 1.3 mg/dl OR estimated glomerular filtration rate (GFR) ≥ 60 mL/min

          -  Baseline left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF ≥ 45% by Multi Gated Acquisition
             Scan (MUGA)/ECHO (echocardiogram)

          -  Baseline Carbon Monoxide Diffusing Capacity (DLCO) (corrected) ≥ 50% of predicted.

          -  Human anti-mouse antibody (HAMA) must be negative (perform on all patients regardless
             of prior therapies).

          -  Consent to adequate contraception.  The effects of 90Y-AHN-12 on the developing fetus
             are unknown.   For this reason and because other therapeutic agents used in this
             trial are known to be teratogenic, women of child-bearing potential and men must
             agree to use adequate contraception (hormonal or barrier method of birth control;
             abstinence) prior to study entry and for the duration of study participation.  Should
             a woman become pregnant or suspect she is pregnant while participating in this study,
             she should inform her treating physician immediately.

          -  Source of allogeneic stem cells must have been identified in event of severe
             myelosuppression

          -  Able to give written consent.

          -  Both men and women of all ethnic groups are eligible for this trial.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Ongoing grade 2 or greater non-hematologic toxicity due to previously administered
             therapies

          -  &lt; 8 days from completion of therapy with any biologic agent

          -  Receiving any investigational agents

          -  Active central nervous system (CNS) leukemia are excluded from this clinical trial
             because of their poor prognosis and because they often develop progressive neurologic
             dysfunction that would confound the evaluation of neurologic and other adverse
             events.  If CNS disease is clinically suspected, patients should have a lumbar
             puncture and/or appropriate radiographic studies performed to determine CNS status
             and study eligibility.  Patients who have had their CNS disease treated and the
             cerebral spinal fluid (CSF) has been cleared of disease are eligible.

          -  History of allergic reactions attributed to compounds of similar chemical or biologic
             composition to 90Y-AHN-12 or other agents used in study.

          -  Uncontrolled illness including, but not limited to, uncontrolled infection,
             symptomatic congestive heart failure, unstable angina pectoris, cardiac arrhythmia,
             or psychiatric illness/social situations that would limit compliance with study
             requirements in the opinion of the enrolling medical provider.

          -  Pregnant and breastfeeding women are excluded from this study because 90Y-AHN-12,
             being radioactive, as well as high dose chemotherapy and total body irradiation (TBI)
             have the potential for teratogenic or abortifacient effects.  Because there is an
             unknown but potential risk for adverse events in nursing infants secondary to
             treatment of the mother with 90Y-AHN-12, breastfeeding should be discontinued if the
             mother is treated with 90Y-AHN-12.  These potential risks may also apply to other
             agents used in this study.

          -  Human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) positive patients: HIV positive patients are
             excluded from this study since: a) HIV-positive patients with immune deficiency are
             at increased risk of lethal infections when treated with marrow-suppressive therapy,
             and b) HIV-positive patients receiving combination anti-retroviral therapy may
             develop pharmacokinetic interactions with 90Y-AHN-12 or other agents administered
             during the study.

          -  &lt; 60 days since an autologous transplant

          -  Bone marrow cellularity &lt;5% (because of concern of myelosuppression)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>12 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Linda Burns, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Masonic Cancer Center, University of Minnesota</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Masonic Cancer Center, University of Minnesota</name>
      <address>
        <city>Minneapolis</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55455</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2011</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>October 3, 2011</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>September 21, 2010</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>CD45+ disease</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Leukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Lymphoid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Precursor Cell Lymphoblastic Leukemia-Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myeloid, Acute</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myeloid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myelogenous, Chronic, BCR-ABL Positive</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myelodysplastic Syndromes</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Preleukemia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
</clinical_study>
