<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="265">
  <!-- This xml conforms to:  http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>Information obtained from ClinicalTrials.gov on October 20, 2011</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01236560</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CDR0000688443</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>COG-ACNS0822</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01236560</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Vorinostat, Temozolomide, or Bevacizumab in Combination With Radiation Therapy Followed by Bevacizumab and Temozolomide in Young Patients With Newly Diagnosed High-Grade Glioma</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized Phase II/III Study of Vorinostat (IND# 71976) and Local Irradiation OR Temozolomide and Local Irradiation OR Bevacizumab (IND# 7921) and Local Irradiation Followed by Maintenance Bevacizumab and Temozolomide in Children With Newly Diagnosed High-Grade Gliomas</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Children's Oncology Group</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      RATIONALE: Vorinostat may stop the growth of tumor cells by blocking some of the enzymes
      needed for cell growth. Drugs used in chemotherapy, such as temozolomide, work in different
      ways to stop the growth of tumor cells, either by killing the cells or by stopping them from
      dividing. Monoclonal antibodies, such as bevacizumab, can block tumor growth in different
      ways. Some block the ability of tumor cells to grow and spread. Others find tumor cells and
      help kill them or carry tumor-killing substances to them. Radiation therapy uses high-energy
      x-rays to kill tumor cells. It is not yet known whether giving vorinostat is more effective
      then temozolomide or bevacizumab when given together with radiation therapy in treating
      glioma.

      PURPOSE: This randomized phase II/III trial is studying vorinostat, temozolomide, or
      bevacizumab to see how well they work compared with each other when given together with
      radiation therapy followed by bevacizumab and temozolomide in treating young patients with
      newly diagnosed high-grade glioma.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      OBJECTIVES:

      Primary

        -  To identify the dose of vorinostat that is feasible when given in combination with
           radiotherapy (RT) in patients with newly diagnosed high-grade gliomas (HGG). (completed
           as of Amendment #1)

        -  To compare 1-year event-free survival of patients with newly diagnosed HGG treated with
           vorinostat (using MTD) versus bevacizumab versus temozolomide when given in combination
           with RT followed by maintenance therapy with bevacizumab and temozolomide. (Phase II)

        -  To compare the event-free survival of patients with newly diagnosed HGG treated with
           the superior chemoradiotherapy (from phase II portion) versus temozolomide given in
           combination with RT followed by maintenance chemotherapy with bevacizumab and
           temozolomide. (Phase III)

      Secondary

        -  To evaluate the anti-tumor activity, as measured by event-free survival (EFS),
           progression-free survival (PFS), and overall survival (OS), of patients with newly
           diagnosed HGG treated with vorinostat, bevacizumab, or temozolomide when given in
           combination with RT followed by maintenance chemotherapy with bevacizumab and
           temozolomide.

        -  To define and evaluate the toxicities of each of the treatment arms of the study.

        -  To conduct gene expression profiling and SNP arrays in patients with newly diagnosed
           HGG.

        -  To assess telomerase activity, hTert expression, and telomere length in patients with
           newly diagnosed HGG.

        -  To document changes in perfusion and diffusion using MR imaging at baseline, prior to,
           during (prior to course 3), and after maintenance therapy with bevacizumab and
           temozolomide.

        -  To correlate functional changes in tumor with responses to bevacizumab treatment using
           MR diffusion/perfusion imaging.

        -  To correlate the results of the bevacizumab biology studies in serum or tumor with EFS.

        -  To explore the prognostic significance of MGMT status for patients newly diagnosed with
           HGG treated with combined surgery, radiation, chemotherapy, and anti-angiogenic
           therapy.

      OUTLINE: This is a multicenter, feasibility, dose-escalation study of vorinostat, followed
      by a phase II study, followed by a phase III study.

        -  Feasibility study (completed as of Amendment #1): Patients undergo 3-D conformal
           radiotherapy (RT) or intensity-modulated RT 5 days a week for 6 weeks. Patients also
           receive oral vorinostat once daily on days 1-5. Courses repeat every week for 6 weeks
           in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.

             -  Maintenance therapy: Beginning 4 weeks after completion of chemoradiotherapy,
                patients receive bevacizumab IV over 30-90 minutes on days 1 and 15 and oral
                temozolomide on days 1-5. Treatment repeats every 28 days for 12 courses in the
                absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.

        -  Phase II study: Patients are stratified according to extent of resection (near total
           resection or gross total resection vs other) and histology (glioblastoma multiforme vs
           other). Patients are randomized to 1 of 3 treatment arms.

             -  Arm I: Patients undergo RT 5 days a week for 6 weeks and receive vorinostat at the
                maximum-tolerated dose determined in the feasibility study.

             -  Arm II: Patients undergo RT as in arm I and receive oral temozolomide once daily
                for 42 days beginning on day 5 of RT.

             -  Arm III: Patients undergo RT as in arm I and receive bevacizumab IV over 30-90
                minutes on days 22 and 36.

      Patients in all arms receive maintenance therapy as in the feasibility study.

        -  Phase III study: Patients are randomized to 1 of 2 treatment arms.

             -  Arm IV: Patients receive RT and temozolomide as in phase II, arm II.

             -  Arm V: Patients receive treatment as in phase II, arm I or phase II, arm III,
                whichever was established as the superior chemoradiotherapy arm in phase II.

      Patients in all arms receive maintenance therapy as in the feasibility study.

      Some patients undergo blood and tumor tissue sample (from surgery) collection for telomerase
      activity, hTert expression, telomere length, and gene expression profiling and SNP arrays
      analysis.

      After completion of study therapy, patients are followed up every 3 months for 1 year, every
      6 months for 4 years, and then annually for 5 years.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Suspended</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2010</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2/Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation:  Randomized, Masking:  Open Label, Primary Purpose:  Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Dose-limiting toxicity of vorinostat when given with radiotherapy (feasibility study)</measure>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Toxicity of vorinostat, bevacizumab, or temozolomide when given in combination with radiotherapy</measure>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Event-free survival of patients in each treatment arm</measure>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival of patients in each treatment arm</measure>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-free survival of patients in each treatment arm</measure>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>5</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">268</enrollment>
  <condition>Brain and Central Nervous System Tumors</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm I</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients undergo RT 5 days a week for 6 weeks and receive vorinostat at the maximum-tolerated dose   determined in the  feasibility study.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm II</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients undergo RT as in arm I and  receive oral temozolomide once daily for 42 days beginning on day 5 of RT.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm III</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients undergo RT as in arm I and receive bevacizumab IV over 30-90 minutes on days 22 and 36.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm IV</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive RT and temozolomide as in phase II, arm II.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm V</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive treatment as in phase II, arm I or phase II, arm III, whichever was established as the superior chemoradiotherapy arm in phase II.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>bevacizumab</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm III</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm V</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>temozolomide</intervention_name>
    <description>Given orally</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm II</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm IV</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>vorinostat</intervention_name>
    <description>Given orally</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm I</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm V</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        DISEASE CHARACTERISTICS:

          -  Newly diagnosed high-grade glioma

               -  Anaplastic astrocytoma

               -  Glioblastoma multiforme

               -  Gliosarcoma

               -  Primary spinal cord malignant glioma allowed

               -  No oligodendroglioma or oligoastrocytoma

          -  Patient must have histological verification of diagnosis

               -  No M+ disease ( defined as evidence of neuraxis dissemination)

               -  No positive CSF cytology

        PATIENT CHARACTERISTICS:

          -  ECOG performance status (PS) 0-2

               -  Karnofsky PS 50-100% (patients &gt; 16 years of age)

               -  Lansky PS 50-100% (patients ≤ 16 years of age)

          -  ANC ≥ 1,000/μL

          -  Platelet count ≥ 100,000/μL

          -  Hemoglobin ≥ 8.0 mg/dL (transfusion independent)

          -  Creatinine clearance or radioisotope GFR ≥ 70 mL/min OR serum creatinine based on age
             and/or gender as follows:

               -  0.4 mg/dL (1 month to &lt; 6 months of age)

               -  0.5 mg/dL (6 months to &lt; 1 year of age)

               -  0.6 mg/dL (1 to &lt; 2 years of age)

               -  0.8 mg/dL (2 to &lt; 6 years of age)

               -  1.0 mg/dL (6 to &lt; 10 years of age)

               -  1.2 mg/dL (10 to &lt; 13 years of age)

               -  1.5 mg/dL (male) or 1.4 mg/dL (female) (13 to &lt; 16 years of age)

               -  1.7 mg/dL (male) or 1.4 mg/dL (female) (≥ 16 years of age)

          -  Proteinuria &lt; 2+ OR urine:protein ratio (UPC) ≤ 0.5

               -  If UPC &gt; 0.5, a 24-hour urine protein should be obtained and level should be &lt;
                  1,000 mg of protein

          -  Total bilirubin ≤ 1.5 times upper limit of normal (ULN)

          -  ALT &lt; 2.5 times ULN

          -  Serum albumin ≥ 2 g/dL

          -  PT INR ≤ 1.5 times ULN

          -  Not pregnant or nursing

          -  Negative pregnancy test

          -  Fertile patients must use effective contraception during all study therapy and for ≥
             6 months after completion of bevacizumab

          -  Hypertension well controlled (≤ 95^th percentile for age and height if patient is ≤
             17 years) by stable doses of medication allowed

               -  For patients &gt; 17 years, systolic blood pressure (BP) ≤ 150 mm Hg or diastolic
                  BP ≤ 100 mm Hg)

          -  Seizure disorder allowed provided patient is well-controlled and on
             nonenzyme-inducing anticonvulsants

          -  No history of myocardial infarction, severe or unstable angina, clinically
             significant peripheral vascular disease, ≥ grade 2 heart failure, or serious and
             inadequately controlled cardiac arrhythmia

          -  No known bleeding diathesis or coagulopathy

          -  No prior arterial thromboembolic events, including transient ischemic attacks or
             cerebrovascular accidents

          -  No prior diagnosis of a deep venous thrombosis, including pulmonary embolism, and no
             known thrombophilic condition (e.g., protein S, protein C, antithrombin III
             deficiency, Factor V Leiden or Factor II G202`0A mutation, homocysteinemia, or
             antiphospholipid antibody syndrome)

          -  No history of an abdominal fistula, gastrointestinal perforation, or intra-abdominal
             abscess within the past 6 months

          -  No serious or non-healing wound, ulcer, or bone fracture

          -  No evidence of significant postoperative intracranial hemorrhage, defined as &gt; 1 cm
             of blood on postoperative MRI scan (potentially in addition to the postoperative
             scan) obtained within the past 14 days

          -  No history of allergic reaction to Chinese hamster ovary cell products or other
             recombinant human antibodies

        PRIOR CONCURRENT THERAPY:

          -  No more than 31 days since definitive surgery

          -  Must not have received any prior chemotherapy, radiotherapy, immunotherapy, or bone
             marrow transplant

          -  More than 7 days since major surgical procedure and recovered

               -  For patients scheduled to receive bevacizumab:

                    -  More than 28 days since major procedure

                    -  More than 14 days since intermediate procedure

                    -  More than 7 days since minor procedure (lumbar picture or placement of PICC
                       lines are not considered minor procedures)

          -  No other current anti-cancer agents

          -  No concurrent nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory medications known to inhibit platelet
             function or known to selectively inhibit cyclooxygenase activity

          -  No concurrent enzyme inducing anticonvulsants

          -  No concurrent HDAC inhibitors (e.g., valproic acid)

          -  No concurrent anticoagulants including systemic thrombolytic agents, heparin, low
             molecular weight heparins, or warfarin except as required to maintain patency of
             pre-existing permanent vascular catheters or for prevention of thrombosis in the
             post-operative period
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>3 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>21 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Maryam Fouladi, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Children's Hospital Medical Center, Cincinnati</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Arkansas Cancer Research Center at University of Arkansas for Medical Sciences</name>
      <address>
        <city>Little Rock</city>
        <state>Arkansas</state>
        <zip>72205</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Childrens Hospital Los Angeles</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90027</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Hospital Central California</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madera</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>93638-8762</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Hospital of Orange County</name>
      <address>
        <city>Orange</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92868</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Lucile Packard Children's Hospital at Stanford University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Palo Alto</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>95798</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UCSF Helen Diller Family Comprehensive Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Francisco</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94115</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Alfred I. duPont Hospital for Children</name>
      <address>
        <city>Wilmington</city>
        <state>Delaware</state>
        <zip>19803</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Lee Cancer Care of Lee Memorial Health System</name>
      <address>
        <city>Fort Myers</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33901</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Nemours Children's Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Jacksonville</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32207</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Miami Children's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Miami</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33155</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center at Orlando</name>
      <address>
        <city>Orlando</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32806</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Florida Hospital Cancer Institute at Florida Hospital Orlando</name>
      <address>
        <city>Orlando</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32803-1273</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Nemours Children's Clinic - Orlando</name>
      <address>
        <city>Orlando</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32806</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Nemours Children's Clinic - Pensacola</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pensacola</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32504</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>All Children's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint Petersburg</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33701</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>AFLAC Cancer Center and Blood Disorders Service of Children's Healthcare of Atlanta - Egleston Campus</name>
      <address>
        <city>Atlanta</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30322</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Curtis and Elizabeth Anderson Cancer Institute at Memorial Health University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Savannah</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>31403-3089</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Simmons Cooper Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Springfield</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>62794-9677</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Indiana University Melvin and Bren Simon Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Indianapolis</city>
        <state>Indiana</state>
        <zip>46202-5289</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Lucille P. Markey Cancer Center at University of Kentucky</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lexington</city>
        <state>Kentucky</state>
        <zip>40536-0093</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kosair Children's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Louisville</city>
        <state>Kentucky</state>
        <zip>40232</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sidney Kimmel Comprehensive Cancer Center at Johns Hopkins</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21231-2410</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Hospitals and Clinics of Minnesota - Minneapolis</name>
      <address>
        <city>Minneapolis</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55404</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Mississippi Cancer Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Jackson</city>
        <state>Mississippi</state>
        <zip>39216-4505</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Siteman Cancer Center at Barnes-Jewish Hospital - Saint Louis</name>
      <address>
        <city>St. Louis</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>63110</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Overlook Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Morristown</city>
        <state>New Jersey</state>
        <zip>07962</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>SUNY Upstate Medical University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Syracuse</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>13210</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Lineberger Comprehensive Cancer Center at University of North Carolina - Chapel Hill</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chapel Hill</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27599-7295</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Blumenthal Cancer Center at Carolinas Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Charlotte</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>28232-2861</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CCOP - MeritCare Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Fargo</city>
        <state>North Dakota</state>
        <zip>58122</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Akron Children's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Akron</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>44308-1062</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cincinnati Children's Hospital Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cincinnati</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>45229-3039</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cleveland Clinic Taussig Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cleveland</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>44195</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Rainbow Babies and Children's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cleveland</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>44106-5000</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Dayton Children's - Dayton</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dayton</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>45404-1815</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Knight Cancer Institute at Oregon Health and Science University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Portland</city>
        <state>Oregon</state>
        <zip>97239-3098</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Penn State Children's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hershey</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>17033-0850</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Greenville Hospital Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Greenville</city>
        <state>South Carolina</state>
        <zip>29605</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sanford Cancer Center at Sanford USD Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sioux Falls</city>
        <state>South Dakota</state>
        <zip>57117-5039</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>East Tennessee Children's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Knoxville</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>37901</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>St. Jude Children's Research Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Memphis</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>38105</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CCOP - Scott and White Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Temple</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>76508</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Hospital and Regional Medical Center - Seattle</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seattle</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>98105</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>West Virginia University Health Sciences Center - Charleston</name>
      <address>
        <city>Charleston</city>
        <state>West Virginia</state>
        <zip>25302</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Midwest Children's Cancer Center at Children's Hospital of Wisconsin</name>
      <address>
        <city>Milwaukee</city>
        <state>Wisconsin</state>
        <zip>53226</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Princess Margaret Hospital for Children</name>
      <address>
        <city>Perth</city>
        <state>Western Australia</state>
        <zip>6001</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
    <country>Australia</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://cancer.gov/clinicaltrials/COG-ACNS0822</url>
    <description>Clinical trial summary from the National Cancer Institute's PDQ® database</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>October 2011</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>October 14, 2011</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 5, 2010</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Gregory H. Reaman</name_title>
    <organization>Children's Oncology Group - Group Chair Office</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>childhood high-grade cerebellar astrocytoma</keyword>
  <keyword>childhood high-grade cerebral astrocytoma</keyword>
  <keyword>untreated childhood brain stem glioma</keyword>
  <keyword>untreated childhood cerebral astrocytoma</keyword>
  <keyword>childhood spinal cord neoplasm</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Glioma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Nervous System Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Central Nervous System Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Temozolomide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dacarbazine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vorinostat</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Bevacizumab</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Antibodies, Monoclonal</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
</clinical_study>
