<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="79">
  <!-- This xml conforms to:  http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>Information obtained from ClinicalTrials.gov on October 20, 2011</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01239368</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>110016</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>11-C-0016</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01239368</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Th1/Tc1 Immunotherapy Following Stem Cell Transplantation in Multiple Myeloma</brief_title>
  <official_title>Multi-Center Phase I Study of Th1/Tc1 Immunotheraphy Following Autologous Hematopoietic Stem Cell Transplantation in High Risk Multiple Myeloma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Hackensack University Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      - Cancer development is associated with problems in immune system functions, which prevent
      the body from attacking and destroying the abnormal cells that lead to tumor growth.
      Research has suggested that certain white blood cells, known as Th1 and Th2 T cells, are
      affected in individuals with some kinds of cancer -- when the proportion of Th2 cells is
      greater than Th1 cells, the immune system's ability to fight off the growth of malignant
      tumors is weakened. Researchers are interested in determining if an infusion of specially
      modified Th1 cells, in addition to stem cell transplant, is a safe and effective treatment
      for individuals with forms of multiple myeloma that might not respond well to standard
      treatments alone.

      Objectives:

      - To determine the safety and effectiveness of the infusion of modified Th1 white blood
      cells, in conjunction with standard treatment, as a treatment for individuals who have been
      diagnosed with high-risk forms of multiple myeloma.

      Eligibility:

      - Individuals age 18 to 75 who have been newly diagnosed with high-risk multiple myeloma and
      who have received no or minimal treatment (4 months or less) yet..

      Design:

        -  Participants will be screened with a medical history, physical examination, blood and
           urine tests, and imaging studies. Some participants may also have a bone marrow or
           other type biopsy to evaluate the state of their disease.

        -  White blood cells will be collected from the participants through an apheresis
           procedure, which will collect and separate the white blood cells and return the rest of
           the blood to the participant.

        -  The collected cells will be grown and expanded under special conditions in the
           laboratory and stored frozen until participants receive all the standard of care
           treatment for multiple myeloma, including a stem cell transplant.

        -  Participants will receive an infusion of the modified Th1 cells a few weeks after the
           transplant, and will remain in the hospital for a few days after receiving the cells to
           monitor the possible immediate effects of the treatment.

        -  Participants will have regular follow-up visits to study the long-term effects of the
           modified Th1 cell infusion....
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background:

        -  Single or tandem autologous stem cell transplants (ASCT) are the standard of care for
           newly diagnosed Multiple Myeloma (MM) which, despite recent progress both with ASCT and
           the introduction of new drugs, continues to be mostly incurable. While
           non-myeloablative allogeneic transplant is being investigated with encouraging results,
           subjects who are not candidates are left without satisfactory therapeutic alternatives.

        -  A new investigational approach to MM treatment consists of adoptive autologous
           immunotherapy. Both pre-clinical and preliminary clinical data suggest that this
           approach can mediate both immune reconstitution and anti-tumor effects following ASCT.
           Potentially, it may be possible to harness such T cell-mediated effects without the
           need for myeloablative high-dose chemotherapy and ASCT.

        -  We will evaluate this new form of therapy using an anti-CD3, anti-CD28 co-stimulated
           autologous T cells ex vivo expansion in a short term (6 days) culture with high-dose
           rapamycin, a system found in murine models to generate Th1 / Tc1 polarized T cells
           (Th1.rapa cells) that are both rapamycin-resistant and apoptosis-resistant with a
           greatly increased in vivo survival.

        -  As Th1 /Tc1 polarized lymphocytes are pivotal in immune mediated tumor surveillance or
           eradication and based on our and others' pre-clinical data, we hypothesize that
           adoptive transfer of Th1.rapa cells to moderately immune depleted subjects
           (post-transplant subjects) will yield Th1 cytokine polarity and thereby will represent
           a T cell population of potential therapeutic benefit for patients with MM. [NOTE: we
           are assessing cytokine polarity but not able to assess in vivo persistence].

      Objectives:

      Primary

      -Evaluate the feasibility and toxicity of an infusion of autologous, ex vivo
      rapamycin-generated, anti-CD3 and anti-CD28 co-stimulated, Th1/Tc1 lymphocytes (Th1.rapa
      cells) in subjects newly diagnosed with high-risk multiple myeloma who are 6 weeks post-
      ASCT.

      Secondary

        -  Characterize the cellular aspects and cytokine phenotype of immune reconstitution in
           recipients of Th1.rapa cells.

        -  Characterize potential clinical anti-tumor responses in a preliminary manner through
           determination of disease-free survival, relapse-free and overall survival

      Eligibility:

      -Adults newly diagnosed with or receiving induction therapy for MM with established adverse
      prognostic features.

      Design:

        -  Subjects must have first received induction therapy followed by 1 or 2 ASCT as
           indicated clinically.

        -  Phase I dose escalation study of the administration of Th1.rapa cells.

        -  Th1.rapa cells infusion at approximately 6 weeks following the last ASCT.

      Seven Th1.rapa cell doses will be tested in cohorts of 1-6 subjects each: ranging from 10(5)
      to 45 x 10(6) cells/Kg of body weight.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation:  Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification:  Safety Study, Intervention Model:  Single Group Assignment, Masking:  Open Label, Primary Purpose:  Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate the feasibility and toxicity of an infusion of autologous, ex vivo rapamycin-generated, anti-CD3 and anti-CD28 co-stimulated, Th1/Tc1 lymphocytes (Th1.rapa cells) in subjects newly diagnosed with high-risk multiple myeloma.</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>-Characterize the cellular aspects and cytokine phenotype of immune reconstitution in recipients of Th1.rapa cells preceded or not by an immune depleting therapy.-Characterize potential clinical anti-tumor responses in a preliminary manner.</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">47</enrollment>
  <condition>Multiple Myeloma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Adoptive Immunotherapy</intervention_name>
    <description>N/A</description>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Th1/Tc1 product</intervention_name>
    <description>N/A</description>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

        MULTIPLE MYELOMA CRITERIA:

        Criteria for newly or recently diagnosed subjects

        -Presence of clonal plasma cells in the bone marrow greater or equal to 10% or a
        documented clonal plasmacytoma

        AND

        -Presence of an M-component; an M-component (IgG or IgA) in serum greater or equal to
        3g/dl or in urine greater or equal to 200 mg/24 h.

        ALTERNATIVELY, in absence of an M-component:

          -  an abnormal serum free light chain (FLC) ratio on the serum FLC assay or if the FLC
             ratio is normal,

          -  baseline bone marrow must have 10% or greater clonal plasma cells.

        AND, IN ADDITION:

          -  Presence, of one or more of the following attributable to the disease (in the
             presence or absence of an M component):

               -  Calcium elevation greater than 11.5 mg/dl (2.65 mmol/l)

               -  Renal insufficiency: serum creatinine greater than 2 mg/dl (177 mmol/l)

               -  Hemoglobin less than 10g/dl (12.5 mmol/l) or 2 g/dl (1.25 mmol/l) below lower
                  normal

               -  Bone disease (lytic lesions or osteopenia)

               -  Other evidence of disease activity: repeated infections, secondary amyloidosis,
                  hyperviscosity, hypogammablobulinemia

          -  Must have high risk disease defined as the presence of any of the following:

               -  Stage II and III of the International Staging System defined as follows:

                    -  stage I: - serum (Beta)2-microglobulin less than 3.5 mg/l plus

                       -----serum albumin greater or equal to 3.5 g/dl

                    -  stage II: neither stage I nor III

                    -  stage III: serum (Beta)2-microglobulin greater or equal to 5.5 mg/L

                         -  del 13 or aneuploidy (by metaphase analysis33)

                         -  del 17p13 by FISH

                         -  (4;14) by FISH31

                         -  (14;16) or t(14;20) by FISH

                         -  plasmablastic morphology at diagnosis(35)

                         -  circulating myeloma cells by FACS (CD38+/CD45low) post induction
                            therapy(36)

        OTHER ELIGIBILITY CRITERIA:

          -  Age greater than or equal to 18 years and less than or equal to 75 years. In subjects
             between 65 and 75 years of age, physiologic age and co-morbidity will be thoroughly
             evaluated before enrolling.

          -  Specifically, any history of cardio-vascular pathology or symptoms, not clearly
             fitting the exclusion criteria will prompt an evaluation by a Clinical Center
             Cardiologist and eligibility wil be considered on a case-by-case basis

          -  Must have received no more than 6 cycles of induction therapy for Multiple Myeloma.

          -  The planned High-Dose chemotherapy must consist of melphalan only and may be followed
             by a post-ASCT consolidation.

          -  Karnofsky performance status of 70% or greater (ECOG 0 or 1)

          -  Ejection fraction (EF) by MUGA or 2-D echocardiogram within institution normal
             limits. In case of low EF, the subject may remain eligible after a stress
             echocardiogram is performed if the EF is more than 35% and if the increase in EF with
             stress is estimated at 10% or more.

          -  Serum creatinine less than or equal to 2.5 mg/dl,

          -  AST and ALT less than or equal to 3 times the upper limit of normal,

          -  Bilirubin less than or equal to1.5 (except if due to Gilbert's disease).

          -  Corrected DLCO greater than or equal to 50% on Pulmonary Function Tests

          -  No history of abnormal bleeding tendency or predisposition to repeated infections.

          -  Patients must be able to give informed consent

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  Prior allogeneic stem cell transplantation

          -  Hypertension not adequately controlled by 3 or less medications.

          -  History of cerebro-vascular accident.

          -  History of documented pulmonary embolus

          -  Clinically significant cardiac pathology: myocardial infarction within 6 months prior
             to enrollment, Class III or IV heart failure according to NYHY, uncontrolled angina,
             severe uncontrolled ventricular arrhythmias, or electrocardiographic evidence of
             acute ischemia or active conduction system abnormalities.

          -  Patients with a history of coronary artery bypass grafting or angioplasty will
             receive a cardiology evaluation and be considered on a case-by-case basis.

          -  HIV seropositive

          -  Patients known or found to be pregnant.

          -  Patients of childbearing age who are unwilling to practice contraception.

          -  Patients may be excluded at the discretion of the PI if it is deemed that allowing
             participation would represent an unacceptable medical or psychiatric risk.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>NCI Referral Office</last_name>
    <phone>1-888-NCI-1937</phone>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hackensack University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hackensack</city>
        <state>New Jersey</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_2011-C-0016.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jemal A, Siegel R, Ward E, Hao Y, Xu J, Murray T, Thun MJ. Cancer statistics, 2008. CA Cancer J Clin. 2008 Mar-Apr;58(2):71-96. Epub 2008 Feb 20.</citation>
    <PMID>18287387</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Alexanian R, Barlogie B, Tucker S. VAD-based regimens as primary treatment for multiple myeloma. Am J Hematol. 1990 Feb;33(2):86-9.</citation>
    <PMID>2301376</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tosi P, Zamagni E, Cellini C, Plasmati R, Cangini D, Tacchetti P, Perrone G, Pastorelli F, Tura S, Baccarani M, Cavo M. Neurological toxicity of long-term (&gt;1 yr) thalidomide therapy in patients with multiple myeloma. Eur J Haematol. 2005 Mar;74(3):212-6.</citation>
    <PMID>15693790</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2011</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>September 30, 2011</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 10, 2010</firstreceived_date>
  <keyword>Multiple Myeloma</keyword>
  <keyword>High Risk</keyword>
  <keyword>Newly Diagnosed</keyword>
  <keyword>Adoptive Immunotherapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Autologous</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Multiple Myeloma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms, Plasma Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
</clinical_study>
