<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="53">
  <!-- This xml conforms to:  http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>Information obtained from ClinicalTrials.gov on October 20, 2011</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01221857</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>GC P#01.01.020</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01221857</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pilot Study Evaluating the Safety and Efficacy of Transplantation of UCB-derived ex Vivo Expanded Stem and Progenitor Cells (NiCord), in Combination With a Second, Unmanipulated CBU in Patients With Hematological Malignancies</brief_title>
  <official_title>Allogeneic Stem Cell Transplantation of NiCord, Umbilical Cord Blood-Derived Ex Vivo Expanded Stem and Progenitor Cells, in Combination With a Second, Unmanipulated Cord Blood Unit in Patients With Hematological Malignancies</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Gamida Cell ltd</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Gamida Cell ltd</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is designed as a pilot double cord study evaluating the safety and efficacy of
      transplantation of NiCord, umbilical cord-derived ex vivo expanded stem and progenitor
      cells, in combination with a second, unmanipulated cord blood unit in patients with
      hematological malignancies. The main study hypothesis is that co-transplantation of NiCord
      and an unmanipulated cord blood unit in patients with hematological malignancies following
      myeloablative therapy, will be safe and well tolerated.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell transplantation (HSCT) is a potentially curative
      procedure for a number of hematological malignancies, bone marrow failure syndromes and
      inherited metabolic disorders. The application of allogeneic HSCT is limited by donor
      availability such that only approximately one-third of otherwise appropriate candidates have
      suitably matched family donors. Alternative donors include mismatched family members or
      matched unrelated donors, but these approaches are often complicated by an increased risk of
      graft-versus-host disease (GvHD) and a prolonged and cumbersome search and procurement
      processes. In addition, far fewer subjects of racial minorities find suitable human
      leukocyte antigen (HLA)-matched donors.

      Umbilical cord blood has been increasingly used as an alternative source of stem cells and
      has extended the availability of allogeneic HSCT to patients who would otherwise not be
      eligible for this curative approach. In the last decade the number of cord blood
      transplantations from related and unrelated donors has increased dramatically. It is
      estimated that more than 20,000 patients have undergone cord blood transplantation from
      unrelated donors to date for a variety of genetic, hematological, immunological, metabolic
      and oncologic disorders. The major advantages of cord blood transplantation include easy
      procurement, no risk to donors, reduced incidence of transmitting infections, immediate
      availability, and reduced risk of acute GvHD in the setting of donor-recipient HLA mismatch.
      Nevertheless, the low cell dose remains a main limitation of this cell source leading to
      delayed hematopoietic reconstitution, higher risk of graft failure and relatively high
      treatment related mortality rates as compared to other hematopoeitic cell sources. To
      improve outcomes and extend applicability of cord blood transplantation, one potential
      solution is ex vivo expansion of cord blood-derived stem and progenitor cells.

      The sponsor has undertaken to develop NiCord, which is based on a novel technology for ex
      vivo cell expansion of cord blood derived hematopoietic progenitor cells. By increasing the
      number of short and long-term reconstitution progenitor cells transplanted, NiCord has the
      potential to enable broader application of umbilical cord blood transplantation, and improve
      its clinical outcomes in subjects with high-risk hematological malignancies.

      The main objective of the current study is to evaluate the safety of co-transplantation of
      NiCord and an unmanipulated cord blood unit to patients with hematological malignancies
      following myeloablative therapy. The study is designed as a pilot double cord study and
      consists of 3 phases:

        1. Screening phase - during this phase the patient undergo clinical assessment and
           screening tests to check his/her eligibility for the study. Once the patient is found
           eligible, the cord blood unit that was carefully selected for the patient in advance,
           enters the cell expansion process.

        2. Conditioning phase - during this phase the patient is treated with the myeloablative
           conditioning regimen and GvHD prophylaxis.

        3. Transplantation and follow-up -  includes transplantation of NiCord and the second,
           unmanipulated cord blood unit, and post-transplant supportive care and follow-up.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2011</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2011</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification:  Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model:  Single Group Assignment, Masking:  Open Label, Primary Purpose:  Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessment of the acute toxicity associated with the infusion of NiCord</measure>
    <time_frame>180 days post-transplant</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessment of the proportion of patients with neutrophil engraftment following co-transplantation of NiCord and unmanipulated cord blood grafts</measure>
    <time_frame>180 days post transplant</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of non-relapse mortality at 100 days</measure>
    <time_frame>100 days post-transplant</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patients who developed acute GvHD grade II-IV and III-IV</measure>
    <time_frame>180 days post-transplant</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time from infusion of both units to neutrophil and platelet engraftment</measure>
    <time_frame>180 days post-transplant</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Contribution of both NiCord and the unmanipulated CBU to initial and sustained engraftment</measure>
    <time_frame>180 days post-transplant</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patients with full donor chimerism (&gt;90%) by day 100</measure>
    <time_frame>180 days post-transplant</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Immune reconstitution at 60, 100 and 180 days</measure>
    <time_frame>60, 100 and 180 days post-transplant</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">12</enrollment>
  <condition>Acute Myeloid Leukemia</condition>
  <condition>Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia</condition>
  <condition>Hodgkin's Disease</condition>
  <condition>Non-Hodgkin's Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Myelodysplastic Syndromes</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>NiCord</intervention_name>
    <description>NiCord is a cell-based product composed of umbilical cord-derived ex vivo expanded stem and progenitor cells.</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria (for both adult and pediatric patients):

          1. Patients must be 8-65 years of age

          2. Patients with one of the following hematologic malignancies:

               -  Acute lymphoblastic leukemia (ALL)

                    -  High risk first complete morphologic remission (CR1), defined as:

                    -  The presence of t(4;11), t(9;22), t(1;19) or MLL rearrangements t(11q23)

                    -  Extreme leukocytosis (WBC &gt;50,000/µl or COG high risk criteria)

                    -  Failure to achieve complete remission after 4 weeks of induction
                       chemotherapy

                    -  Hypodiploidy

                    -  Second or subsequent remission

               -  Acute myelogenous leukemia (AML) at the following stages:

                    -  High risk first complete morphologic remission (CR1), defined as:

                    -  High-risk cytogenetics including monosomy chromosome 5 or 7, del(5q),
                       abn(3q26), 11q23 abnormalities {excluding t(9;11)}, complex karyotypic
                       abnormalities

                    -  Failure to to achieve complete remission after standard induction therapy

                    -  FLT-3 internal tandem duplication

                    -  A history of antecedent hematological disorder

                    -  Patients who are felt to have therapy-related AML whose prior malignancy
                       has been in remission for at least 12 months

                    -  Second or subsequent remission

                    -  Partial remission (defined as 5-10% blasts in the bone marrow)

               -  Myelodysplastic Syndrome (MDS) with International Prognostic Scoring System
                  (IPSS) risk category of INT-1 or greater

               -  Non-Hodgkin's lymphoma or Hodgkin's disease with at least one of the following
                  features:

                    -  Refractory to upfront chemotherapy

                    -  Second or subsequent complete or partial remission (partial remission
                       defined as ≥50% reduction of disease from the prior course of chemotherapy)
                       and not appropriate candidates for autologous stem cell transplantation.

          3. Patients must have two partially HLA-matched CBUs. Units must be HLA-matched at 4-6/6
             HLA class I (HLA-A &amp; HLA-B, low resolution) and II (HLA-DRB1, high resolution) loci
             with the patient and 3-6/6 HLA-A,B,DRB1 loci with each other (using same resolution
             of typing as indicated above). The unmanipulated and manipulated CBUs should contain
             a pre-cryopreserved, nucleated cell dose of at least 2.5x10^7 and 1.5x10^7 per
             kilogram, respectively The manipulated CBU will have undergone volume reduction (both
             plasma and red blood cell depletion) prior to cryopreservation

          4. The manipulated CBU will have undergone volume reduction (both plasma and red blood
             cell depletion) prior to cryopreservation

          5. Subjects' Performance score ≥70% by Karnofsky (age ≥13) or a Lansky Play-Performance
             scale of ≥70% (age &lt; 13)

          6. Patient has sufficient physiologic reserves including:

               -  Ejection fraction of &gt;40% by echocardiogram, radionuclide scan or cardiac MRI

               -  Pulmonary function tests demonstrating FVC and FEV1 of &gt;50% of predicted for age
                  and DLCO &gt; 50% of predicted

               -  Creatinine clearance test (by Cockcroft-Gault equation) ≥60 mL/min for adult
                  patients

               -  Serum Bilirubin &lt; 2.0 mg/dl

               -  Hepatic transaminases (ALT/AST) &lt; 3 x upper limit of normal range

          7. Patient must have at least one of the following back-up stem cell sources in case of
             engraftment failure:

               -  Patient has a third CBU as a possible back up. Unit must be HLA-matched at 4-6/6
                  HLA class I (HLA-A &amp; HLA-B, low resolution) and II (HLA-DRB1, high resolution)
                  loci with the patient with a minimum cryopreserved cell dose of 2.5x10^7/kg
                  recipient body weight

               -  Patient's haploidentical family member has been identified and agreed to donate
                  hematopoietic stem cells in case of engraftment failure

          8. Patient or guardian signs the written informed consent after being aware of the
             nature of the patient's disease and willingly consents to the treatment program after
             being informed of alternative treatments, potential risks, benefits, and discomforts

        Exclusion Criteria (for both adult and pediatric patients):

          1. Less than twenty-one days have elapsed since the patient's last radiation or
             chemotherapy and the initiation of the stem cell transplant preparative regimen

          2. Evidence of HIV infection or HIV positive serology

          3. Evidence of active Hepatitis B, Hepatitis C or EBV

          4. Lymphoma patients with progressive disease

          5. Pregnancy or lactation

          6. Active malignancy other than that for which the UCB transplant is being performed
             within 12 months of enrollment

          7. Uncontrolled bacterial, fungal or viral infection

          8. Patients with signs and symptoms of active central nervous system (CNS) disease

          9. HLA-matched related donor able to donate

         10. Prior allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell transplant

         11. Allergy to bovine, Gentamicin or to any product, which may interfere with the
             treatment

         12. Enrolled in another clinical trial or received an investigational treatment during
             the last 30 days, unless approved by Sponsor
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>8 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>David Snyder, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Gamida Cell ltd</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Joanne Kurtzberg, Professor, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Duke University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mitchell Horwitz, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Duke University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>David Snyder, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>972-2-6595666</phone>
    <email>David.snyder@gamida-cell.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Duke University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>2400 Pratt Street, Durham</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27705</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Joanne Kurtzberg, Professor, MD</last_name>
      <phone>919-668-1119</phone>
      <email>kurtz001@mc.duke.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Mitchell Horwitz, MD</last_name>
      <phone>(919) 668-1045</phone>
      <email>mitchell.horwitz@duke.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Joanne Kurzberg, Professor, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Mitchell Horwitz, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.gamida-cell.com</url>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.dukehealth.org/</url>
  </link>
  <verification_date>June 2011</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>June 6, 2011</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 14, 2010</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>David Snyder, PhD</name_title>
    <organization>Gamida Cell Ltd.</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Double Umbilical Cord Blood Stem Cell Transplantation</keyword>
  <keyword>Hematological Malignancies</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hodgkin Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Lymphoid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Precursor Cell Lymphoblastic Leukemia-Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myeloid, Acute</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myeloid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, Non-Hodgkin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myelodysplastic Syndromes</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Preleukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hematologic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
</clinical_study>
