<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="94">
  <!-- This xml conforms to:  http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>Information obtained from ClinicalTrials.gov on October 20, 2011</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01301664</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>97022</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01301664</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Cartilage Tissue Engineering</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Chin-Hung Chang</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Far Eastern Memorial Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Taiwan : Food and Drug Administration</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In this study, the investigators explored the hypothesis that osteoarthritic cartilage
      fragments can promote chondrogenesis of MSCs. Non-wearing parts of cartilage tissues were
      harvested from one osteoarthritic patient during the total knee arthroplasty surgery.
      Cartilage fragments and MSCs were wrapped into fibrin glue; and the constructs were
      implanted subcutaneously into nude mice.

      Moreover, the investigators will collect the discard cartilage to develop an acellular
      cartilage ECM-derived scaffold in the joint replacement surgery. In addition, the
      investigators will harvest the redundant bone marrow from drilling or useless synovium
      during the surgery to separate the mesenchymal stem cells. Furthermore, these mesenchymal
      stem cells will be transfected with hTERT for rejuvenation and then will be labeled with
      fluorescent dye PKH26 for application of animal study. To sum up, the investigators plan to
      use human, natural, and discard materials from the joint replacement surgery to develop
      appropriate allograft for cartilage repair and hope that one day this ideal would be apply
      in clinical.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Extracellular matrix (ECM) is thought to participate significantly in guiding the
      differentiation process of mesenchymal stem cells (MSCs). In this study, we explored the
      hypothesis that osteoarthritic cartilage matrix can promote chondrogenesis of MSCs.
      Cartilage matrix was harvested from the health-like parts of osteoarthritic cartilage
      tissue. Cartilage fragments and MSCs were wrapped into fibrin glue; and the constructs were
      implanted subcutaneously into nude mice. Histological analysis showed a round and elongated
      cell appearance with positive Alcian blue staining of cartilage matrix formation in the
      constructs. However, the cells in fibrin glue only were condensed like MSCs in pellet
      culture. Immunohistochemical staining was abundantly positive for type II collagen in
      neo-cartilage regions of cartilage fragment-fibrin glue-MSC constructs, while the constructs
      without cartilage fragments were negative in staining for type II collagen. The gene
      expressions of type II collagen in the constructs with 60 mg fragments were significantly
      elevated after 4 weeks of implantation. Conversely, constructs without cartilage fragments
      failed to express type II collagen, which indicated that MSCs could not differentiate into a
      chondrogenic lineage. In conclusion, we demonstrated the effects of osteoarthritic cartilage
      matrix in promoting chondrogenic differentiation of MSCs. This was a favorable method
      without exogenous growth factors induction.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Available</overall_status>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Expanded Access</study_type>
  <study_design>N/A</study_design>
  <condition>Mesenchymal Stem Cells</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>total knee / hip replacement</intervention_name>
    <description>Human cartilage tissues were harvested from osteoarthritic patient during total knee arthroplasty surgery.</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  30-70 years old

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  more than 70 years old
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>30 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Chia-Chun Chen, Master</last_name>
    <email>chia_chun_@hotmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>September 2011</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>September 20, 2011</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 5, 2010</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>The bone marrow-derived mesenchymal stem cells (BMMSCs) were obtained from redundant bone marrow from drilling during the joint replacement surgery.</keyword>
  <keyword>The synovial-derived mesenchymal stem cells (SMSCs) were isolated from synovial membranes in the joint replacement surgery.</keyword>
  <keyword>Cartilage slices were obtained from discard cartilage in the joint replacement surgery.</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
</clinical_study>
