<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="156">
  <!-- This xml conforms to:  http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>Information obtained from ClinicalTrials.gov on October 20, 2011</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01326104</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Pro00018020</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01326104</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Vaccine Immunotherapy for Recurrent Medulloblastoma and Primitive Neuroectodermal Tumor (PNET)</brief_title>
  <acronym>REMATCH</acronym>
  <official_title>Recurrent Medulloblastoma and Primitive Neuroectodermal Tumor Adoptive T Cell Therapy During Recover From Myeloablative Chemotherapy and Hematopoietic Stem Cell Transplantation</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Duke University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Duke University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <authority>United States: Department of Defense</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will have two phases. During Phase I, the investigators will treat patients with
      increasing doses of the tumor-specific immune cells that the investigators have expanded in
      the investigators clinical laboratory to establish the safety of this treatment regimen.
      These patients will also receive dendritic cell vaccines to help boost the function of these
      immune cells and maintain their growth after being returned to the patient. The
      investigators expect to treat approximately 9 patients during the Phase I component to
      establish that this treatment seems safe.   In the Phase II component, once the treatment
      has been shown to be safe, the investigators will treat a larger number of patients
      (approximately 35) with expanded tumor-specific immune cells and dendritic cell vaccines and
      evaluate the impact on tumor growth in these patients.  This will allow us to determine
      whether tumor growth is prevented or delayed compared to patients that have received similar
      treatment without immunotherapy.  This type of comparison to previously treated patients
      (called historical control comparison) will allow us to determine whether this treatment
      regimen looks promising enough to evaluate in larger clinical trials to definitively
      establish the effectiveness of this approach.

      Immunotherapy is a specific approach to treating cancer that has shown promise in adult
      patients for the treatment of melanoma, malignant brain tumors, and other cancers, and the
      investigators hope to use the experience the investigators have gained in the immunologic
      treatment of adult patients with malignant brain tumors at the investigators center to
      improve the clinical outcome for children affected by this disease.  This study has
      significant potential to impact the families of civilians and military dependents, as the
      brain is the most frequent site of crippling injuries in humans and unfortunately, brain
      cancer is currently the leading cause of cancer deaths in children in the United States.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background:  Malignant brain tumors now represent the most frequent cause of cancer death in
      children1.  Despite aggressive and highly toxic multi-modality therapy including surgery,
      craniospinal radiation, and high-dose chemotherapy coupled with peripheral blood stem cell
      transplantation (HDC + PBSCT), almost half the children diagnosed with the most common
      malignant brain tumors, medulloblastoma and primitive neuroectodermal tumors (MB/PNETs),
      will still die from recurrent disease.  Furthermore, survivors are often left with severe
      and lifelong treatment-associated cognitive and motor deficits. The development of more
      effective and tumor-specific therapies that will not add further toxicity to existing
      treatments is paramount in improving clinical outcomes for children affected by MB/PNETs.
      Immunotherapy targeting tumor-specific antigens expressed within brain tumors is a modality
      potentially capable of meeting this clear and urgent need8.

      Despite considerable advancements and promising clinical results observed in immunotherapy
      trials at our center and others directed against adult malignant brain tumors, efforts in
      the immunologic treatment of pediatric brain tumors have been limited to relatively few
      notable studies. This is due, at least in part, to the often limited viable tumor tissue
      available for tumor cell-based vaccine preparations, and the lack of identification of
      consistently expressed tumor-specific antigens within these cancers.

      The use of total tumor RNA-loaded dendritic cells (DCs) was pioneered by Drs. Nair and
      Gilboa at our institution, as a novel platform for inducing potent immunologic responses
      against the variety of uncharacterized and patient-specific antigens present within
      malignant tumor cells.  The investigators have demonstrated that sufficient RNA for clinical
      vaccine preparations can be amplified with high fidelity using existing molecular
      technologies from as few as 500 isolated pediatric and adult brain tumor cells, thus
      allowing vaccine preparation from surgical biopsies and even microdissected archival tumor
      specimens. The investigators are currently exploring adoptive cellular therapy using
      amplified tumor RNA-pulsed DCs and autologous lymphocyte transfer (DC + ALT therapy) in
      adult patients with recurrent GBM (FDA IND BB-13630; Duke IRB protocol 6677; PI: Duane A.
      Mitchell, M.D., Ph.D.). In this proposal, the investigators aim to extend evaluation of this
      novel platform to the treatment of recurrent MB/PNETs (reMB/PNETs) during hematopoietic
      recovery from HDC + PBSCT.

      Immunotherapy administered during recovery from HDC (Group A) or NMA salvage chemotherapy
      (Group B) may have tremendous advantages, as adoptive cellular therapy following
      lymphodepletive condition regimens has emerged as the most effective treatment strategy for
      advanced and refractory melanoma, with remarkable objective clinical responses in up to 75%
      of treated patients, including durable complete regressions of metastatic lesions within the
      CNS. Though the mechanisms by which lymphodepletion enhances immunotherapy in humans are not
      well elucidated, elegant studies in murine tumor models have highlighted the depletion of
      immunosuppressive regulatory T cells (Tregs), increased bioavailability of inflammatory
      cytokines and homeostatic proliferative cytokines (most notably IL-7 and IL-15) after
      removal of host lymphocytes and natural killer (NK) cells that compete with transferred
      tumor-specific T cells, and increased toll-receptor agonistic signals due to systemic
      release of gut microbial antigens during myeloablative therapy as the key catalysts for
      induction of potent anti-tumor immunity.

      Objective/Hypothesis: Our hypothesis is that DC + xALT therapy targeting reMB/PNETs during
      recovery from myeloablative chemotherapy will be safe and will prolong the 12-month
      progression-free survival (PFS-12) (H0: 3.14(pi) ≤ 0.33; H1: 3.14(pi) &gt; 0.55) in children
      and young adults with reMB/PNETs.

      Specific Aims:  A Phase I/II clinical trial of DC + ALT therapy during hematopoietic
      recovery from HDC + PBSCT in pediatric patients with reMB/PNETs will be conducted with the
      following Aims:

        1. Establish the safety of DC + ALT therapy during hematopoietic recovery from HDC + PBSCT
           (Group A) or NMA salvage chemotherapy (Group B) in children with reMB/PNETs;

        2. Determine the impact of DC + ALT therapy on progression-free survival (PFS) and overall
           survival (OS) of children with reMB/PNETs compared to historical controls;

        3. Investigate the correlation between clinical outcome and the frequency and persistence
           of tumor-specific T cells in the peripheral blood of treated patients;

        4. Determine the impact of induction therapy and HDC + PBSCT (Group A) or NMA salvage
           chemotherapy (Group B) on circulating levels of homeostatic and inflammatory cytokines,
           toll-receptor activation status, and on the functional recovery of lymphocyte and NK
           cellular subsets in children with re-MB/PNETs receiving DC + ALT therapy; Study Design:
            A single-arm, prospective Phase I/II clinical trial of DC + xALT therapy is planned in
           pediatric and young adult patients with reMB/PNETs.  The maximum tolerated dose of
           adoptively transferred tumor-specific lymphocytes will be established during Phase I
           using a 3+3 study design and then 35 patients will be treated during Phase II with the
           MTD of DC + xALT therapy to estimate the clinical efficacy. The primary endpoint of the
           Phase I trial will be safety and defining the MTD. The primary endpoint of the Phase II
           trial will be PFS-12.  With 35 patients, the Phase II study will have 90% power to
           differentiate between PFS-12 of 33% (null hypothesis) and 55% (alternative hypothesis)
           assuming a type I error rate of 0.10.

      Impact:  These studies will address the clear and urgent need for novel and less toxic
      therapy for the treatment of MB and PNETs in the pediatric population. As the leading cause
      of cancer related deaths in children, this therapy has significant potential to favorably
      alter the disease outcome for pediatric cancers overall.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation:  Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification:  Safety Study, Intervention Model:  Parallel Assignment, Masking:  Open Label, Primary Purpose:  Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Establishing the safety and DLT of DC + xALT therapy in this patient population with TTRNA-xALT and TTRNA-DCs will be the primary goal in the Phase I portion of the trial.</measure>
    <time_frame>44 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>A 3+3 Phase I study design with 3 lymphocyte (xALT) dose levels will be used to assess the safety of DC + xALT therapy, and to determine the maximum tolerated dose (MTD) for DC + xALT. An escalating total dose of TTRNA-xALT (3 x 10^6/Kg, 3 x 10^7/Kg, and 3 x 10^8/Kg) with TTRNA-DCs (2 x 10^7) will be evaluated in separate cohorts of 3 to 6 patients each for the purpose of establishing a MTD and a DLT in this patient population.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>For the Phase II portion of the trial, the primary efficacy endpoint will be 12-month progression-free survival (PFS-12) rate after treatment with DC + xALT therapy as a surrogate for overall survival.</measure>
    <time_frame>48 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The Phase II portion of this study will assess the clinical impact of DC + xALT therapy among pediatric patients with reMB/PNETs.  The basis for making this assessment will be the proportion of patients who survive 12 months without disease progression (PFS-12) as a surrogate clinical marker for OS in this patient population.  Progression-free survival will be measured from the initiation of HDC for comparison to our historical experience of HDC + PBSCT (Group A) or NMA salvage chemotherapy (Group B) in this patient population.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">64</enrollment>
  <condition>Medulloblastoma</condition>
  <condition>Neuroectodermal Tumors</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>TTRNA-xALT with TTRNA-DC</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>An escalating total dose of TTRNA-xALT (3 x 10^6/Kg, 3 x 10^7/Kg, and 3 x 10^8/Kg) with TTRNA-DCs (2 x 10^7) will be evaluated in separate cohorts of 3 to 6 patients each for the purpose of establishing a maximally tolerated dose (MTD) and a dose-limiting toxicity (DLT) in this patient population.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>TTRNA-xALT with TTRNA-DCs</intervention_name>
    <description>An escalating total dose of TTRNA-xALT (3 x 106/Kg, 3 x 107/Kg, and 3 x 108/Kg) with TTRNA-DCs (2 x 107) will be evaluated in separate cohorts of 3 to 6 patients each for the purpose of establishing a maximally tolerated dose (MTD) and a dose-limiting toxicity (DLT) in this patient population.</description>
    <arm_group_label>TTRNA-xALT with TTRNA-DC</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age ≤ 30 years of age.

          -  Patients must have histologically confirmed reMB/PNET and received definitive
             radiotherapy (craniospinal + focal boost) prior to relapse.

          -  Patients with neurological deficits should have deficits that are stable for a
             minimum of 1 week prior to registration.

          -  Karnofsky Performance Status (KPS) of &gt; 50% (KPS for &gt; 16 years of age) or Lansky
             performance Score (LPS) of ≥ 50 (LPS for ≤ 16 years of age) assessed within 2 weeks
             prior to registration.

          -  Bone Marrow:

               -  ANC (Absolute neutrophil count) ≥ 1000/µl (unsupported).

               -  Platelets ≥ 100,000/µl (unsupported).

               -  Hemoglobin &gt; 8 g/dL (may be supported).

          -  Renal:

               -  Serum creatinine ≤ upper limit of institutional normal

               -  GFR of at least 70 ml/min/1.73m2.

          -  Hepatic:

               -  Bilirubin ≤ 1.5 times upper limit of normal for age.

               -  SGPT (Serum Glutamic Oxaloacetic Transaminase)(ALT) ≤ 3 times institutional
                  upper limit of normal for age.

               -  SGOT (AST) ≤ 3 times institutional upper limit of normal for age.

          -  Cardiac:

               -  ECHO cardiogram with a shortening fraction of &gt; 45%.

               -  EKG without clinically significant arrhythmias.

          -  Patients of childbearing or child-fathering potential must be willing to use a
             medically acceptable form of birth control, which includes abstinence, while being
             treated on this study.

          -  Patient or patient guardian consent to PBSC and/or bone marrow harvest following
             registration.

          -  Signed informed consent according to institutional guidelines must be obtained prior
             to registration.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Pregnant or need to breast feed during the study period (Negative serum pregnancy
             test required).

          -  Active infection requiring treatment or an unexplained febrile (&gt; 101.5o F) illness.

          -  Known immunosuppressive disease or human immunodeficiency virus infection.

          -  Patients with active renal, cardiac (congestive cardiac failure, myocardial
             infarction, myocarditis), or pulmonary disease.

          -  Patients receiving concomitant immunosuppressive agents for medical condition

          -  Patients who need definitive radiotherapy for treatment of reMB/PNET.

          -  Patients receiving any other concurrent anticancer or investigational drug therapy.

          -  Patients with any clinically significant unrelated systemic illness (serious
             infections or significant cardiac, pulmonary, hepatic or other organ dysfunction),

          -  Patients with inability to return for follow-up visits or obtain follow-up studies
             required to assess toxicity to therapy.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>30 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jennifer F King, RN</last_name>
    <phone>919-668-5364</phone>
    <email>jennifer.f.king@duke.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Duke University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Durham</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27710</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Denise Lally-Goss</last_name>
      <phone>919-684-3862</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Duane Mitchell</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://neuro.surgery.duke.edu/modules/div_neuro_bip/index.php?id=1</url>
    <description>Duke Brain Tumor Immunotherapy Program</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>September 2011</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>September 8, 2011</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>July 22, 2010</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Recurrent Medulloblastoma and Primitive Neuroectodermal Tumors</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Medulloblastoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neuroectodermal Tumors</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neuroectodermal Tumors, Primitive</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
</clinical_study>
