<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="193">
  <!-- This xml conforms to:  http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>Information obtained from ClinicalTrials.gov on October 20, 2011</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01257750</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>10-09-063</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01257750</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Treatment of Corneal Neovascularization With Topical Pazopanib</brief_title>
  <official_title>Safety and Efficacy of Topical Pazopanib in Treatment of Corneal Neovascularization</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Massachusetts Eye and Ear Infirmary</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Massachusetts Eye and Ear Infirmary</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine the safety and efficacy of a drug [Pazopanib
      (Votrient)] as a treatment for corneal neovascularization. The cornea is the clear, central
      portion of the eye and neovascularization means blood vessel growth. The cornea is typically
      avascular, or without blood vessels. Corneal neovascularization in the cornea and can put
      vision at risk. Numerous diseases of the cornea such as inflammation, ischemia (restriction
      of blood supply), infection, degeneration (or deterioration), trauma, or corneal stem cell
      deficiency can lead to corneal neovascularization. This major ocular complication can lead
      to corneal scarring, edema (swelling), lipid deposits, and inflammation that may
      significantly alter your vision. In addition, it worsens the outcome of potential future
      treatments, such as a corneal transplant. A corneal transplant is a treatment that many
      patients with severe corneal disease may ultimately need.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Normally avascular, under many pathologic conditions, vessels may invade the cornea from the
      limbal vascular plexus. Infection, inflammation, ischemia, degeneration, or trauma, and the
      loss of the limbal stem cell barrier can cause corneal neovascularization. Growth of new
      vessels may result in corneal scarring, edema, lipid deposition, and inflammation that may
      alter visual acuity and is a leading cause of monocular visual impairment and blindness.
      Additionally, it results in the loss of immune response across the cornea, thereby worsening
      the prognosis of a subsequent penetrating keratoplasty (PK). Growth of new blood and
      lymphatic vessels from preexisting vessels are mediated by members of the vascular
      endothelial growth factor (VEGF) family. In previous studies, inhibition of new blood or
      lymphatic vessels has been achieved by neutralization of vascular endothelial growth factor
      A (VEGF-A). It has also been shown that platelet-derived growth factor-B (PDGF-B) plays a
      role in corneal and choroidal neovascularization by regulating mural cell recruitment.
      Inhibition of PDGF-B and VEGF-A signaling pathways has shown to more effectively promote
      vessel regression than solely inhibiting VEGF-A. Pazopanib is a drug designed to block these
      pathways, stop new growth, and regress old vessel growth.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2011</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2011</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation:  Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification:  Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model:  Single Group Assignment, Masking:  Open Label, Primary Purpose:  Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety and Tolerability of Topical Pazopanib in the Treatment of Corneal Neovascularization as Identified by Ocular Examination</measure>
    <time_frame>12 Weeks of follow-up</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Incidence and severity of ocular adverse events, as identified by eye examination and visual acuity testing through week 12
Incidence and severity of other adverse events, as identified by physical examination, subject reporting, and changes in vital signs (blood pressure and heart rate) through week 12</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Efficacy - Changes in the Extent of Corneal Neovascularization at Weeks 1, 3, 7 and 12</measure>
    <time_frame>Through 12 weeks of Follow-Up</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Neovascular Area (NA), measuring the area of the corneal vessels themselves 2
Vessel Caliber (VC), measuring the mean diameter of the corneal vessels
Invasion Area (IA) measuring the fraction of the total corneal area invaded by the vessels
Mean change in Best Spectacle-Corrected Visual Acuity (BCVA) from baseline to week 3 and 12
In order to meet the secondary endpoints, the treatment will be considered efficacious if the area of neovascularization or vessel caliber decreases by 20% compared to baseline.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Corneal Neovascularization</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Pazopanib</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>This is a single site, open label, safety and efficacy study of pazopanib (5mg/ml) where 20 patients with corneal neovascularization will be recruited to receive pazopanib in one eye.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pazopanib (5mg/ml)</intervention_name>
    <description>Topical pazopanib, 4 times per day for 3 weeks</description>
    <arm_group_label>Pazopanib</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Votrient</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Ability to provide written informed consent

          -  Ability to comply with study assessments and study requirements (for example, able to
             open the eye drop foil-wrap packaging and eye drop vials, willing to adhere to the
             daily dosing schedule) for the full duration of study

          -  Age &gt; 18 years

          -  Patients with superficial or deep corneal neovascularization that extends farther
             than 1 mm from the limbus

          -  Patients are in stable overall health

          -  Alanine aminotransferase (ALT), aspartate aminotransferase (AST), alkaline
             phosphatase and bilirubin ≤ 1.5x upper limit of normal (ULN) or isolated bilirubin
             &gt;1.5x ULN is acceptable if bilirubin is fractionated and direct bilirubin &lt;35%

          -  Single QTcF &lt; 450 msec; or QTcF &lt; 480 msec in subjects with Bundle Branch Block

          -  A female is eligible to enter and participate in this study if she is of
             Non-childbearing potential (i.e., physiologically incapable of becoming pregnant),

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Current or chronic history of liver disease, or known hepatic or biliary
             abnormalities (with the exception of Gilbert's syndrome or asymptomatic gallstones)

          -  History of any clotting disorder, including predisposition to hypercoagulation or any
             previous thromboembolic event

          -  Major surgery within 1 month of screening

          -  Has received treatment with anti-VEGF agents (topical, intraocular or systemic)
             within 60 days of study entry. This includes both approved and investigational
             treatments.

          -  Has received investigational therapy within 60 days prior to study entry

          -  Concurrent enrollment in another clinical investigational medicinal product or device
             study

          -  Concurrent use of anti-VEGF agents

          -  Corneal or ocular surface infection within 30 days prior to study entry

          -  Full thickness or lamellar keratoplasty within 90 days prior to study entry

          -  Other ocular surgeries within 60 days prior to study entry

          -  Ocular or periocular malignancy

          -  Soft Contact lens (excluding bandage contact lens) use within 2 weeks prior to study
             entry

          -  Persistent epithelial defect (&gt;1mm and ≥14 days duration) within 2 weeks prior to
             study entry

          -  Intravitreal or periocular steroids within 4 weeks prior to study entry

          -  Change in dose/frequency of topical steroids and/or nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory
             drugs (NSAIDs) within 2 weeks prior to study entry

          -  Poorly controlled Hypertension: systolic blood pressure (BP) &gt; 150 or diastolic BP &gt;
             90

          -  Medical history of uncontrolled diabetes mellitus, with hemoglobin A1c (HbA1c) &gt;7%

          -  Women 45 years of age or younger that are of child bearing potential as defined by:

               -  No history of a hysterectomy

               -  No history of a bilateral oophorectomy (ovariectomy)

               -  No history of a bilateral tubal ligation

               -  Not post-menopausal

          -  Subjects using hormone replacement therapy (HRT) that have experienced total
             cessation of menses for ≤ 1 year, OR, in questionable cases, have a follicle
             stimulating hormone (FSH) value &lt;40 mIU/mL and an estradiol value &gt; 40pg/mL (&gt;140
             pmol/L) OR have documented evidence OR have had documented evidence of menopause
             based on FSH and estradiol concentrations prior to initiation of HRT. Signs of
             current infection, including fever and current treatment with antibiotics

          -  Participation in another simultaneous medical investigation or trial STUDY
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Reza Dana, MD, MPH, MSc</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Mass Eye and Ear Infirmary</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Massachusetts Eye and Ear Infirmary</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02114</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Cornea Research</last_name>
      <phone>617-573-3313</phone>
      <email>cornea_research@meei.harvard.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Brandon Udelhofen</last_name>
      <phone>617-391-5894</phone>
      <email>brandon_udelhofen@meei.harvard.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2011</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 29, 2011</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 22, 2010</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Reza Dana, MD, MPH, MSc</name_title>
    <organization>Massachusetts Eye &amp; Ear Infirmary</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>corneal neovascularization</keyword>
  <keyword>pazopanib</keyword>
  <keyword>votrient</keyword>
  <keyword>rosacea</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Neovascularization, Pathologic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Corneal Neovascularization</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
</clinical_study>
