<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="241">
  <!-- This xml conforms to:  http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>Information obtained from ClinicalTrials.gov on October 20, 2011</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01261247</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MC0986</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2010-02326</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>10-004705</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>CLBH589BUS59T</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>MC0986</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01261247</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Panobinostat in Treating Patients With Relapsed or Refractory Non-Hodgkin Lymphoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase II Study of the Histone Deacetylase (HDAC) Inhibitor LBH589 (Panobinostat) in Patients With Relapsed or Refractory Non-Hodgkin Lymphoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Mayo Clinic</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Mayo Clinic</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Panobinostat may stop the growth of cancer cells by blocking some of the enzymes needed for
      cell growth. This phase II trial is studying how well panobinostat works in treating
      patients with relapsed or refractory non-Hodgkin lymphoma
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES: I. To evaluate the proportion of confirmed response of LBH589 in
      patients with relapsed or refractory non-Hodgkin lymphoma.  SECONDARY OBJECTIVES: I. To
      describe the toxicities associated with LBH589 in patients with NHL. II. To evaluate overall
      survival, progression-free survival, and duration of response in patients treated with
      LBH589.  TERTIARY OBJECTIVES: I. To evaluate the pharmacokinetics of LBH589. II. To assess
      the correlation between clinical (toxicity and/or tumor response or activity) effects with
      the pharmacologic (pharmacokinetic/pharmacodynamic) parameters, and/or biologic (correlative
      laboratory) results.  OUTLINE: Patients receive oral panobinostat 3 times weekly. Treatment
      repeats every 28 days for up to 12 courses in the absence of disease progression or
      unacceptable toxicity.  After completion of study treatment, patients are followed up every
      6 months for up to 2 years.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2011</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification:  Efficacy Study, Intervention Model:  Single Group Assignment, Masking:  Open Label, Primary Purpose:  Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of confirmed responses defined to be a CR or PR noted as the objective status</measure>
    <time_frame>Every 28 days for up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Survival time due to any cause; estimated using the method of Kaplan-Meier for the patients included in evaluating the decision criteria</measure>
    <time_frame>Every 6 months for up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-free survival time due to any cause; will be estimated using the method of Kaplan-Meier</measure>
    <time_frame>Every 6 months for up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of response as assessed by Kaplan-Meier</measure>
    <time_frame>Every 6 months for up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetic/pharmacodynamic of LBH589 and correlation with clinical effects as assessed by immunoblotting, SNPs analysis, serum cytokine assays, and flow cytometry for suppressive monocytes (correlative studies)</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline and day 1 of courses 3, 5, 7 and every three courses thereafter for up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">37</enrollment>
  <condition>Adult Nasal Type Extranodal NK/T-cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Anaplastic Large Cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Angioimmunoblastic T-cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Extranodal Marginal Zone B-cell Lymphoma of Mucosa-associated Lymphoid Tissue</condition>
  <condition>Hepatosplenic T-cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Nodal Marginal Zone B-cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Peripheral T-cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Post-transplant Lymphoproliferative Disorder</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Adult Burkitt Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Adult Diffuse Large Cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Adult Lymphoblastic Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Adult T-cell Leukemia/Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Grade 1 Follicular Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Grade 2 Follicular Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Grade 3 Follicular Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Mantle Cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Mycosis Fungoides/Sezary Syndrome</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Small Lymphocytic Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Small Intestine Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Splenic Marginal Zone Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Waldenstrom Macroglobulinemia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm I</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive oral panobinostat 3 times weekly. Treatment repeats every 28 days for up to 12 courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>panobinostat</intervention_name>
    <description>Given orally</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm I</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Faridak</other_name>
    <other_name>HDAC inhibitor LBH589</other_name>
    <other_name>histone deacetylase inhibitor LBH589</other_name>
    <other_name>LBH589</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>laboratory biomarker analysis</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm I</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Genetic</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>western blotting</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm I</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Blotting, Western</other_name>
    <other_name>Western Blot</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Genetic</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>DNA analysis</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm I</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>flow cytometry</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm I</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>pharmacological study</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm I</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>pharmacological studies</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>immunohistochemistry staining method</intervention_name>
    <description>Optional correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm I</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>immunohistochemistry</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria

          -  Biopsy-proven relapsed or refractory non-Hodgkin lymphoma requiring treatment, who
             have failed, unable to tolerate, or refused other available active therapies;
             patients should not have other treatment options considered curative (NOTE: for
             patients with lymphoma without CNS involvement, a re-biopsy is necessary unless the
             patient has had a previous biopsy =&lt; 6 months prior to treatment on this protocol if
             there has been no intervening treatment; patients with biopsy-proven CNS lymphoma at
             any time are not required to have a rebiopsy to be eligible for this study); NOTE:
             relapsed NHL is defined as NHL that relapses after at least one prior therapy and
             does not have available curative therapy; refractory NHL is defined as NHL that has
             progressed or not responded to most recent therapy and has had at least one prior
             therapy and have no available curative therapies

          -  Measurable disease by CT or MRI or the CT portion of the PET/CT: must have at least
             one lesion that has a single diameter of &gt;= 2 cm or tumor cells in the blood &gt;= 5 x
             10^9/L; skin lesions can be used if the area is &gt;= 2 cm in at least one diameter and
             photographed with a ruler

          -  The following disease types are eligible: transformed lymphomas: diffuse large B cell
             lymphoma, mantle cell lymphoma, follicular lymphoma grade III; precursor B
             lymphoblastic leukemia/lymphoma; mediastinal (thymic) large B-cell lymphoma; Burkitt
             lymphoma/leukemia; precursor T-lymphoblastic leukemia/lymphoma; primary cutaneous
             anaplastic large cell lymphoma; anaplastic large cell lymphoma - primary systemic
             type; small lymphocytic lymphoma/chronic lymphocytic leukemia; follicular lymphoma,
             grades 1, 2; extranodal marginal zone B-cell lymphoma of MALT type; nodal marginal
             zone B-cell lymphoma; splenic marginal zone B-cell lymphoma; peripheral T cell
             lymphoma, unspecified; anaplastic large cell lymphoma (T and null cell type);
             lymphoplasmacytic lymphoma (Waldenstrom Macroglobulinemia); CNS lymphoma; post
             transplant lymphoproliferative disorders; mycosis fungoides/Sezary syndrome; primary
             effusion lymphoma; blastic NK-cell lymphoma; adult T-cell leukemia/lymphoma;
             extranodal NK/T-cell lymphoma, nasal type; enteropathy-type T-cell lymphoma;
             hepatosplenic T-cell lymphoma; subcutaneous panniculitis-like T-cell lymphoma;
             angioimmunoblastic T-cell lymphoma; anaplastic large cell lymphoma - primary
             cutaneous type

          -  For lymphoplasmacytic lymphoma patients without measurable lymphadenopathy,
             measurable disease can be defined by both of the following criteria: bone marrow
             lymphoplasmacytosis with &gt; 10% lymphoplasmacytic cells or aggregates, sheets,
             lymphocytes, plasma cells, or lymphoplasmacytic cells on bone marrow biopsy and
             quantitative IgM monoclonal protein &gt; 1,000 mg/dL

          -  ANC &gt;= 1000/uL

          -  Hgb &gt;= 9 g/dl

          -  PLT &gt;= 75,000/uL

          -  Total bilirubin =&lt; 1.5 x upper limit of normal (ULN) or if total bilirubin is &gt; 1.5 x
             ULN the direct bilirubin must be normal

          -  AST =&lt; 3 x ULN

          -  Albumin &gt; 3.0 g/dl

          -  Creatinine =&lt; 2.5 x ULN

          -  Serum potassium, magnesium and phosphorus &gt;= LLN and =&lt; 1.2 x ULN

          -  Total serum calcium [corrected for serum albumin] or ionized calcium &gt;= LLN

          -  Clinically euthyroid; patients are permitted to receive thyroid hormone supplements
             to treat underlying hypothyroidism

          -  Baseline MUGA or ECHO must demonstrate LVEF &gt;= the lower limit of the institutional
             normal

          -  Ability to understand and the willingness to sign a written informed consent document

          -  Willingness to return to Mayo Clinic

          -  Life expectancy &gt;= 12 weeks

          -  Willingness to provide blood and tissues samples for research studies as required by
             the protocol

          -  Negative pregnancy test done =&lt; 7 days prior to registration, for women of
             childbearing potential only

          -  ECOG performance status (PS) 0, 1 or 2

        Exclusion Criteria

          -  Prior HDAC, DAC, HSP90 inhibitors or valproic acid for the treatment of cancer

          -  Patients who will need valproic acid for any medical condition during the study or
             within 5 days prior to first panobinostat treatment

          -  Candidate for known standard therapy for the patient's disease that is potentially
             curative

          -  Uncontrolled infection requiring ongoing antibiotics

          -  Any prior therapy for lymphoma within the previous 2 weeks for standard treatments
             and within 4 weeks for experimental therapies unless the patient has recovered from
             the nadir of the previous treatment to a level that meets the inclusion criteria

          -  Receiving corticosteroids &gt; 20mg of prednisone per day (or equivalent)

          -  Persistent toxicities &gt;= grade 2 from prior chemotherapy or biological therapy
             regardless of interval since last treatment

          -  Patients with congenital long QT syndrome

          -  History or presence of sustained ventricular tachyarrhythmia (patients with a history
             of atrial arrhythmia are eligible but should be discussed with the study PI prior to
             enrollment)

          -  Any history of ventricular fibrillation or torsade de pointes

          -  Bradycardia defined as HR &lt; 50 bpm; patients with pacemakers are eligible if HR &gt;= 50
             bpm

          -  Screening ECG with a QTcFredericia (QTcF) &gt; 450 msec

          -  Right bundle branch block + left anterior hemiblock (bifascicular block)

          -  Patients with myocardial infarction or unstable angina =&lt; 6 months prior registration

          -  Other clinically significant heart disease (e.g. CHF NY Heart Association class III
             or IV, uncontrolled hypertension, history of labile hypertension, or history of poor
             compliance with an antihypertensive regimen)

          -  Pregnant women or women of reproductive ability who are unwilling to use effective
             contraception during the study and for 3 months after stopping treatment

          -  Nursing women

          -  Men who are unwilling to use a condom (even if they have undergone a prior vasectomy)
             while having intercourse with any woman, while taking the drug and for 3 months after
             stopping treatment

          -  Other concurrent chemotherapy, immunotherapy, radiotherapy, or any ancillary therapy
             considered investigational (utilized for a non-FDA-approved indication and in the
             context of a research investigation); patients should have recovered from any
             immunotherapy, chemotherapy, or radiation therapy related toxicities

          -  Known positivity for human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) or hepatitis C with
             uncontrolled disease; baseline testing for HIV and hepatitis C is not required

          -  Active other malignancy requiring treatment that would interfere with the assessments
             of response of the lymphoma to protocol treatment

          -  Inability to swallow or impairment of gastrointestinal function or gastrointestinal
             disease that may significantly alter the absorption of the drugs (e.g. ulcerative
             disease, uncontrolled nausea, vomiting, diarrhea &gt; CTCAE Grade 2, malabsorption
             syndrome or small bowel resection) that would preclude use of oral medications

          -  Thrombolic or embolic events such as a cerebrovascular accident including transient
             ischemic attacks within the past 6 months

          -  Any severe and/or uncontrolled medical conditions or other conditions that, in the
             treating physician's opinion, could adversely impact their ability to participate in
             the study; patients on chronic oxygen therapy, those with liver disease such as
             cirrhosis, chronic hepatitis or chronic persistent hepatitis, or uncontrolled
             infections will be excluded

          -  Concomitant use of strong or moderate CYP3A4 inhibitors

          -  Using medications that have a relative risk of prolonging the QT interval or inducing
             torsade de pointes if treatment cannot be discontinued or switched to a different
             medication prior to starting study drug

          -  Active bleeding tendency.  NOTE: Patients on therapeutic anticoagulation should be
             monitored carefully to maintain therapeutic level of anticoagulation to avoid
             increased risk of bleeding due to concurrent drug induced thrombocytopenia.  It is
             suggested that patients who require anticoagulation therapy while on therapy use low
             molecular weight heparin (LMWH).

          -  Major surgery =&lt; 4 weeks prior to registration or have not recovered from side
             effects of such therapy

          -  History of other prior malignancies except for properly treated basal cell or
             squamous cell carcinoma of skin, in situ cervical cancer, in situ breast cancer or
             early stage prostate cancer
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Patrick Johnston, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Mayo Clinic</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mayo Clinic in Arizona</name>
      <address>
        <city>Scottsdale</city>
        <state>Arizona</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Mayo Clinic Clinical Trials Office</last_name>
      <phone>507-538-7623</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Craig B. Reeder, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mayo Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rochester</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55905</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Mayo Clinic Clinical Trials Office</last_name>
      <phone>507-538-7623</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Patrick B. Johnston, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2011</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>September 22, 2011</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>December 14, 2010</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Patrick Bruce Johnston, M.D.</name_title>
    <organization>Mayo Clinic Cancer Center</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Burkitt Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Immunoblastic Lymphadenopathy</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Lymphocytic, Chronic, B-Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, T-Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia-Lymphoma, Adult T-Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, Follicular</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, Large B-Cell, Diffuse</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, Non-Hodgkin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoproliferative Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Waldenstrom Macroglobulinemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Mycoses</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Mycosis Fungoides</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sezary Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, B-Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Precursor Cell Lymphoblastic Leukemia-Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, T-Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, T-Cell, Peripheral</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, Large-Cell, Anaplastic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, B-Cell, Marginal Zone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, Mantle-Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, Extranodal NK-T-Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Histone Deacetylase Inhibitors</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
</clinical_study>
