<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="184">
  <!-- This xml conforms to:  http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>Information obtained from ClinicalTrials.gov on October 20, 2011</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01245335</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CLI-2010-1</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01245335</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Bone Marrow Aspirate Concentrate (BMAC) for Treatment of Critical Limb Ischemia (CLI)</brief_title>
  <official_title>Pivotal Study of the Safety and Effectiveness of Autologous Bone Marrow Aspirate Concentrate (BMAC) for the Treatment of Critical Limb Ischemia Due to Peripheral Arterial Disease</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Harvest Technologies</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Harvest Technologies</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Injections of concentrated bone marrow nucleated cells into ischemic tissues will result in
      vasculogenesis.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Bone marrow aspirate is collected and processed by centrifugation to remove red blood cells.
      The buffy coat is concentrated by removing plasma. The resultant concentrate of cells is
      injected into ischemic tissues of the lower limb.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation:  Randomized, Endpoint Classification:  Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model:  Parallel Assignment, Masking:  Double Blind (Subject, Investigator), Primary Purpose:  Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Amputation Free Survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Six Months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Survival without a major (above the ankle) amputation</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change In Rutherford Classification</measure>
    <time_frame>Six Months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Change in the subjects clinical status as measured by Rutherford Classification</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Pain</measure>
    <time_frame>Six Months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Change in Subjects perception of pain as measured on a 100 mm visual analog scale</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">210</enrollment>
  <condition>Critical Limb Ischemia Due to Peripheral Arterial Occlusive Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>BMAC Treatment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Injection of 40 ml of autologous bone marrow concentrate (BMAC) prepared with the SmartPReP2 BMAC System</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo Injection</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>injection of placebo into ischemic tissue of the lower extremity</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>BMAC injection</intervention_name>
    <description>Injection of 40 ml of autologous bone marrow aspirate concentrate (BMAC) prepared with the SmartPReP2 BMAC System</description>
    <arm_group_label>BMAC Treatment</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo injection</intervention_name>
    <description>injection of placebo into ischemic tissue of the lower extremity</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo Injection</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        1. Diagnosis of Critical Limb Ischemia per protocol (see diagnostic criteria #2) with
        regard to the study limb.

        Existence of a PAOD with clinical presentation corresponding to Rutherford Category 4 or
        Category 5 as defined in the reporting standards adopted by the Society of Vascular
        Surgeons (table 1) 2. Patient meets at least one of the following diagnostic criteria in
        the study limb:

        a. Ankle artery occlusion pressure absolute ≤60 mmHg or ABI ≤0.5 b. Toe artery occlusive
        pressure &lt; 50mm Hg or TBI ≤0.5 c. TcPO2 ≤30 mmHg on the dorsum of the foot, lying down
        breathing room air. 3. There is no reasonable open surgical or endovascular
        revascularization option as determined by the treating vascular specialist.  Factors that
        may contribute to the determination of inoperability may include:

          1. Anatomical considerations

             1.  No outflow targets 2.  No appropriate conduit (i.e. vein for bypass) 3.  Long
             segment occlusions or calcified lesions that predict poor outcome with endovascular
             approaches.

          2. High risk medical conditions

             1. Unstable cardiac disease. 2. Severe Malnutrition

          3. History of prior failed revascularization attempts

          4. The patient's unsuitability must be attested to  by at least 2 qualified physicians;

               1. The attending vascular surgeon will provide the primary assessment.

               2. The confirmatory opinion must come from a fully licensed physician. (not a
                  resident)

               3. If anatomical considerations are invoked, the second physician may be a vascular
                  surgeon, interventional radiologist, cardiologist, or vascular medicine
                  specialist.

               4. If medical co-morbidity is deemed the high risk aspect, then the confirmatory
                  opinion may be obtained from an internist, family physician, cardiologist,
                  vascular medicine, nephrologists, or vascular surgeon.

               5. All candidates for this study must be presented for consideration at the
                  treating institution's Multidisciplinary Vascular Conference, if dissenting
                  opinions are expressed these opinions are to be noted by the local PI and the
                  case should then be submitted to the overall multicenter study PI to determine
                  study eligibility.

             4. Age &gt;18 years and ability to understand the planned treatment 5. Subject has read
             and signed the IRB approved Informed Consent form 6. Patients for whom the following
             medication(s) is prescribed must have a one month stable baseline of
             appropriate/maximally tolerated therapy prior to enrollment:  Plavix/asprin therapy,
             anticoagulation therapy, cholesterol lowering agent, and or blood pressure
             medication. If any of these medications are not prescribed notation of the reason for
             omission is to be provided.

             7. Hematocrit ≥ 28.0%, White Blood Cell count ≤ 14,000, Platelet count ≥ 50,000,
             Creatinine ≤ 2.5 mg / dL, INR ≤ 1.6 unless on Coumadin, or PTT &lt;1.5 x control (to
             avoid bleeding complications)  Patients on Coumadin will be corrected prior to the
             procedure and must have an INR&lt;1.6 at the time of randomization/surgery.

             Exclusion Criteria:

             1. Life expectancy &lt;6 months due to concomitant illnesses 2. History of bone marrow
             diseases (especially NHL, MDS) that prohibit transplantation 3. Terminal renal
             failure with existing dependence on dialysis or serum creatinine &gt;2.5 mg/dL 4. Known
             active malignancy or results outside of normal limits from the following tests: PAP,
             Chest X-ray, PSA, Mammogram, Hemocult unless follow-up studies reveal patient to be
             cancer free.

             5 Poorly controlled diabetes mellitus (HgbA1C&gt;10%) 6 Medical risk that precludes
             anesthesia (conscious sedation), or ASA Class 5 7. Life-threatening complications of
             the ischemia necessitating immediate amputation 8. Uncorrected iliac artery occlusion
             on index side 9. No Doppler signal in the foot (ABI =0) 10. Extensive necrosis of the
             index limb or other conditions that make amputation inevitable (Rutherford Category
             6).

             11. Active clinical infection or infection being treated by antibiotics within one
             week of enrollment 12. Treatment with immunosuppressant drugs (including Prednisone &gt;
             5 mg per day).

             13. Female who is pregnant or nursing, or of child bearing potential and is not using
             a reliable birth control method.

             14. Underwent a major open cardiovascular surgical procedure (carotid endarterectomy,
             arterial aneurysm or bypass surgery, or coronary artery bypass surgery) or a
             myocardial infarction within the 3 months prior to randomization 15. Underwent a
             successful or partially successful endovascular intervention for peripheral arterial
             occlusive disease. (ie. Aorta, iliac, femoral, popliteal, or tibial artery
             angioplasty, stenting, or atherectomy) within the prior 3 months.

             16. Endovascular coronary  intervention (ie. Angioplasty, atherectomy, stenting)
             within 1 month prior to randomization.

             17. Underwent a failed attempt for endovascular revascularization during the prior 1
             month. For the purpose of this exclusion criteria an endovascular procedure is
             considered a failure if: 1) The procedure is diagnostic only with no intervention
             performed, (for example in the case where wire crossing can not be obtained). 2) The
             treated artery recoils, thromboses, or dissects resulting in occlusion of the treated
             arterial segment, documented by intraoperative imaging.   Note that endovascular
             procedures with suboptimal results but not meeting criteria 1 or 2 above may qualify
             for inclusion after 3 months as in #15 above.

             18.  Cerebrovascular accident within 6 months prior to randomization. 19. Treatment
             with topical growth factors or hyperbaric oxygen (HBO) within 30 days, or systemic
             growth factor treatment within 6 months of enrollment.

             -
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mark Iafrati, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Tufts Medical Ctr</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>John Bonasera</last_name>
    <phone>508-732-7500</phone>
    <phone_ext>230</phone_ext>
    <email>jbonasera@harvesttech.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Jeffrey Lindquist</last_name>
    <phone>508-732-7500</phone>
    <phone_ext>219</phone_ext>
    <email>jlindquist@harvesttech.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Tufts Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02111</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ann Marie Melanson, RN</last_name>
      <phone>617-636-0730</phone>
      <email>amelanson@tufts-nemc.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Noah Rosen, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Roper St Francis Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Charleston</city>
        <state>South Carolina</state>
        <zip>29401</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Lorri Bennett, RN</last_name>
      <phone>843-720-8380</phone>
      <email>Lorri.Bennett@RSFH.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>John Hallett, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Baylor Medical Ctr</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dallas</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>75226</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Pamela Coker</last_name>
      <phone>214-820-2273</phone>
      <email>pamelaco@baylorhealth.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Gregory Pearl, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2011</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>July 8, 2011</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 18, 2010</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>John Bonasera, Director of Regulatory and Clinical Affairs</name_title>
    <organization>Harvest Technologies</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>CLI</keyword>
  <keyword>Critical Limb Ischemia</keyword>
  <keyword>PAOD</keyword>
  <keyword>Stem Cells</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Arterial Occlusive Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ischemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Peripheral Arterial Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Peripheral Vascular Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
</clinical_study>
