<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="261">
  <!-- This xml conforms to:  http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>Information obtained from ClinicalTrials.gov on October 20, 2011</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01269411</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CDR0000691784</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>PMH-PHL-075</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01269411</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>RO4929097 in Treating Patients With Recurrent Invasive Gliomas</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase I Pharmacodynamic and &quot;High Content&quot; Study of the Gamma-Secretase Inhibitor RO4929097 in Patients With Recurrent Malignant Gliomas (MGs) Targeting p75NTR to Inhibit Brain Tumor Initiating Cells (BTICs) and Recurrent Invasive Gliomas</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Princess Margaret Hospital, Canada</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      RATIONALE: RO4929097 may stop the growth of tumor cells by blocking some of the enzymes
      needed for cell growth.

      PURPOSE: This phase I trial is studying the side effects and best dose of RO4929097 in
      treating patients with recurrent invasive gliomas.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      OBJECTIVES:

      Primary

        -  To determine, in patients with recurrent MGs (many of whom receive dexamethasone, a
           moderate CYP3A4 inducer), the safety and maximum-tolerated dose of RO4909297
           administered at 2 dose levels. (part A)

        -  To determine the pharmacokinetics, intratumoral drug concentration, target modulation,
           and evidence of any treatment effect in the malignant glioma tumor tissue by R04929097
           administered at the dose found in Part A.

      Secondary

        -  To determine the pharmacokinetic (PK) profile of RO4909297 in patients with recurrent
           MGs (many of whom receive dexamethasone, a moderate CYP3A4 inducer). (part B)

        -  To determine the progression-free survival of patients with recurrent malignant glioma
           following treatment with R04929097.

        -  To determine if the RPTD dose of RO4929097 significantly inhibits p75^NTR cleavage and
           processing. (part B)

        -  To determine the effects of RO4929097 on the establishment and growth of BTIC cultures
           in neurosphere growth conditions, effects on proliferation, ability to self-renewal,
           and ability to differentiate along lineage-specific pathways. (part B)

        -  To determine the ability of RO4929097 to inhibit Notch signaling, by assessing
           downstream target activation, in glioma tissue of patients with recurrent MG. (part B)

        -  To determine the association between a number of serum, tumor, and BTIC markers and
           response to R04929097. (part B)

      OUTLINE: This is a multicenter, dose-escalation (part A) study followed by an open-label
      (part B) study.

        -  Part A: Patients receive oral RO4929097 once daily on days 1-3, 8-10, and 15-17.
           Courses repeat every 21 days in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable
           toxicity.

        -  Part B: Patients receive oral RO4929097 once daily on days 1-7 and undergo surgery on
           day 8. Beginning 28 days later, patients receive oral RO4929097 once daily on days 1-3,
           8-10, and 15-17. Courses repeat every 21 days in the absence of disease progression or
           unacceptable toxicity.

      Post resection tumor specimens are collected for correlative studies, including
      pharmacokinetic and biomarker assays.

      After completion of study therapy, patients are followed up at 30 days and then every 3
      month for up to 6-12 months.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2010</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2011</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Masking:  Open Label, Primary Purpose:  Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety and maximum-tolerated dose of RO4909297 (part A)</measure>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics, intratumoral drug concentration, target modulation, and evidence of any treatment effect</measure>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetic (PK) profile of RO4909297  (part B)</measure>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-free survival following treatment with R04929097</measure>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>If the RPTD dose of RO4929097 significantly inhibits p75NTR cleavage and processing (part B)</measure>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Effects of RO4929097 on the establishment and growth of BTIC cultures in neurosphere growth conditions, effects on proliferation, ability to self-renewal, and ability to differentiate along lineage-specific pathways (part B)</measure>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Ability of RO4929097 to inhibit Notch signaling, by assessing downstream target activation (part B)</measure>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Association between a number of serum, tumor, and BTIC markers and response to R04929097 (part B)</measure>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">22</enrollment>
  <condition>Brain and Central Nervous System Tumors</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>gamma-secretase/Notch signalling pathway inhibitor RO4929097</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>laboratory biomarker analysis</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>pharmacological study</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>therapeutic conventional surgery</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        DISEASE CHARACTERISTICS:

          -  Patients must have radiographic progression of a histologically confirmed
             glioblastoma, high-grade astrocytoma, NOS, anaplastic mixed oligo-astrocytoma, or
             anaplastic oligodendroglioma

               -  In patients that present radiographic evidence of progression after concurrent
                  treatment with radiation and low-dose temozolomide, diagnosis of progression
                  should be made after at least 2 cycles of monthly temozolomide in order to rule
                  out pseudoprogression

               -  Secondary MGs (evolving from a prior low-grade glioma) can be included as long
                  as they are considered malignant in the latest resection

          -  Patients must have at least one enhancing lesion that can be accurately measured as &gt;
             1 X 1 cm on a MRI

          -  Prior treatment must include radiotherapy (with or without temozolomide)

               -  No limit to the number of prior recurrences or surgeries

          -  For Part B only, surgical resection should be considered a reasonable therapeutic
             option for a patient that can tolerate surgical resection

               -  Patients with multifocal disease can be included as long as resection is
                  considered a reasonable option to manage the nodule that is progressing

               -  There must be sufficient tissue available (minimum from a 1 X 1 cm lesion) for a
                  biopsy to be taken during surgery

          -  There must be sufficient tissue available for evaluation of p75^NTR status from a
             prior surgery (using immunohistochemistry on fixed tissue or, in uncommon cases in
             which frozen tissue is available from a prior surgery, western blot) (part B)

        PATIENT CHARACTERISTICS:

          -  ECOG performance status &lt; 2 (Karnofsky &gt; 50%)

          -  Life expectancy of greater than 4 weeks

          -  Absolute neutrophil count &gt; 1,500/mcL

          -  Platelets &gt; 100,000/mcL

          -  Hemoglobin &gt; 90 g/L (or &gt; 9 g/dL)

          -  Total bilirubin &lt; 2.0 mg/dL

          -  BUN &lt; 25 mg/dL

          -  AST/ALT &lt; 3 X institutional upper limit of normal

          -  Creatinine within institutional normal limits OR creatinine clearance &gt; 60 mL/min

          -  No major medical illnesses or psychiatric impairments that, in the investigator's
             opinion, would prevent administration or completion of protocol therapy

          -  Not pregnant or nursing

          -  Negative serum pregnancy test

          -  Fertile patients must use two forms of contraception (i.e., barrier contraception and
             one other method of contraception) at least 4 weeks prior to study entry, during, and
             for 12 months after completion of study therapy

          -  Able to swallow pills

          -  Patients with a history of seizures need to have had no generalized seizures in the
             last month prior to entering the study

          -  No history of allergic reactions attributed to compounds of similar chemical or
             biologic composition to RO4929097

          -  No malabsorption syndrome or other condition that would interfere with intestinal
             absorption

          -  Patients who are serologically positive for hepatitis A, B, or C, and have a
             resulting positive serological test, or have a history of liver disease, other forms
             of hepatitis, or cirrhosis are ineligible

          -  No uncontrolled hypocalcemia, hypomagnesemia, hyponatremia, hypophosphatemia, or
             hypokalemia (within 7 days prior to study treatment), despite adequate electrolyte
             supplementation

          -  No uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to, ongoing or active
             infection, symptomatic congestive heart failure, unstable angina pectoris, cardiac
             arrhythmia other than chronic, stable atrial fibrillation, or psychiatric
             illness/social situations that would limit compliance with study requirements

          -  HIV-positive patients on combination antiretroviral therapy are ineligible

          -  Baseline QTc ≤ 450 msec (male) or QTc ≤ 470 msec (female)

          -  No history of risk factors for QT interval prolongation, including, but not limited
             to, family or personal history of long QT syndrome, recurrent syncope without known
             etiology, or sudden unexpected death

          -  No history of torsades de pointes or other significant cardiac arrhythmias or the
             need for concomitant meds with known potential to prolong QT interval or
             antiarrhythmics

        PRIOR CONCURRENT THERAPY:

          -  See Disease Characteristics

          -  Patients must have recovered from the effects of any prior treatment (systemic
             chemotherapy/radiotherapy) or surgery (&lt;CTCAE grade 2 toxicities related to prior
             therapy)

          -  Patients who have had chemotherapy, surgery, or radiotherapy within 4 weeks (6 weeks
             for nitrosoureas or mitomycin C) prior to entering the study are not eligible

          -  Patients may not be receiving any other investigational agents

          -  Patients cannot be receiving enzyme-inducing anti-epileptic drugs (EIAEDs)

               -  If previously treated with EIAEDs, patients must have been switched to
                  non-EIAEDs 4 weeks prior to starting RO4929097

               -  Enzyme-inducing antiepileptic drugs (EIAEDs) include: carbamazepine (Tegretol);
                  oxcarbazepine (Trileptal); phenobarbital (or derivatives); phenytoin (Dilantin)

               -  3.1.10.2 Non enzyme-inducing Antiepileptic Drugs (Non-EIAEDs) include: clobazam
                  (Frisium); clonazepam (Rivotril); gabapentin (Neurontin); levetiracetam
                  (Keppra); lamotrigine (Lamictal); topiramate (Topamax)

          -  No concurrent medications that are strong inducers/inhibitors or substrates of CYP3A4

               -  Even though dexamethasone is a moderate inducer of CYP3A4, patients may remain
                  on dexamethasone at the lowest dose possible

          -  Stable or decreasing steroid dose within 5 days prior to registration required

          -  No medications with narrow therapeutic indices that are metabolized by cytochrome
             P450 (CYP450), including warfarin sodium (Coumadin®)

          -  No other investigational or commercial agents or therapies may be administered with
             the intent to treat the patient's malignancy

          -  No re-irradiation (any technique) is allowed

          -  If a patient elects to have a new resection of his/her tumor in the absence of
             progression of the disease, treatment will be discontinued and no re-challenge will
             be allowed after this additional surgery

          -  Use of food that may interfere with the metabolism of RO4929097 is prohibited,
             including grapefruit or grapefruit juice
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Peter Forsyth, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Tom Baker Cancer Centre - Calgary</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Foothills Medical Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Calgary</city>
        <state>Alberta</state>
        <zip>T2N 2N9</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Tom Baker Cancer Centre - Calgary</name>
      <address>
        <city>Calgary</city>
        <state>Alberta</state>
        <zip>T2N 4N2</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Margaret and Charles Juravinski Cancer Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hamilton</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>L8V 5C2</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Princess Margaret Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>M5G 2M9</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Toronto Western Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>M5T 2S8</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://cancer.gov/clinicaltrials/PMH-PHL-075</url>
    <description>Clinical trial summary from the National Cancer Institute's PDQ® database</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>August 2011</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>August 27, 2011</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>December 31, 2010</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Malcolm J. Moore</name_title>
    <organization>Princess Margaret Hospital</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>adult anaplastic oligodendroglioma</keyword>
  <keyword>adult brain stem glioma</keyword>
  <keyword>adult giant cell glioblastoma</keyword>
  <keyword>adult glioblastoma</keyword>
  <keyword>adult gliosarcoma</keyword>
  <keyword>adult mixed glioma</keyword>
  <keyword>recurrent adult brain tumor</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Glioma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Nervous System Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Central Nervous System Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
</clinical_study>
