<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="159">
  <!-- This xml conforms to:  http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>Information obtained from ClinicalTrials.gov on October 20, 2011</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01265615</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>VDCRS03</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01265615</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Paricalcitol Versus Calcitriol for the Management of Renocardiac Syndrome in Renal Transplant Patients</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase 4 Study of Paricalcitol and Calcitriol for Reparative Management of Chronic Allograft Dysfunction and Renocardiac Syndrome in Vitamin D Insufficient Renal Transplant Recipients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Ural State Medical Academy</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Ural Institute of Cardiology</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Ural State Medical Academy</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Russia: Ethics Committee</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      We hypothesize that paricalcitol and calcitriol in dose-dependent manner are effective for
      the management of chronic allograft dysfunction (CAD), protection and repair of kidney and
      heart, management of chronic renocardiac syndrome (CRS). We assume that paricalcitol can
      have some advantages if compare with calcitriol or cholecalciferol due to absence of
      calcemic and phosphatemic complications alongside with great beneficial potential.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Paricalcitol and calcitriol are identically effective for the management of chronic
      allograft dysfunction (CAD), protection and repair of kidney and heart, management of
      chronic renocardiac syndrome (CRS). Vitamin D can reduce progression of CAD. Activation of
      VDR in proximal part of nephron leads to rapid non-genomic beneficial effects with urgent
      multilevel protection of the most functionally important portion of kidney. Rising
      expression of VDR in distal portions of nephron stimulates slows genomic effects with some
      local repair responses.

      Hormone D may stimulate recruitment and activity of the different origin stem-progenitor
      cells (SPCs) with beneficial effects on different stages of regeneration by force of para-
      and autocrine activity. SPCs are revealing mostly in interstitium and among fibroblast-like
      cells. Vitamin D did not confirm efficacy as a tool for management of  mesenchymal stem
      cells (MSCs) in human however it needs more research experimental evidences due to
      multifactorial influence on SPCs in human being including immunosuppressive and
      bone-marrow-related effects of cyclosporine in kidney transplant (Tx) patients. Paricalcitol
      and calcitriol can slow down migration and infiltration of MSC into interstitium and vessel
      wall. The side population of mature and SPCs (first of all, with bone-marrow and mesenchymal
      phenotype) is the most metabolically and functionally active portion of cells with high
      sensitivity to vitamin D receptor (VDR) activation that responsible for repair of tissue.

      The most optimal scheme of treatment with vitamin D in patients with CAD and CRS is an
      administration of paricalcitol with dose 2-4 μg daily and supplemental intake of vitamin D
      including special diet, multivitamins, and others with optimal dose until 1800 international
      units (IU) but excluding insolation as a factor of skin carcinoma. High-dose medicinal
      intake of calcitriol (until 6 mcg and higher) showed relatively high efficacy but rather
      excessive level of complications mediated with mineral metabolism.

      Paricalcitol and calcitriol may significantly improve contractility of myocardium and reduce
      cardiovascular risk, heart failure (HF) and hypertension with some beneficial effects on
      cardiorenal axis and renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 2010</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 2010</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation:  Randomized, Endpoint Classification:  Pharmacokinetics/Dynamics Study, Intervention Model:  Parallel Assignment, Masking:  Double Blind (Subject, Investigator), Primary Purpose:  Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>CAD (Chronic Allograft Dysfunction) Degree</measure>
    <time_frame>day 180 after Tx (transplantation)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Beyond 180 days, chronic allograft dysfunction (CAD) was characterized by mean Banff degree (revised 2005/2007 criteria) with the data of renal biopsy material. Renal tissue was recovered during routined biopsy. We assessed antibody-mediated rejection, borderline changes, T-cell-mediated rejection, interstitial fibrosis and tubular atropthy, and other changes. Grades:
Grade I. Mild interstitial fibrosis and tubular atrophy (&lt;25% of cortical area) II. Moderate (26-50%) III. Severe (&gt;50%) (may include non-specific vascular and glomerular sclerosis)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Heart Failure (HF)</measure>
    <time_frame>on day 180 after Tx (transplantation)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>NYHA (New York Heart Association) functional class verified with veloergometry probe and by NYHA clinical classification NYHA Class  Symptoms I  No symptoms and no limitation in ordinary physical activity, e.g. shortness of breath when walking, climbing stairs etc.
II  Mild symptoms and slight limitation during ordinary activity. III  Marked limitation in activity due to symptoms, even during less-than-ordinary activity, e.g. walking short distances (20-100 m).
Comfortable only at rest. IV  Severe limitations. Experiences symptoms even while at rest. Mostly bedbound patients.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>GFR (Glomerular Filtration Rate)</measure>
    <time_frame>on day 180</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Estimated glomerular filtration rate (eGFR) was calculated using the abbreviated form of the Modification of Diet in Renal Disease (MDRD) study equation: eGFR = exp (5.228 − 1.154 × ln (serum creatinine) − 0.203 × ln (age). Concerning of GFR with Tc99m DTPA renography was used for the complex analysis of renal function. Camera based GFR estimated from Tc99m DTPA renography was named Gates GFR.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>CAD (Chronic Allograft Dysfunction) Degree</measure>
    <time_frame>on day 90</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>CAD degree measured by Banff score after routine renal biopsy (revised 2005/2007 criteria). We assessed antibody-mediated rejection, borderline changes, T-cell-mediated rejection, interstitial fibrosis and tubular atropthy, and other changes. Grades:
Grade I. Mild interstitial fibrosis and tubular atrophy (&lt;25% of cortical area) II. Moderate (26-50%) III. Severe (&gt;50%) (may include non-specific vascular and glomerular sclerosis)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Serum Creatinine</measure>
    <time_frame>on day 180 after Tx</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>After an overnight fast, plasma concentrations of hemoglobin, creatinine, cholesterol, glucose, total calcium, and phosphate were measured using an autoanalyzer as described by Adorini L. (2005)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Circulating SP (Side Population) Stem-Progenitor Cells</measure>
    <time_frame>on day 180</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Renal cells and solid tissue were obtained from the normal portion of cortex obtained from surgically removed kidneys or by standart biopsy on day 180. Cytofluorimetric analysis and immunofluorescence were performed as described by Oliver J.A. (2004). Sorting and analysis of different cells was done on a FACS (fluorescent activated cell sorting) and by flow cytometry. Cells were analyzed with EPICS systems (Beckman Coulter). Quantification of mRNA expression was achieved using Assays-on-Demand gene expression kits and the ABI PRISM 7000 Sequence Detection System (Applied Biosystem).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>VDR (Vitamin D Receptor) Expression in Myocardium</measure>
    <time_frame>on day 180</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>VDR content was determined by using an ELISA developed in this laboratory. The protein concentration of the homogenates was determined by the method of Bradford (1976), using BSA as a standard.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>VDR (Vitamin D Receptor) Expression in Kidney</measure>
    <time_frame>on day 180</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>VDR content was determined by using an ELISA developed in this laboratory. The protein concentration of the homogenates was determined by the method of Bradford (1976), using BSA as a standard.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Systolic Blood Pressure</measure>
    <time_frame>on day 180</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>SBP measured by routine method</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Coronary Calcium Score</measure>
    <time_frame>on day 180</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Bone mineral density assessed by dual-energy X-ray absorptiometry (DXA) of the whole body, lumbar spine and hip was performed using Hologic scanners (QDR 1000W or QDR 2000). The total Agatston coronary calcium score (CCS) was measured as the sum of calcified plaque scores of all the coronary arteries. The amount of calcium present in the coronary arteries is scored according to the Agatson scale, as follows: 0 - no identifiable disease; 1 to 99 - mild disease; 100 to 399 - moderate disease; 400 or higher - severe disease.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">109</enrollment>
  <condition>Cardiorenal Syndrome</condition>
  <condition>Chronic Allograft Nephropathy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Paricalcitol treatment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>6-8 μg daily per os (orally) without special diet</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Calcitriol treatment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>2-4 μg daily orally under with dietary restrictions of vitamin D</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cholecalciferol</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>alendronate sodium/ cholecalciferol capsules with recommended daily allowance equals 1200-2400 IU per day</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Supplemental</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>intake of cholecalciferol in food and multivitamins, less than 400-900 IU per day</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Paricalcitol</intervention_name>
    <description>paricalcitol group (6-8 μg daily per os - orally - without special diet)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Paricalcitol treatment</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Zemplar</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Calcitriol</intervention_name>
    <description>calcitriol group (2-4 μg daily orally under with dietary restrictions of vitamin D)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Calcitriol treatment</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Rocaltrol</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cholecalciferol</intervention_name>
    <description>cholecalciferol group (intake of cholecalciferol with recommended daily allowance equals 1200-2400 IU per day)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cholecalciferol</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Fosamax</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Supplemental</intervention_name>
    <description>intake of cholecalciferol in food and multivitamins, less than 400-900 IU per day</description>
    <arm_group_label>Supplemental</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Diet, sun, multivitamin drugs, food</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age 40-75

          -  Male

          -  History of chronic kidney disease and cardiorenal syndrome

          -  Written informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Female

          -  Acute illness

          -  Life-threat competitive illness

          -  Mental disorders

          -  Endocrinologic diseases (including diabetes mellitus, hyperparathyroidism, and other
             thyroid disorders)

          -  Need for dialyses

          -  Hypercalcemia

          -  Concomitant use of hormone or cytokine medication

          -  Participation to any drug-investigation during the previous 60 days as checked with
             VIP check
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>40 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Alexander Kharlamov, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Ural Institute of Cardiology</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Alexander Perrish, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Ural State Medical Academy</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ural Institute of Cardiology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Yekaterinburg</city>
        <zip>620144</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Russian Federation</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.cardio-burg.ru</url>
    <description>Ural Institute of Cardiology</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.usma.ru</url>
    <description>Ural State Medical Academy</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>November 2010</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 23, 2011</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>December 22, 2010</firstreceived_date>
  <firstreceived_results_date>December 27, 2010</firstreceived_results_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Jan Gabinsky/ Prof. Dr., C.E.O.</name_title>
    <organization>Ural Institute of Cardiology</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>chronic allograft nephropathy</keyword>
  <keyword>stem-progenitor cells</keyword>
  <keyword>cardiorenal syndrome</keyword>
  <keyword>calcitriol</keyword>
  <keyword>paricalcitol</keyword>
  <keyword>cholecalciferol</keyword>
  <keyword>cardiac repair</keyword>
  <keyword>renal repair</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Kidney Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Calcitriol</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cholecalciferol</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vitamin D</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ergocalciferols</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vitamins</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
</clinical_study>
