<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="177">
  <!-- This xml conforms to:  http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>Information obtained from ClinicalTrials.gov on October 20, 2011</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01254578</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CDR0000688918</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>OSU-2010C0069</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01254578</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Lenalidomide After Donor Bone Marrow Transplant in Treating Patients With High-Risk Hematologic Cancers</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 1 Study of Lenalidomide Maintenance Following Allogeneic Hematopoietic Cell Transplantation in Patients With Select High Risk Hematological Malignancies</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Arthur G. James Cancer Hospital &amp; Richard J. Solove Research Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Unspecified</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      RATIONALE: Biological therapies, such as lenalidomide, may stimulate the immune system in
      different ways and stop cancer cells from growing.

      PURPOSE: This phase I clinical trial is studying the side effects and the best dose of
      lenalidomide after donor bone marrow transplant in treating patients with high-risk
      hematologic cancer.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      OBJECTIVES:

      Primary

        -  To determine the maximal-tolerable dose (MTD) of lenalidomide after allogeneic
           hematopoietic stem cell transplantation (AHSCT) in patients with advanced acute myeloid
           leukemia (AML), non-Hodgkin's lymphoma (NHL), or chronic lymphocytic leukemia (CLL).

        -  To define the qualitative and quantitative toxicities of lenalidomide in regard to
           organ specificity, time course, predictability, and reversibility following AHSCT in
           these patients.

      Secondary

        -  To determine the anti-tumor response in patients treated with lenalidomide after AHSCT
           when compared with historical controls.

        -  To evaluate the plasma and cellular pharmacokinetics of lenalidomide in patients
           enrolled on this study and interactions with supportive agents such as calcineurin
           inhibitors.

        -  To evaluate the frequency of acute and chronic graft-vs-host disease and graft failure
           in patients enrolled on this study.

        -  To prospectively assess the feasibility of administering an oral agent post-transplant
           as measured by efficiency of patients being registered to therapy early and also
           meeting eligibility criteria for lenalidomide treatment.

        -  To perform pharmacodynamic studies following lenalidomide treatment including
           development of B, T, and myeloid cell chimerism; assessment of immune activation;
           cytokines; tumor cell expression of co-stimulatory molecules; development of anti-tumor
           antibodies and immunoglobulin recovery; and re-expression of microRNAs that may mediate
           lenalidomide anti-tumor effect.

      OUTLINE: This is a multicenter, dose-escalation study. Patients are stratified according to
      diagnosis (high-risk acute myeloid leukemia vs non-Hodgkin lymphoma vs high-risk chronic
      lymphocytic leukemia, small lymphocytic lymphoma, or B-prolymphocytic leukemia).

      Patients receive oral lenalidomide once daily on days 1-28. Courses repeat every 28 days for
      up to 24 courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.

      Patients undergo blood and bone marrow biopsies and aspirate collection at baseline and
      periodically during study for pharmacokinetic and pharmacodynamic studies. Buccal swab
      samples are also collected at baseline and analyzed for genetic polymorphisms.

      After completion of study therapy, patients are followed up for up to 1 year.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2010</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Masking:  Open Label, Primary Purpose:  Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximal-tolerable dose (MTD) of lenalidomide after allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell transplantation</measure>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall response in patients treated with lenalidomide</measure>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">90</enrollment>
  <condition>Leukemia</condition>
  <condition>Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Neoplastic Syndrome</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>lenalidomide</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Genetic</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>polymorphism analysis</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>laboratory biomarker analysis</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>pharmacological study</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        DISEASE CHARACTERISTICS:

          -  Histologically confirmed hematologic malignancy meeting 1 of the following criteria:

               -  High-risk acute myeloid leukemia meeting 1 the following criteria:

                    -  First complete response (CR) and ≥ 60 years of age OR &lt; 60 years of age
                       with high-risk cytogenetics as defined by CALGB OR high-molecular risk and
                       not eligible or willing to undergo myeloablative conditioning

                    -  Second or later complete remission

                    -  Not in remission but with &lt; 5% blasts within 3 weeks of start of
                       conditioning chemotherapy for allogeneic transplantation

                    -  Patients with a history of CNS involvement allowed provided disease is in
                       remission at the time of transplantation

               -  Non-Hodgkin lymphoma (NHL) meeting 1 of the following criteria:

                    -  Follicular lymphoma (grades 1, 2, or 3a by WHO criteria) or monocytoid
                       lymphoma that has relapsed after ≥ 2 prior chemotherapy regimens AND no
                       lymph node groups ≥ 3 cm OR ≥ 50% reduction in estimated lymph node
                       diameter with most recent salvage therapy

                    -  Diffuse large B-cell NHL that has relapsed after an autologous stem cell
                       transplant but is still sensitive to chemotherapy by virtue of a partial
                       response (PR) or CR after most recent salvage chemotherapy

                    -  Transformed follicular lymphoma that has achieved a PR or CR following
                       chemotherapy

                    -  Mantle cell lymphoma that has relapsed after ≥ 2 prior different
                       chemotherapy regimens (this could include autologous transplantation)

                    -  Peripheral T-cell NHL or angioimmunoblastic lymphoma that has relapsed but
                       is still chemotherapy sensitive

                    -  Recurrent ALK-negative anaplastic large cell lymphoma that is chemotherapy
                       sensitive

               -  High-risk chronic lymphocytic leukemia (CLL), small lymphocytic lymphoma (SLL),
                  or primary and secondary B-prolymphocytic leukemia (PLL) meeting 1 of the
                  following criteria:

                    -  del(17p13.1) disease that has been treated (may have been given as
                       consolidation therapy)

                    -  Less than PR to chemoimmunotherapy or relapsed within 2 years of treatment

                    -  Nucleoside analog refractory disease or disease that relapsed after two
                       prior regimens

                    -  Patients with Richter (large cell) transformation allowed provided the
                       large cell component of the disease is in remission (&lt; 10% large cells in
                       the bone marrow allowed)

          -  Patient has undergone an allogeneic stem cell transplantation using a
             reduced-intensity or non-myeloablative conditioning regimen within the past 60 days

               -  At least 40% T-cell donor chimerism at day 30

        PATIENT CHARACTERISTICS:

          -  ECOG performance status 0-2 (Karnofsky 60-100%)

          -  Life expectancy &gt; 3 months

          -  Myeloid engraftment with absolute neutrophil count &gt; 1,000/μL and platelet count &gt;
             50,000/μL (after allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell transplantation [AHSCT])

          -  Total bilirubin normal

          -  AST and ALT ≤ 2.5 times upper limit of normal (ULN)

               -  AST &lt; 3 times ULN after AHSCT

          -  Creatinine clearance ≥ 60 mL/min

          -  DLCO &gt; 40% with no symptomatic pulmonary disease

          -  LVEF ≥ 30% by echocardiogram or MUGA

          -  Not pregnant or nursing

          -  Negative pregnancy test

          -  Fertile patients must agree to use two acceptable methods of contraception (one
             highly effective method and one additional effective method) or practice abstinence
             for ≥ 28 days before, during, and ≥ 28 days after completing lenalidomide

          -  HIV negative

          -  No uncontrolled infection requiring intravenous therapy or poorly controlled diabetes
             mellitus

          -  No history of allergic reactions attributed to compounds of similar chemical or
             biologic composition to lenalidomide

          -  No uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to, any of the
             following:

               -  Ongoing or active infection

               -  Symptomatic congestive heart failure

               -  Unstable angina pectoris

               -  Cardiac arrhythmia

               -  Psychiatric illness and/or social situations that would limit compliance with
                  study requirements

          -  No history of grade 3 or 4 graft-vs-host disease (GVHD)

               -  If patient has acute GVHD grade 1 or 2, GVHD must be controlled and dose of oral
                  prednisone or equivalent ≤ 20 mg per day (after AHSCT)

        PRIOR CONCURRENT THERAPY:

          -  See Disease Characteristics

          -  More than 4 weeks since prior chemotherapy (excluding steroids), radiotherapy, or
             radioimmunoconjugate therapy (6 weeks for nitrosoureas or mitomycin C) and recovered

          -  No other concurrent investigational agents
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Leslie Andritsos, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Arthur G. James Cancer Hospital &amp; Richard J. Solove Research Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Arthur G. James Cancer Hospital and Richard J. Solove Research Institute at Ohio State University Comprehensive Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Columbus</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>43210-1240</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ohio State University Cancer Clinical Trial Matching Service</last_name>
      <phone>866-627-7616</phone>
      <email>osu@emergingmed.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://cancer.gov/clinicaltrials/OSU-2010C0069</url>
    <description>Clinical trial summary from the National Cancer Institute's PDQ® database</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>December 2010</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>December 16, 2010</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>December 3, 2010</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Leslie Andritsos</name_title>
    <organization>Arthur G. James Cancer Hospital and Richard J. Solove Research Institute at Ohio State University Comprehensive Cancer Center</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>adult acute myeloid leukemia with 11q23 (MLL) abnormalities</keyword>
  <keyword>adult acute myeloid leukemia with del(5q)</keyword>
  <keyword>adult acute myeloid leukemia with inv(16)(p13;q22)</keyword>
  <keyword>adult acute myeloid leukemia with t(15;17)(q22;q12)</keyword>
  <keyword>adult acute myeloid leukemia with t(16;16)(p13;q22)</keyword>
  <keyword>adult acute myeloid leukemia with t(8;21)(q22;q22)</keyword>
  <keyword>recurrent adult diffuse large cell lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>recurrent adult T-cell leukemia/lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>recurrent grade 1 follicular lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>recurrent grade 2 follicular lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>recurrent grade 3 follicular lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>recurrent mantle cell lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>angioimmunoblastic T-cell lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>refractory chronic lymphocytic leukemia</keyword>
  <keyword>recurrent small lymphocytic lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>prolymphocytic leukemia</keyword>
  <keyword>Richter syndrome</keyword>
  <keyword>adult acute myeloid leukemia in remission</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hematologic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lenalidomide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Thalidomide</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
</clinical_study>
