<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="86">
  <!-- This xml conforms to:  http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>Information obtained from ClinicalTrials.gov on October 20, 2011</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01270139</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NANOM</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01270139</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Plasmonic Nanophotothermic Therapy of Atherosclerosis</brief_title>
  <acronym>NANOM</acronym>
  <official_title>Silica-Gold Nanoparticles and Mesenchymal Stem Cells Versus Composite Ferro-Magnetic Approach For Management of Atherosclerotic Plaque and Artery Remodeling</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Ural State Medical Academy</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Ural Institute of Cardiology</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Ural State Medical Academy</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Russia: Ethics Committee</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The investigators hypothesize that nanoburning is very challenging technique to demolish and
      reverse the plaque especially in combination with stem cell technologies promising
      functional restoration of the vessel wall.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Cardiovascular disease (CVD) is one of the main cause of disability and death worldwide. The
      underlying cause generally is atherosclerosis and more in particular thrombotic rupture of
      an atherosclerotic plaque in a vital artery. The restoration of blood flow to ischemic
      myocardium is established as the preeminent objective for treatment of patients with CVD .
      Some modern angioplasty techniques generally just manipulate the form of the plaque and have
      some clinical and technical restrictions, relatively high complication rate and restenosis
      risk.

      The most common techniques in current practice are angioplasty with stenting, and CABG
      surgery (for patients with multivessel disease). Balloon angioplasty and stenting in fact
      manage the form of the plaque, and does not create a significant problem of plaque residue
      flowing from the site. Once a role for elective stent implantation was established, the next
      goal was to overcome the complications of subacute stent thrombosis (first of all, with the
      use of drug-eluting stents) and neointimal hyperplasia (bare-metal stents) through
      pharmacologic and physical means. Among unresolved issues the investigators can describe
      restrictions in patients with stenosis of an unprotected left main coronary artery,
      multivessel disease, diabetes mellitus, still rather high rate of in-stent restenosis, and
      as a solution of the problem with a foreign body in vessel, the development of biodegradable
      stents. Among physical obstacles for stenting the investigators may note that
      atherosclerotic plaque build-up can exist in a number of different forms. The plaque can be
      quite hard and scaly, or more fatty and pliable. Moreover, Dr. Peters D. with colleagues
      from Santa-Barbara (2009) published own data about new modular, multifunctional micelles
      that contain a targeting element, a fluorophore, and, when desired, a drug component in the
      same particle. Targeting atherosclerotic plaques in ApoE-KO mice fed a high-fat diet was
      accomplished with the pentapeptide cysteine-arginine-glutamic acid-lysine-alanine, which
      binds to clotted plasma proteins. The fluorescent micelles bind to the entire surface of the
      plaque, and notably, concentrate at the shoulders of the plaque, a location that is prone to
      rupture. They also show that the targeted micelles deliver an increased concentration of the
      anticoagulant drug hirulog to the plaque compared with untargeted micelles that may reduce
      bleeding complications and atherogenesis.

      Moreover, the ability of statin drugs to reduce the volume of atherosclerotic plaque in the
      coronary artery wall, termed plaque regression, has received much attention. The statins
      have a remarkable track record of lowering cholesterol and improving survival. Apart from
      lowering low-density lipoprotein cholesterol (LDL-C) levels, they also have a multitude of
      other actions, often collectively described as pleiotropic effects. JUPITER (2003), REVERSAL
      (2004), PROVE IT (2004), ESTABLISH (2004), and ASTEROID (2006) trials have showed that low
      LDL levels after intensive statin therapy when accompanied by raised HDL, can regress, or
      partially reverse, the plaque buildup in the coronary arteries. The findings suggest that
      the various components of atheroma respond differently to treatment with medical therapies,
      and can be used to target plaques that are likely to respond. Thus, lipid pool, inflammatory
      reaction in the forms of cellular migration, humoral substance release, and edema are still
      the most likely to be targets of pharmacotherapy. But, for instance, fibrous tissue, mineral
      deposits, and ground substance would seem to be irreversible despite metabolic manipulation.

      Numerous devices recently have been described that utilize the application of heat to
      resolve atherosclerotic plaque (laser technique, electrosurgical removing of plaque, or with
      the use of radio frequency sparking, and others). Plasmonics is a novel invasive approach in
      medicine, and metal nanoparticles are a new type of optically active composite spherical one
      consisting of a dielectric core covered by a thin metallic shell which is typically gold.
      When nanoparticles are irradiated with near-infrared laser, they absorb energy, which is
      quickly transferred through nonradiative relaxation into heat and accompanied effects, and
      eventually leads to irreparable damage of tissue. In oncology, metal nanoparticles may
      provide a novel means of targeted plasmonic photothermal therapy (PPTT) in tumor tissue,
      minimizing damage to surrounding healthy tissue. However, this approach does not use in
      cardiology today possessing the great potential for angioplasty. The efficiency of
      nanotechnologies, however, is limited by gaps in the current understanding of the thermal
      interactions between nanoparticles and laser light pulses or continuous waves in the context
      of complex biological environments. Irradiation, even with moderate pulses of energy, can
      induce melting, evaporation, and fragmentation of nanoparticles. These events can
      drastically alter the intended therapeutic effects and lead to the formation of vapor
      bubbles as well as acoustic waves and shock waves . But the last disadvantages can become
      advantages depending on purposes of the treatment. Thus the study opens a new chapter in the
      history of plasmonics.

      The investigators designed this study to check potent clinical opportunities, efficacy and
      safety of such novel technique for angioplasty as plasmonic atherodestruction. The
      investigators have drawn the following research questions: 1) Is it possible to
      plasmonically entirely destruct a plaque with minimal complications? 2) What level of safety
      is typical for the different approaches if compare with stenting? 3) What are advantages and
      disadvantages of the different delivery techniques - stem cells or magnetic field? 4) What
      is the meaning of the transplanted mesenchymal CD73+CD105+ stem-progenitor cells for the
      atherosclerosis management? 5) Can plasmonic nanophotothermal therapy (PPTT) get an
      alternative to stenting?

      Plasmonic photothermic therapy (PPTT) can potentially reduce a volume of plaque. PPTT melts
      an atherosclerotic plaque tissue with irreparable burning of targeted tissues, vapor
      bubbling of cellular cytoplasm and extracellular matrix with subsequent degradation of
      tissues, and destructive effects of acoustic and shock waves as the possible plaque-killing
      mechanisms. NPs are absolutely safe for an organism but entire kinetics is mostly unknown.
      The most dangerous approach with lowest level of efficacy and safety is a delivery of NPs
      with microbubbles if compare with stem cell-based one. Mesenchymal stem cells have
      appropriate effectiveness as a local delivery system with a lot of beneficial properties
      such as anti-inflamative, anti-apoptotic, and multi-metabolic effects leading to the plaque
      degradation. Thus, PPTT can become an alternative to stenting.

      Among potential problems the investigators may name 1) technique of the delivery of these
      nanoparticles directly into the plaque (stem cells, aleuronic microbubbles with surfaced
      antibodies (as a local delivery system), direct injection or infusion into the coronary
      arteries and plaques during CABG or PCI); 2)  high risk of acute fatal atherothrombosis at
      the heat site due to destruction of the fibrous cap of plaque (role of nanoparticles
      adhesion on the surface of endothelium); 3) long-term effects of the nanodestruction locally
      and in entire organism (distribution and effects of accumulation in different organs); 4)
      mechanism of this effect (plasmonic microexplosion and burning of tissue, lysis of cells due
      to vapor bubbling of cellular cytoplasm and extracellular tissues, destructive acoustic and
      shock waves); 5) optimal biophysical parameters and necessary energy levels of
      nanodetonation to prevent burning of surrounding tissues and perforation of the vessel; 6)
      plasmonic damage is irreparable, and it means the investigators have to combine it with
      another biotechnology for the restoration of vessel such as the use of stem cells; 7)
      optimal type of stem cells (source, origin, level of differentiation, potential,
      properties).

      So, disadvantages of current low-invasive approaches (stenting, statin drugs, and others,
      laser, electrosurgery devices):

        -  Foreign body in the heart

        -  Restenosis, including neointimal hyperplasia (adventitial and circulating
           stem-progenitor cells of different origin are involved)

        -  Risk of fatal acute or sub-acute atherothrombosis (including 'in-stent' sub-acute
           atherothrombosis)

        -  Non-pathogenetic - cannot reverse or significantly regress the plaque

        -  No effect for remodeling and calcification (restriction for necessary remodeling)

        -  Clinical restrictions for some group (multivessel disease, left main CAD, diabetes
           mellitus, severe CAD and etc), on the another hand, CABG is very traumatic procedure
           (solution - MICS, including achievements in endoscopic stereotaxic surgery), but CABG
           is still an approach in charge in severe or high-risk patients

      Disadvantages of the approach:

        -  Necessity of the special delivery technique

        -  Lost function of artery - irreparable pro-fibrotic damage - necessity of another
           clinical management for restoration of tissue - necessity of the restoration therapy
           with stem cells

        -  Threat of acute fatal atherothrombosis due to rupture of (vulnerable) plaque

        -  Cannot treat non-organic part of plaque - necessity of the special therapy - stem cells

        -  Harm of potent detrimental side-effects - vapor bubbling (boiling of cytoplasm and ECM
           with subsequent lysis of cells, and provocation of pro-apoptotic cascades), acoustic
           and shock waves due to plasma-generated laser-related detonation of nanoshells in
           tissue

        -  Erratic (uncontrollable) heating - surrounding tissue of the site of interest can
           achieve a temperature until 38-39°. But at the site of burning final temperature can be
           at about 50-180 C (cauterization/ searing/ melting effect) with following pro-fibrous
           effect of tissue.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">August 2011</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation:  Randomized, Endpoint Classification:  Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model:  Parallel Assignment, Masking:  Double Blind (Subject, Investigator), Primary Purpose:  Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Plaque volume</measure>
    <time_frame>in 12th month after intervention</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Plaque volume on month 12</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Composition of plaque</measure>
    <time_frame>in month 12 after intervention</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>composition of plaque</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>event free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>in month 12 after intervention</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>event free survival</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>restenosis rate</measure>
    <time_frame>in month 12 after intervention</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>restenosis rate</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>acute atherothrombosis rate</measure>
    <time_frame>at month 12 after intervention</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>acute atherothrombosis rate</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>coronary flow-mediated vasodilation</measure>
    <time_frame>in month 12 after intervention</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>coronary flow-mediated vasodilation</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>intima-media thickness</measure>
    <time_frame>in month 12 after intervention</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>intima-media thickness</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">180</enrollment>
  <condition>Stable Angina</condition>
  <condition>Heart Failure</condition>
  <condition>Atherosclerosis</condition>
  <condition>Multivessel Coronary Artery Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Nanogroup</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>60 patients into nanogroup with the use of 60/15-70/40 nm silica-gold nanoparticles (NPs) transplanted by endoscopic cardiac surgery in the composition of bioengineered on-artery patch grown on the basis of biopolymeric scaffold and host circulating CD45-CD34-CD73+CD105+ progenitor cells</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ferro-magnetic group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>60 - into ferro-magnetic group with 60/15-70/40 nm silica-gold iron-bearing NPs with delivery in hand of magnetic navigation system</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Stenting control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>60 - in sirolimus-eluting stenting control</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Transplantation of nanoparticles</intervention_name>
    <description>60 patients into nanogroup with the use of 60/15-70/40 nm silica-gold nanoparticles (NPs) transplanted by endoscopic cardiac surgery in the composition of bioengineered on-artery patch grown on the basis of biopolymeric scaffold and host circulating CD45-CD34-CD73+CD105+ progenitor cells</description>
    <arm_group_label>Nanogroup</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Transplantation of ferro-magnetic nanoparticles</intervention_name>
    <description>60 - into ferro-magnetic group with 60/15-70/40 nm silica-gold iron-bearing NPs with delivery in hand of magnetic navigation system</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ferro-magnetic group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Put in stenting</intervention_name>
    <description>60 - in sirolimus-eluting stenting control</description>
    <arm_group_label>Stenting control</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age 45-65 years old

          -  Male and female

          -  Multivessel coronary artery disease without indications for CABG

          -  Stable angina with indications for PCI

          -  NYHA II-III functional class of heart failure

          -  De novo treatment

          -  Atherosclerosis of proximal left anterior descending artery with &lt;50% stenosis

          -  Non-calcified atherosclerosis

          -  Treated hypertension

          -  Signed written informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of MI

          -  History of PCI, CABG

          -  Indications for CABG

          -  Contraindications for PCI, CABG

          -  History of unstable angina

          -  History of atrial fibrillation, or other arrhythmias

          -  History of stroke

          -  NYHA I, IV functional class of heart failure

          -  Diabetes mellitus (fasting glucose &gt; 7.0 mmol/L or random glucose &gt; 11.0 mmol/L)

          -  Untreated hypertension (in supine position: systole&gt;140 mm Hg, diastole &gt; 90 mmHg)

          -  Smoking

          -  History of any cardiovascular disease

          -  Asthma

          -  Participation to any drug-investigation during the previous 60 days as checked with
             VIP check
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>45 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jan Gabinsky, M.D., Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Ural Institute of Cardiology</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Olga Kovtun, M.D., Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Ural State Medical Academy</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Alexander Kharlamov, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Ural Institute of Cardiology</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ural Institute of Cardiology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Yekaterinburg</city>
        <state>Sverdlovsk oblast</state>
        <zip>620144</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Russian Federation</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.cardio-burg.ru</url>
    <description>Ural Institute of Cardiology</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.usma.ru</url>
    <description>Ural State Medical Academy</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>September 2011</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>September 8, 2011</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>December 30, 2010</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>nanoparticles</keyword>
  <keyword>mesenchymal stem cell</keyword>
  <keyword>plasmonics</keyword>
  <keyword>atherosclerosis</keyword>
  <keyword>IVUS</keyword>
  <keyword>stenting</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Atherosclerosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Coronary Artery Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myocardial Ischemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Coronary Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Heart Failure</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
</clinical_study>
