<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="268">
  <!-- This xml conforms to:  http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>Information obtained from ClinicalTrials.gov on October 20, 2011</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01245270</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>REC 10/S0801/54</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>902</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01245270</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study of Acute Oral Administration of Anthocyanins on Insulin Resistance</brief_title>
  <official_title>Study of Acute Oral Administration of Anthocyanins on Insulin Resistance</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Aberdeen</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Aberdeen</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United Kingdom: Research Ethics Committee</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Dietary strategies for alleviating the metabolic complications such as diabetes associated
      with obesity are actively being pursued as alternatives to pharmaceutical interventions. The
      genus Vaccinium (e.g. blueberry, blaeberry, cranberry) has been used traditionally as a
      source of folk remedies for established diabetic symptoms, primarily as leaf or stem
      infusions or decoctions. Berries from this family such as blaeberry (BL) and blueberry (BB)
      are enriched in anthocyanins, polyphenolics recognized for their ability to provide and
      activate cellular antioxidant protection, inhibit inflammatory gene expression, and
      consequently protect against oxidant-induced and inflammatory cell damage and cytotoxicity.
      The association of obesity with adipose tissue stress, macrophage recruitment, and
      inflammatory gene expression suggests that eating edible berries from this genus might
      provide an effective alternative or supplementary intervention to attenuate obesity-
      associated inflammation and the associated insulin resistance.

      The aim of this study is to determine the acute effects of anthocyanin supplementation on
      insulin resistance, inflammation and bioavailability following a single acute dose taken
      orally as a capsule of a concentrated bilberry/blaeberry extract which is rich in
      anthocyanins.  This study will also provide information on the levels of anthocyanins in the
      patients' blood, urine and faeces.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation:  Randomized, Endpoint Classification:  Efficacy Study, Intervention Model:  Crossover Assignment, Masking:  Double Blind (Subject, Investigator), Primary Purpose:  Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Plasma glucose</measure>
    <time_frame>Plasma will also be collected over 24 hours post single intervention</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Change in non fasted glucose following single intervention or placebo over the 24hr period</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Bioavailability in plasma</measure>
    <time_frame>Plasma will also be collected -15,-10, -5, 15, 30, 45, 60, 90, 120, 150, and 300 minutes and 24 hours post intervention</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To measure the amount of anthocyanins and phenolic-derived metabolites by liquid chromatography mass spectrometry (LC-MS) being absorbed from the gut and excreted following the single intervention.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Bioavailability in urine</measure>
    <time_frame>Urine will also be collected (if possible) 0, 1, 3 and 5 hours, with all urine collected within the 24 hour time period post intervention</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To measure the amount of anthocyanins and phenolic-derived metabolites by liquid chromatography mass spectrometry (LC-MS) being absorbed from the gut and excreted following the single intervention.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Bioavailability in faeces</measure>
    <time_frame>Faecal sample  will be collected 24 hr post intervention</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To measure the amount of anthocyanins and phenolic-derived metabolites by liquid chromatography mass spectrometry (LC-MS) being absorbed from the gut and excreted following the single intervention.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">12</enrollment>
  <condition>Type 2 Diabetes</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Blaeberry concentrated capsule</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Volunteers will be given a single capsule of 0.47 grams of mirtoselect (a concentrated blaeberry extract)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo caspules</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Volunteers will be given a single placebo capsule</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Mirtoselect</intervention_name>
    <description>Male subjects aged &gt;40 and &lt;70 years, with type 2 diabetes controlling their diabetes by diet alone closely matched for adiposity as determined by waist circumference (n=12).
Volunteers will be randomised double blinded into two groups (n=12 per group) and given a single capsule of either 0.47 grams of a blaeberry extract (mirtoselect provided by Indena S.p.A (http://www.mirtoselect.info/)  or a control capsule. Following a two week wash out period the volunteers will be asked to take a second single capsule of either of 0.47 grams of mirtoselect  or a control gelatin capsule in a cross over study, the opposite of what they took the first time.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Blaeberry concentrated capsule</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo caspules</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male subjects

          -  Aged &gt;40 and &lt;70

          -  Clinical diagnosis of Type 2 diabetes controlling their diabetes  by diet alone

          -  All subjects must live in the Aberdeenshire area of Scotland

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Medical exclusion criteria

          -  Clinical diagnosis of thromboembolic or coagulation disease

          -  Clinical diagnosis of unregulated thyroid disease

          -  Clinical diagnosis of kidney disease

          -  Clinical diagnosis of severe gastrointestinal disorders

          -  History of Alcohol or any other substance abuse
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>40 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Nigel Hoggard, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Aberdeen Rowett Institute of Nutrition and Health</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Nigel Hoggard, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>01224 716655</phone>
    <email>N.Hoggard@abdn.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Aberdeen Rowett Institute of Nutrition and Health</name>
      <address>
        <city>Aberdeen</city>
        <zip>AB21 9SB</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Nigel Hoggard, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>01224 716655</phone>
      <email>N.Hoggard@abdn.ac.uk</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Nigel Hoggard, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Martineau LC, Couture A, Spoor D, Benhaddou-Andaloussi A, Harris C, Meddah B, Leduc C, Burt A, Vuong T, Mai Le P, Prentki M, Bennett SA, Arnason JT, Haddad PS. Anti-diabetic properties of the Canadian lowbush blueberry Vaccinium angustifolium Ait. Phytomedicine. 2006 Nov;13(9-10):612-23. Epub 2006 Sep 18.</citation>
    <PMID>16979328</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zafra-Stone S, Yasmin T, Bagchi M, Chatterjee A, Vinson JA, Bagchi D. Berry anthocyanins as novel antioxidants in human health and disease prevention. Mol Nutr Food Res. 2007 Jun;51(6):675-83. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17533652</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lau FC, Bielinski DF, Joseph JA. Inhibitory effects of blueberry extract on the production of inflammatory mediators in lipopolysaccharide-activated BV2 microglia. J Neurosci Res. 2007 Apr;85(5):1010-7.</citation>
    <PMID>17265471</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>DeFuria J, Bennett G, Strissel KJ, Perfield JW 2nd, Milbury PE, Greenberg AS, Obin MS. Dietary blueberry attenuates whole-body insulin resistance in high fat-fed mice by reducing adipocyte death and its inflammatory sequelae. J Nutr. 2009 Aug;139(8):1510-6. Epub 2009 Jun 10.</citation>
    <PMID>19515743</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2011</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>July 26, 2011</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 16, 2010</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Nigel Hoggard</name_title>
    <organization>University of Aberdeen</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>anthocyanin</keyword>
  <keyword>blaeberries</keyword>
  <keyword>bilberries</keyword>
  <keyword>blueberries</keyword>
  <keyword>mirtoselect</keyword>
  <keyword>glucose disposal</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 2</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Insulin Resistance</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
</clinical_study>
