<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="174">
  <!-- This xml conforms to:  http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>Information obtained from ClinicalTrials.gov on October 20, 2011</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01167166</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>04-19</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01167166</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Safety and Efficacy of 72-hour and 120-hour Infusion of ON 01910.Na in Acute Myeloid Leukemia (AML) and Acute Lymphoid Leukemia (ALL)</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 1/2, Single Arm Study To Assess the Efficacy and Safety of 72-Hour and 120-Hour Continuous Intravenous Dosing of ON 01910.Na Administered Every Other Week in Patients With Relapsed/Refractory Acute Myeloid or Lymphocytic Leukemia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Onconova Therapeutics, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Onconova Therapeutics, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      For patients with leukemia who have not responded to or have progressed after an initial
      response to standard therapy, therapeutic options are limited.  Although responses to
      standard regimens do occur, durable remissions are achieved infrequently and current
      regimens are not curative in the majority of patients. Identification of active agents in
      patients with relapsed Acute Myeloid Leukemia (AML) ultimately affords the potential for use
      upfront as a component of induction regimens that may translate to improved outcome.
      Therefore, development of new agents is of critical importance. This study will look at a
      new, investigational agent, ON 01910.Na, to determine if it has the potential to help
      Patients with AML and Acute Lymphocytic Leukemia (All).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a single center, open-label, phase 1/2 study in which two to thirty three patients
      with refractory acute myeloid or lymphocytic leukemia who meet all other inclusion/exclusion
      criteria will be administered a daily dose of 2400 mg ON 01910.Na dose as a intravenous
      continuous infusion (IVCI) over 24 hours for 72 to 120 consecutive hours every 2 weeks for
      the first 8 weeks and every 4 weeks afterwards.

      In the phase 1 component of the trial, a standard dose escalation scheme will be followed
      with the enrolment of at least three patients treated with a daily dose of 2400 mg ON
      01910.Na IVCI over 24 hours for 72 hours.  The dose escalation scheme will follow a
      traditional dose escalation rule, also known as the &quot;3+3&quot; rule:

      If none of the initial three patients treated in the 72-hour cohort experience dose-limiting
      toxicity (DLT), during the first two 2-week cycles, then a new cohort of three patients will
      be treated at the same 2400 mg/24h daily dose but for an increased 120 hours duration.

      DLT is defined as an adverse event possibly related to ON 01910.Na that is:

        -  Grade ≥ 3 non-hematological toxicity other than nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, fever,
           esophagitis/dysphagia

        -  Grade ≥ 3 nausea and vomiting uncontrolled by antiemetics; grade ≥ 3 diarrhea
           uncontrolled by antidiarrheal agents; grade ≥ 3 drug-induced fever uncontrolled by
           antipyretics; grade ≥3 metabolic abnormalities that are not controlled by optimal
           supportive care measures

        -  Grade ≥ 3 stomatitis and/or esophagitis/dysphagia lasting &gt; 3 days

        -  Marrow cellularity &lt;5% on day 42 or later (6 weeks) from start of therapy without
           evidence of leukemia

      If one of the three patients in the 72-hour cohort experiences a DLT during the first two
      cycles, then three additional patients will be treated for the same 72 hours duration.
      Escalation to the 120-hour cohort will proceed only if no more than one of the six patients
      treated in the 72-hour cohort experiences a DLT.

      If two or more patients in the 72-hour cohort experience DLT during the first two cycles,
      then the maximum tolerated dose (MTD) will have been exceeded, no further dosing extension
      will occur, and a full safety review will determine if further enrollment of patients will
      proceed.

      If none of the initial three patients in the 120-hour cohort experiences DLT during the
      first two cycles, this regimen will be confirmed as the Maximum Tolerated Dose (MTD) and no
      further dose escalation will occur.

      If one of the three patients in the 120-hour cohort experiences DLT during the first two
      cycles, then three additional patients will be treated for the same duration.  If no more
      than one patient experiences a DLT, the 120-hour regimen will be confirmed as the Maximum
      Tolerated Dose (MTD) and no further dose escalation will occur.

      If two or more patients in the 120 hours cohort experience DLT during the first two cycles,
      then the maximum tolerated dose (MTD) will be determined to be 2400 mg/24h administered for
      72 hours every other week.

      Once the phase 1 portion of the study is completed, accrual to the phase 2 portion will
      begin. Patients treated at the MTD during the phase 1 portion will be included in the phase
      2 component and will be evaluated for response and secondary end points.

      The total study duration is 30 weeks, which includes a 2-week screening phase, a 24-week
      dosing phase, and a 4-week follow-up phase that begins after the last dose of ON 01910.Na.
      Beginning at week 4, and every 2 weeks thereafter, patients will be assessed for response
      and followed up.

      Patients who achieve by week 24 a response or stabilization of their disease are eligible to
      receive an additional 24 weeks of ON 01910.Na at the same dose and will be followed up.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification:  Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model:  Single Group Assignment, Masking:  Open Label, Primary Purpose:  Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Dose Limiting Toxicity (DLT)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 8 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>DLT: adverse event possibly related that is:
Grade ≥ 3 non-hematological toxicity other than nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, fever, esophagitis/dysphagia
Grade ≥ 3 nausea and vomiting uncontrolled by antiemetics; grade ≥ 3 diarrhea uncontrolled by antidiarrheal agents; grade ≥ 3 drug-induced fever uncontrolled by antipyretics; grade ≥3 metabolic abnormalities that are not controlled by optimal supportive care measures
Grade ≥ 3 stomatitis and/or esophagitis/dysphagia lasting &gt; 3 days
Marrow cellularity &lt;5% on day 42 or later (6 weeks) from start of therapy without evidence of leukemia</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in bone marrow blast cell and peripheral blood counts at 5, 13 and 25 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Determine the clinical response rate (complete or partial remission) according to response criteria in patients with relapsed/refractory acute myeloid or lymphocytic leukemia (1 Cheson BD, Bennett JM, Kopecky KJ, et al. Revised Recommendations of the International Working Group for Diagnosis, Standardization or Response Criteria, Treatment Outcomes and Reporting Standards for Therapeutic Trials in Acute Myeloid Leukemia. JCO 21:4642, 2003).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Concentration of ON 01910.Na in plasma</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 1 and Week 3</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Blood samples to determine concentration of ON 01910.Na in plasma will be collected at 6 hours after the start of the second 24-hour infusion (Day 2) at Weeks 1 and 3.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">34</enrollment>
  <condition>Acute Myeloid Leukemia</condition>
  <condition>Acute Myelocytic Leukemia</condition>
  <condition>Acute Lymphoid Leukemia</condition>
  <condition>Acute Lymphocytic Leukemia</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ON 01910.Na Concentrate</intervention_name>
    <description>The dose of ON 01910.Na will be 2400 mg/24h as an intravenous continuous infusion over 72 or 120 hours every 2 weeks for the first 8 weeks and every 4 weeks afterwards.</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. ≥ 18 years of age.

          2. Histologically documented or cytologically confirmed diagnosis of one of the
             following hematological malignancies:

               -  Acute myelocytic leukemia (AML) refractory to standard induction treatment, or
                  relapsed after standard therapy (including transformed myeloproliferative
                  diseases with at least 10% blasts in bone marrow and chronic myeloid leukemia in
                  a blast phase)

               -  Acute lymphocytic leukemia (ALL) refractory to induction treatment, or relapsed
                  after standard therapy

          3. Patients should not have received any prior chemotherapy for their leukemia within 14
             days and should have recovered from any toxicity related to prior chemotherapy to at
             least grade 1. In the presence of rapidly proliferating disease, patients can be
             included after a washout period of 7 days. Hydroxyurea can be administered as
             clinically indicated, and no washout is required.

          4. Patients may not be candidates for, or must have declined, bone marrow
             transplantation from an HLA-identical donor in the immediate future (ie, within 4
             weeks) or other chemotherapeutic regimens known to produce consistent remissions.

          5. Patients with known meningeal infiltration may be enrolled only if radiation has been
             completed, and a clearing of peripheral blood blasts has been noted.  Intrathecal
             therapy can be continued if judged to be in the best interest of the patient to
             prevent recurrence, provided there is no toxicity associated with it and there has
             been clearance of blasts in the cerebrospinal fluid.

          6. ECOG Performance Status 0, 1 or 2.

          7. Willing to adhere to the prohibitions and restrictions specified in this protocol.

          8. Patient (or his/her legally authorized representative) must have signed an informed
             consent document indicating that he/she understands the purpose of and procedures
             required for the study and is willing to participate in the study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Any active malignancy within the past year except basal cell or squamous cell skin
             cancer or carcinoma in situ of the cervix or breast.

          2. Known HIV-1 seropositivity.

          3. Uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to symptomatic
             congestive heart failure, unstable angina pectoris or cardiac arrhythmia.

          4. Uncontrolled active systemic infection not adequately responding to appropriate
             therapy.

          5. Total bilirubin &gt; 1.5 mg/dL not related to hemolysis or Gilbert's disease.

          6. ALT or AST &gt; 2.5 X ULN.

          7. Serum creatinine &gt; 2.0 mg/dL.

          8. Ascites requiring active medical management including paracentesis, or hyponatremia
             (defined as serum sodium value of &lt;130 Meq/L).

          9. Female patients who are pregnant or lactating; Male patients with female sexual
             partners who are unwilling to follow the strict contraception requirements (condom
             use). Patients of reproductive potential who do not agree to use adequate
             contraceptive [including prescription oral contraceptives (birth control pills),
             contraceptive injections, intrauterine device (IUD), double-barrier method
             (spermicidal jelly or foam with condoms or diaphragm), contraceptive patch, or
             surgical sterilization] before entry and throughout the study; Female patients with
             reproductive potential who do not have a negative serum or urine beta-HCG pregnancy
             test at screening.

         10. Major surgery without full recovery or major surgery within 3 weeks of ON 01910.Na
             treatment start.

         11. Uncontrolled hypertension (defined as a systolic pressure equal to or greater than
             160 and/or a diastolic pressure equal to or greater than 110).

         12. New onset seizures (within 3 months prior to the first dose of ON 01910.Na) or poorly
             controlled seizures

         13. Any concurrent investigational agent or chemotherapy, radiotherapy or immunotherapy.

         14. Psychiatric illness/social situations that would limit the patient's ability to
             tolerate and/or comply with study requirements.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jorge Cortes, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Francois E. Wilhelm, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>267 759-3680</phone>
    <email>fwilhelm@onconova.us</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Texas M. D. Anderson Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jorge Cortes, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.mdanderson.org/patient-and-cancer-information/index.html</url>
    <description>Patient and cancer information on M. D. Anderson Cancer Center web site.</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>September 2011</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>September 22, 2011</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>July 19, 2010</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Leukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Lymphoid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Precursor Cell Lymphoblastic Leukemia-Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myeloid, Acute</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myeloid</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
</clinical_study>
