<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="125">
  <!-- This xml conforms to:  http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>Information obtained from ClinicalTrials.gov on October 20, 2011</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01244906</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NSH 911</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01244906</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Post-transplant Cyclophosphamide and Sirolimus Following RIC Transplant</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase II Trial of Post-Transplant Cyclophosphamide and Sirolimus for Graft-versus-host Disease (GVHD) Prophylaxis Following Reduced Intensity Allogeneic Hematopoietic Stem Cell Transplantation</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Northside Hospital, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Blood and Marrow Transplant Group of Georgia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Northside Hospital, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This trial will evaluate the safety and efficacy of post-transplant Cy and sirolimus
      following reduced intensity allogeneic SCT.  It is hoped that the combination of a reduced
      intensity preparative regimen with a calcineurin-free GVHD prophylaxis regimen will decrease
      the risk of acute and chronic GVHD, by both limiting mucosal toxicity and augmenting immune
      reconstitution, thereby improving the safety of the procedure.  The past experience with
      post-transplant Cy suggests that SCT recipients will attain rapid donor T cell chimerism,
      which the investigators hope will translate into improved disease control through the well
      documented graft-versus-malignancy effects of donor T cells.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Intervention Model:  Single Group Assignment, Masking:  Open Label, Primary Purpose:  Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of GVHD</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>To estimate the incidence of graft-versus-host disease (GVHD) when utilizing post-transplant cyclophosphamide (Cy) and sirolimus for GVHD prophylaxis following reduced intensity allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell transplantation (SCT) in patients with high risk hematologic malignancies.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of ANC/Platelet engraftment</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately Day 30</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>To estimate the incidence of neutrophil and platelet engraftment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Study outcomes</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>To obtain estimates of overall survival (OS), relapse, non-relapse mortality (NRM) and event-free survival (EFS)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessment of toxicities</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Characterize additional hematologic and non-hematologic toxicities associated with this transplant regimen</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Chimerism</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Characterize rate of achievement of full donor chimerism</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">26</enrollment>
  <condition>Hematologic Neoplasms</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Allogeneic Hematopoietic Stem Cell Transplantation</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients will receive fludarabine, busulfan and cyclophosphamide as the conditioning regimen prior to an allo SCT.  Patients will then receive 2 doses of cyclophosphamide post-transplant and utilize sirolimus and mycophenolate mofetil (in mismatched transplants) as GVHD prophylaxis.</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Availability of a 7/8 or 8/8 (HLA-A, B, C, DR) related or unrelated donor

          -  Age 18-75

          -  One of the following high-risk malignancies

          -  Chronic Myelogenous Leukemia

          -  Acute Myelogenous Leukemia

          -  Myelodysplastic Syndrome

          -  Myelofibrosis

          -  Acute Lymphocytic Leukemia

          -  Acute Lymphoblastic Lymphoma

          -  Chronic Lymphocytic Leukemia

          -  Prolymphocytic Leukemia

          -  Low-grade non-Hodgkin's Lymphoma

          -  Mantle Cell Lymphoma

          -  Hodgkin Lymphoma

          -  Myeloma

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Poor cardiac function (EF &lt;40%)

          -  Poor pulmonary function (FEV1 and FVC &lt;50% predicted)

          -  Poor liver function (bilirubin &gt;/= 2 mg/dl not due to hemolysis, Gilbert's or primary
             malignancy)

          -  Poor renal function (creatinine &gt;/= 2 mg/dl or creatinine clearance &lt;40mL/min)

          -  Karnofsky status &lt;70%

          -  HIV positive
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Scott R Solomon, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Blood and Marrow Transplant Group of Georgia</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Scott R Solomon, MD</last_name>
    <phone>404-255-1930</phone>
    <email>ssolomon@bmtga.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Stacey Brown</last_name>
    <phone>404-851-8238</phone>
    <email>stacey.brown@northside.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Northside Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Atlanta</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30342</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Scott R Solomon, MD</last_name>
      <phone>404-255-1930</phone>
      <email>ssolomon@bmtga.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Stacey Brown</last_name>
      <phone>404-851-8238</phone>
      <email>stacey.brown@northside.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Lawrence E Morris, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Asad Bashey, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>H. Kent Holland, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Szydlo R, Goldman JM, Klein JP, Gale RP, Ash RC, Bach FH, Bradley BA, Casper JT, Flomenberg N, Gajewski JL, Gluckman E, Henslee-Downey PJ, Hows JM, Jacobsen N, Kolb HJ, Lowenberg B, Masaoka T, Rowlings PA, Sondel PM, van Bekkum DW, van Rood JJ, Vowels MR, Zhang MJ, Horowitz MM. Results of allogeneic bone marrow transplants for leukemia using donors other than HLA-identical siblings. J Clin Oncol. 1997 May;15(5):1767-77.</citation>
    <PMID>9164184</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>de Witte T, Brand R, van Biezen A, Mufti G, Ruutu T, Finke J, von dem Borne P, Vitek A, Delforge M, Alessandrino P, Harlahakis N, Russell N, Martino R, Verdonck L, Kröger N, Niederwieser D; European Blood and Marrow Transplantation Group (EBMT), Chronic Leukemia Working Party (CLWP)-MDS subcommittee. Allogeneic stem cell transplantation for patients with refractory anaemia with matched related and unrelated donors: delay of the transplant is associated with inferior survival. Br J Haematol. 2009 Sep;146(6):627-36. Epub 2009 Jul 14.</citation>
    <PMID>19604243</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Basara N, Schulze A, Wedding U, Mohren M, Gerhardt A, Junghanss C, Peter N, Dölken G, Becker C, Heyn S, Kliem C, Lange T, Krahl R, Pönisch W, Fricke HJ, Sayer HG, Al-Ali H, Kamprad F, Niederwieser D; East German Study Group Hematology and Oncology (OSHO). Early related or unrelated haematopoietic cell transplantation results in higher overall survival and leukaemia-free survival compared with conventional chemotherapy in high-risk acute myeloid leukaemia patients in first complete remission. Leukemia. 2009 Apr;23(4):635-40. Epub 2009 Jan 8.</citation>
    <PMID>19151786</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mielcarek M, Storer BE, Sandmaier BM, Sorror ML, Maloney DG, Petersdorf E, Martin PJ, Storb R. Comparable outcomes after nonmyeloablative hematopoietic cell transplantation with unrelated and related donors. Biol Blood Marrow Transplant. 2007 Dec;13(12):1499-507.</citation>
    <PMID>18022580</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Taylor PA, Lees CJ, Blazar BR. The infusion of ex vivo activated and expanded CD4(+)CD25(+) immune regulatory cells inhibits graft-versus-host disease lethality. Blood. 2002 May 15;99(10):3493-9.</citation>
    <PMID>11986199</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Edinger M, Hoffmann P, Ermann J, Drago K, Fathman CG, Strober S, Negrin RS. CD4+CD25+ regulatory T cells preserve graft-versus-tumor activity while inhibiting graft-versus-host disease after bone marrow transplantation. Nat Med. 2003 Sep;9(9):1144-50. Epub 2003 Aug 17.</citation>
    <PMID>12925844</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Trenado A, Charlotte F, Fisson S, Yagello M, Klatzmann D, Salomon BL, Cohen JL. Recipient-type specific CD4+CD25+ regulatory T cells favor immune reconstitution and control graft-versus-host disease while maintaining graft-versus-leukemia. J Clin Invest. 2003 Dec;112(11):1688-96.</citation>
    <PMID>14660744</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zhao D, Zhang C, Yi T, Lin CL, Todorov I, Kandeel F, Forman S, Zeng D. In vivo-activated CD103+CD4+ regulatory T cells ameliorate ongoing chronic graft-versus-host disease. Blood. 2008 Sep 1;112(5):2129-38. Epub 2008 Jun 12.</citation>
    <PMID>18550852</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zorn E, Kim HT, Lee SJ, Floyd BH, Litsa D, Arumugarajah S, Bellucci R, Alyea EP, Antin JH, Soiffer RJ, Ritz J. Reduced frequency of FOXP3+ CD4+CD25+ regulatory T cells in patients with chronic graft-versus-host disease. Blood. 2005 Oct 15;106(8):2903-11. Epub 2005 Jun 21.</citation>
    <PMID>15972448</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rieger K, Loddenkemper C, Maul J, Fietz T, Wolff D, Terpe H, Steiner B, Berg E, Miehlke S, Bornhäuser M, Schneider T, Zeitz M, Stein H, Thiel E, Duchmann R, Uharek L. Mucosal FOXP3+ regulatory T cells are numerically deficient in acute and chronic GvHD. Blood. 2006 Feb 15;107(4):1717-23. Epub 2005 Nov 8.</citation>
    <PMID>16278306</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rezvani K, Mielke S, Ahmadzadeh M, Kilical Y, Savani BN, Zeilah J, Keyvanfar K, Montero A, Hensel N, Kurlander R, Barrett AJ. High donor FOXP3-positive regulatory T-cell (Treg) content is associated with a low risk of GVHD following HLA-matched allogeneic SCT. Blood. 2006 Aug 15;108(4):1291-7. Epub 2006 Apr 20.</citation>
    <PMID>16627754</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Coenen JJ, Koenen HJ, van Rijssen E, Kasran A, Boon L, Hilbrands LB, Joosten I. Rapamycin, not cyclosporine, permits thymic generation and peripheral preservation of CD4+ CD25+ FoxP3+ T cells. Bone Marrow Transplant. 2007 May;39(9):537-45. Epub 2007 Mar 12.</citation>
    <PMID>17351648</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zeiser R, Nguyen VH, Beilhack A, Buess M, Schulz S, Baker J, Contag CH, Negrin RS. Inhibition of CD4+CD25+ regulatory T-cell function by calcineurin-dependent interleukin-2 production. Blood. 2006 Jul 1;108(1):390-9. Epub 2006 Mar 7.</citation>
    <PMID>16522809</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lehnert S, Rybka WB. Amplification of the graft-versus-host reaction by cyclophosphamide: dependence on timing of drug administration. Bone Marrow Transplant. 1994 Apr;13(4):473-7.</citation>
    <PMID>8019473</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mayumi H. [Cyclophosphamide-induced immunological tolerance: an overview] Nippon Geka Gakkai Zasshi. 1996 Dec;97(12):1097-108. Review. Japanese.</citation>
    <PMID>9032788</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mayumi H, Himeno K, Tanaka K, Tokuda N, Fan JL, Nomoto K. Drug-induced tolerance to allografts in mice. XII. The relationships between tolerance, chimerism, and graft-versus-host disease. Transplantation. 1987 Aug;44(2):286-90.</citation>
    <PMID>3307052</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Luznik L, Jalla S, Engstrom LW, Iannone R, Fuchs EJ. Durable engraftment of major histocompatibility complex-incompatible cells after nonmyeloablative conditioning with fludarabine, low-dose total body irradiation, and posttransplantation cyclophosphamide. Blood. 2001 Dec 1;98(12):3456-64.</citation>
    <PMID>11719388</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Luznik L, Engstrom LW, Iannone R, Fuchs EJ. Posttransplantation cyclophosphamide facilitates engraftment of major histocompatibility complex-identical allogeneic marrow in mice conditioned with low-dose total body irradiation. Biol Blood Marrow Transplant. 2002;8(3):131-8.</citation>
    <PMID>11939602</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>O'Donnell PV, Luznik L, Jones RJ, Vogelsang GB, Leffell MS, Phelps M, Rhubart P, Cowan K, Piantados S, Fuchs EJ. Nonmyeloablative bone marrow transplantation from partially HLA-mismatched related donors using posttransplantation cyclophosphamide. Biol Blood Marrow Transplant. 2002;8(7):377-86.</citation>
    <PMID>12171484</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Luznik L, Bolaños-Meade J, Zahurak M, Chen AR, Smith BD, Brodsky R, Huff CA, Borrello I, Matsui W, Powell JD, Kasamon Y, Goodman SN, Hess A, Levitsky HI, Ambinder RF, Jones RJ, Fuchs EJ. High-dose cyclophosphamide as single-agent, short-course prophylaxis of graft-versus-host disease. Blood. 2010 Apr 22;115(16):3224-30. Epub 2010 Feb 2.</citation>
    <PMID>20124511</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Uberti JP, Ayash L, Braun T, Reynolds C, Silver S, Ratanatharathorn V. Tacrolimus as monotherapy or combined with minidose methotrexate for graft-versus-host disease prophylaxis after allogeneic peripheral blood stem cell transplantation: long-term outcomes. Bone Marrow Transplant. 2004 Sep;34(5):425-31.</citation>
    <PMID>15273705</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2011</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>June 8, 2011</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 18, 2010</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Scott R. Solomon, MD</name_title>
    <organization>The Blood and Marrow Transplant Program at Northside Hospital</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Chronic Myelogenous Leukemia</keyword>
  <keyword>Acute Myelogenous Leukemia</keyword>
  <keyword>Myelodysplastic Syndrome</keyword>
  <keyword>Myelofibrosis</keyword>
  <keyword>Acute Lymphocytic Leukemia</keyword>
  <keyword>Acute Lymphoblastic Lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Chronic Lymphocytic Leukemia</keyword>
  <keyword>Prolymphocytic Leukemia</keyword>
  <keyword>Low-grade non-Hodgkin's Lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Mantle Cell Lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Hodgkin Lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Myeloma</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Graft vs Host Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hematologic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cyclophosphamide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sirolimus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Everolimus</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
</clinical_study>
