<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="50">
  <!-- This xml conforms to:  http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>Information obtained from ClinicalTrials.gov on October 20, 2011</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01256398</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CDR0000690286</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>CALGB-10701</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01256398</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Dasatinib Followed by Stem Cell Transplant in Treating Older Patients With Newly Diagnosed Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase II Study of Dasatinib (Sprycel®) (IND #73969, NSC #732517) as Primary Therapy Followed by Transplantation for Adults &gt;/= 50 Years With Newly Diagnosed Ph+ Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia by CALGB, ECOG and SWOG</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Cancer and Leukemia Group B</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Unspecified</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      RATIONALE: Dasatinib may stop the growth of cancer cells by blocking some of the enzymes
      needed for cell growth. Giving chemotherapy before a stem cell transplant stops the growth
      of cancer cells by stopping them from dividing or killing them. Monoclonal antibodies, such
      as alemtuzumab, can block cancer growth in different ways. Some block the ability of cancer
      cells to grow and spread. Others find cancer cells and help kill them or carry
      cancer-killing substances to them. Giving more than one drug (combination chemotherapy) and
      giving dasatinib together with chemotherapy may kill more cancer cells.

      PURPOSE: This phase II clinical trial is studying how well dasatinib followed by stem cell
      transplant works in treating older patients with newly diagnosed acute lymphoblastic
      leukemia.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      OBJECTIVES:

      Primary

        -  Estimate the disease-free survival (DFS) and overall survival (OS) profiles in newly
           diagnosed patients 50 years or older who have Ph+ (BCR/ABL+) ALL receiving sequential
           dasatinib followed by allogeneic or autologous HCT or chemotherapy followed by
           dasatinib maintenance.

      Secondary

        -  Compare the OS and DFS profiles for each of the three cohorts to those from similar
           populations from other studies.

        -  Determine the ability of dasatinib to produce or maintain a BCR/ABL-negative status, as
           judged by Q-PCR following sequential dasatinib, chemotherapy, and HCT.

        -  Determine the feasibility of collecting adequate peripheral blood stem cells for
           autologous HCT following dasatinib therapy and assess for residual Ph+ (BCR/ABL+) cells
           by Q-PCR.

        -  Study the safety and efficacy of autologous HCT following therapy with dasatinib.

        -  Study the safety and efficacy of reduced-intensity preparatory regimen followed by an
           allogeneic HCT following induction therapy with dasatinib.

        -  Study the safety and efficacy of dasatinib maintenance administered after allogeneic or
           autologous HCT or chemotherapy.

        -  Correlate plasma and CSF levels of dasatinib when given orally during induction.

      OUTLINE: This is a multicenter study.

        -  Remission induction therapy (RIT): Patients receive oral dasatinib daily continuously
           and dexamethasone orally or IV on days 1-7.

        -  Early intensification therapy: Patients with bone marrow ≤ 20% blasts are assigned to
           cohort A and patients with bone marrow &gt; 20% blasts are assigned to cohort B.

             -  Cohort A: Patients receive dasatinib and dexamethasone as in RIT.

             -  Cohort B: Patients receive dasatinib and dexamethasone as in RIT, and vincristine
                sulfate IV and daunorubicin hydrochloride IV on days 1, 8, and 15.

      Patients who do NOT achieve a complete response (CR) or CR with incomplete hematologic
      recovery based on bone marrow continue on to second induction therapy; patients who achieve
      a hematologic and morphologic CR continue on to CNS prophylaxis therapy.

        -  Second induction therapy: Patients receive dasatinib and dexamethasone as in RIT,
           cyclophosphamide IV on day 1, daunorubicin hydrochloride IV and vincristine sulfate IV
           on days 1 and 8, and filgrastim subcutaneously (SC) beginning on day 9 and continuing
           for ≥ 7 days or one dose of pegfilgrastim on day 9.

        -  CNS prophylaxis therapy: Patients receive oral dasatinib daily continuously during CNS
           prophylaxis therapy; methotrexate intrathecally (IT), vincristine sulfate IV, and
           methotrexate IV over 3 hours on days 1, 15, and 29; oral methotrexate every 6 hours for
           a total of 4 doses each on days 1-2, 15-16, and 29-30; leucovorin calcium IV on days 2,
           16, and 30; and oral leucovorin calcium every 6 hours for a total of 8 doses each on
           days 3-4, 17-18, and 31-32.

        -  Transplantation or alternative chemotherapy and maintenance therapy: Patients aged
           50-70 years with an HLA-matched related or unrelated donor are assigned to allogeneic
           transplantation, patients aged 50-70 years without an HLA-matched related or unrelated
           donor are assigned to autologous transplantation, and patients aged &gt; 70 years or who
           are not transplantation candidates are assigned to alternative chemotherapy.

             -  Allogeneic transplantation: Patients receive fludarabine phosphate IV over 30
                minutes and alemtuzumab IV over 30 minutes on days -7 through -3 and melphalan IV
                over 30 minutes on day -2. Patients undergo allogeneic peripheral blood stem cell
                transplantation (PBSCT) on day 0. Patients then receive filgrastim SC beginning on
                day 1 and continuing until count recovery and tacrolimus IV or orally beginning on
                day -2 and beginning to taper on day 100 (for matched related donors) or day 180
                (for mismatched related or unrelated donors). Beginning on day 30, patients
                receive oral dasatinib daily as maintenance therapy. Treatment continues for ≥ 12
                months in the absence of disease progression.

             -  Autologous transplantation:

                  -  Mobilization: Patients receive etoposide phosphate IV continuously on days
                     1-4, high-dose cytarabine IV over 2 hours every 12 hours for a total of 8
                     doses on days 1-4, and filgrastim SC once or twice daily beginning on day 14
                     and continuing until peripheral blood stem cell collection is complete or WBC
                     &gt; 50,000/μL.

                  -  Leukapheresis: Patients undergo leukapheresis beginning when WBC &gt; 10,000/μL
                     for a target collection of ≥ 5 x 10^6 CD34+ cells/kg. After completion of
                     stem cell collection, patients receive oral dasatinib twice daily until 3
                     days before transplantation.

                  -  Transplantation: Beginning ≥ 4 weeks after recovery from toxicity related to
                     previous treatment, patients receive melphalan IV over 30 minutes on days -2
                     and -1. Patients undergo autologous PBSCT on day 0. Patients then receive
                     filgrastim SC beginning on day 0 and continuing until count recovery.

                  -  Maintenance therapy: Beginning on day 30, patients receive oral dasatinib
                     once daily. Treatment continues for ≥ 12 months in the absence of disease
                     progression.

             -  Alternative chemotherapy: Beginning 3-10 days after completion of CNS prophylaxis
                therapy, patients receive etoposide phosphate IV continuously on days 1-4,
                high-dose cytarabine IV over 2 hours every 12 hours for a total of 8 doses on days
                1-4, and filgrastim SC once or twice daily beginning on day 14 and continuing
                until count recovery.

                  -  Maintenance therapy: Patients receive oral dasatinib once daily beginning on
                     day 30. Patients also receive vincristine sulfate IV every 4 weeks,
                     dexamethasone for 5 days every 4 weeks, oral mercaptopurine once daily, and
                     oral methotrexate once weekly. Treatment continues for ≥ 12 months in the
                     absence of disease progression.

      NOTE: Patients with CNS leukemia or testicular disease may receive additional treatment.

      Bone marrow, cerebrospinal fluid, serum, peripheral blood, and buccal smear samples may be
      collected periodically during study treatment for qualitative-PCR analysis, pharmacokinetic
      analysis, and other laboratory studies.

      After completion of study treatment, patients are followed up every month for 1 year, every
      3 months for 2 years, every 6 months for 2 years, and every year for 5 years.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2010</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Masking:  Open Label, Primary Purpose:  Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Disease-free survival (DFS) at 3 years</measure>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Probability of being BCR-ABL negative in the bone marrow and peripheral blood at the completion of the CNS prophylaxis course (restricted to those patients achieving a complete response [CR])</measure>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Feasibility of maintenance therapy in this patient population (restricted to those patients achieving a CR)</measure>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival</measure>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>DFS</measure>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Response</measure>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">66</enrollment>
  <condition>Leukemia</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>alemtuzumab</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>cyclophosphamide</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>cytarabine</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>dasatinib</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>daunorubicin hydrochloride</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>dexamethasone</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>etoposide phosphate</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>fludarabine phosphate</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>leucovorin calcium</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>melphalan</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>mercaptopurine</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>methotrexate</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>vincristine sulfate</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Genetic</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>polymerase chain reaction</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>laboratory biomarker analysis</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>pharmacological study</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell transplantation</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>autologous hematopoietic stem cell transplantation</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>peripheral blood stem cell transplantation</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        DISEASE CHARACTERISTICS:

          -  Unequivocal histologic diagnosis of ALL

          -  Detection of the t(9;22)(q34;q11) or 3-way variant by metaphase cytogenetics or
             BCR-ABL positive status by molecular analysis (Q-PCR or FISH) in a CLIA-approved
             laboratory

          -  Enrolled on required companion study CALGB-8461 (Cytogenetic Studies in Acute
             Leukemia)

        PATIENT CHARACTERISTICS:

          -  Not pregnant or nursing

          -  Negative pregnancy test

          -  Fertile patients must use effective birth control during and for 3 months after
             completion of the last dose of dasatinib

        PRIOR CONCURRENT THERAPY:

          -  No prior therapy except up to one week of corticosteroids and/or hydroxyurea

          -  No concurrent H_2 blockers or proton pump inhibitors
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>50 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Meir Wetzler, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Roswell Park Cancer Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Tunnell Cancer Center at Beebe Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lewes</city>
        <state>Delaware</state>
        <zip>19958</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Clinical Trials Office - Tunnell Cancer Center</last_name>
      <phone>302-645-3171</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CCOP - Christiana Care Health Services</name>
      <address>
        <city>Newark</city>
        <state>Delaware</state>
        <zip>19713</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Clinical Trial Office - CCOP - Christiana Care Health Services</last_name>
      <phone>302-623-4450</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Florida Hospital Cancer Institute at Florida Hospital Orlando</name>
      <address>
        <city>Orlando</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32803-1273</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Clinical Trials Office - Florida Hospital Cancer Institute</last_name>
      <phone>407-303-5623</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Chicago Cancer Research Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60637-1470</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Clinical Trials Office - University of Chicago Cancer Research</last_name>
      <phone>773-834-7424</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Fort Wayne Medical Oncology and Hematology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Fort Wayne</city>
        <state>Indiana</state>
        <zip>46845</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sreenivasa R. Nattam, MD</last_name>
      <phone>260-484-8830</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Harold Alfond Center for Cancer Care</name>
      <address>
        <city>Augusta</city>
        <state>Maine</state>
        <zip>04330</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Thomas H. Openshaw</last_name>
      <phone>207-621-6100</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CancerCare of Maine at Eastern Maine Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bangor</city>
        <state>Maine</state>
        <zip>04401</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Clinical Trials Office - CancerCare of Maine</last_name>
      <phone>207-973-4274</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Union Hospital of Cecil County</name>
      <address>
        <city>Elkton MD</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21921</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Frank Beardell, MD</last_name>
      <phone>302-737-7700</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UNMC Eppley Cancer Center at the University of Nebraska Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Omaha</city>
        <state>Nebraska</state>
        <zip>68198-6805</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Clinical Trials Office - UNMC Eppley Cancer Center at the Univ</last_name>
      <phone>800-999-5465</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Norris Cotton Cancer Center at Dartmouth-Hitchcock Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lebanon</city>
        <state>New Hampshire</state>
        <zip>03756-0002</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Clinical Trials Office - Norris Cotton Cancer Center</last_name>
      <phone>603-650-7609</phone>
      <email>cancerhelp@dartmouth.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cancer Institute of New Jersey at Cooper - Voorhees</name>
      <address>
        <city>Voorhees</city>
        <state>New Jersey</state>
        <zip>08043</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Clinical Trials Office - Cancer Institute of New Jersey at Coo</last_name>
      <phone>856-325-6757</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Roswell Park Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Buffalo</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>14263-0001</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Clinical Trials Office - Roswell Park Cancer Institute</last_name>
      <phone>877-275-7724</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Monter Cancer Center of the North Shore-LIJ Health System</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lake Success</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>11042</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ruthee-Lu Bayer, MD</last_name>
      <phone>516-562-8973</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Don Monti Comprehensive Cancer Center at North Shore University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Manhasset</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>11030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Clinical Trials Office - Don Monti Comprehensive Cancer Center</last_name>
      <phone>516-734-8900</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Long Island Jewish Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>New Hyde Park</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>11040</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ruthee-Lu Bayer, MD</last_name>
      <phone>516-562-8973</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Wake Forest University Comprehensive Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Winston-Salem</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27157-1096</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Clinical Trials Office - Wake Forest University  Comprehensive</last_name>
      <phone>336-713-6771</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://cancer.gov/clinicaltrials/CALGB-10701</url>
    <description>Clinical trial summary from the National Cancer Institute's PDQ® database</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>October 2011</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>October 11, 2011</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>December 7, 2010</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Monica M. Bertagnolli</name_title>
    <organization>Cancer and Leukemia Group B</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Philadelphia chromosome positive adult precursor acute lymphoblastic leukemia</keyword>
  <keyword>untreated adult acute lymphoblastic leukemia</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Leukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Lymphoid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Precursor Cell Lymphoblastic Leukemia-Lymphoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>6-Mercaptopurine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cytarabine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Methotrexate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fludarabine monophosphate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vidarabine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cyclophosphamide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Melphalan</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Campath 1G</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Etoposide phosphate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fludarabine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Alemtuzumab</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Daunorubicin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dexamethasone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Etoposide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vincristine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>BB 1101</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dasatinib</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dexamethasone acetate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dexamethasone 21-phosphate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leucovorin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Levoleucovorin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
</clinical_study>
