<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="12">
  <!-- This xml conforms to:  http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>Information obtained from ClinicalTrials.gov on October 20, 2011</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01251172</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CDR0000689644</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>CINJ-011003</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01251172</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>RO4929097 After Autologous Stem Cell Transplant in Treating Patients With Multiple Myeloma</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase II Study of RO4929097 to Eradicate Residual Disease in Patients With Multiple Myeloma Post Single Autologous Stem Cell Transplant</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Cancer Institute of New Jersey</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Unspecified</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      RATIONALE: Giving chemotherapy, such as melphalan, before autologous stem cell transplant
      stops the growth of cancer cells by stopping them from dividing or killing them. Before
      treatment, stem cells are collected from the patient's blood and stored. After chemotherapy,
      the stem cells are returned to the patient to replace the blood-forming cells that were
      destroyed by the chemotherapy. RO4929097 may stop the growth of cancer cells by blocking
      some of the enzymes needed for cell growth. Giving RO4929097 after autologous stem cell
      transplant may kill more cancer cells.

      PURPOSE: This phase II clinical trial is studying how well RO4929097 after autologous stem
      cell transplant works in treating patients with multiple myeloma.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      OBJECTIVES:

      Primary

        -  To determine the efficacy of RO4929097 in eradicating residual/persistent disease in
           multiple myeloma patients status post single high-dose melphalan/autologous stem cell
           rescue with residual/persistent disease post-transplant.

      Secondary

        -  To determine the safety of single agent RO4929097 post-autologous stem cell transplant
           in multiple myeloma patients.

        -  To analyze Notch receptor and ligand protein expression in pre-transplant,
           pre-treatment with RO4929097, and post-treatment bone marrow biopsy samples.

        -  To isolate and identify clonogenic multiple myeloma progenitor cells from bone marrow
           aspirate and/or peripheral blood at the following time points: pre-transplant, day 100
           post-transplant, and post-treatment staging bone marrow biopsy.

        -  To analyze Notch receptor and ligand protein expression on isolated clonogenic
           progenitor myeloma cells.

        -  To characterize the tumor xenograft-initiating potential of clonogenic myeloma cells in
           adult Casper zebrafish and SCID-hu model and evaluate the drug toxicity and therapeutic
           potential of RO4929097 with these models.

        -  To analyze anti-angiogenic effects of RO4929097 as measured by reduction in microvessel
           density and VEGFR-1 expression in pre-treatment and post-treatment bone marrow biopsy
           samples.

        -  To determine whether measurement of soluble surrogate markers of angiogenesis prior to
           and following treatment with RO4929097 provide an early marker of disease response to
           Notch inhibition.

      OUTLINE: This is a multicenter study.

        -  Stem cell transplantation and chemotherapy: Patients undergo standard mobilization and
           collection of autologous peripheral stem cells (≥ 4.0 x 10^6 CD34+ cells/kg). Patients
           then receive high-dose melphalan IV on days -3 and -2 and undergo autologous stem cell
           transfusion on day 0. Patients with progressive disease, stable disease, partial
           response, stringent complete response, or complete response are taken off study;
           patients with residual/persistent disease (very good partial response [VGPR]*) at day
           100 continue to therapeutic treatment.

      NOTE: *Patients who meet the criteria for VGPR but have findings of abnormal bone marrow
      cytogenetic study demonstrating ≥ 10% metaphase cells positive for either high-risk
      chromosomal abnormalities or persistent disease-related chromosomal abnormalities (e.g.,
      chromosome del 13; del17p, t(4;14), t(14;16), t(6;14) or complex cytogenetics) will have a
      repeat bone marrow biopsy assessment with cytogenetics within 2-3 weeks. If the repeat
      biopsy findings suggest persistent high-risk cytogenetic findings, then the patient is
      considered eligible to receive gamma-secretase inhibitor RO4929097 to eradicate residual
      disease.

        -  Therapeutic treatment: Beginning 100-110 days after transplantation, patients receive
           oral gamma-secretase inhibitor RO4929097 once daily on days 1-3, 8-10, and 15-17.
           Courses repeat every 21 days in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable
           toxicity.

      Blood and bone marrow samples are collected periodically for laboratory correlative studies.

      After completion of study treatment, patients are followed up for at least 4 weeks.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2010</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Masking:  Open Label, Primary Purpose:  Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall response rate of patients treated with gamma-secretase inhibitor RO4929097</measure>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pre-post comparison of the biologic effects</measure>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Isolating and identifying clonogenic myeloma progenitor cells and subsequently characterizing the tumor xenograft-initiation potential of these cells</measure>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Association of clinical response (relapses) and the myeloma stem cell kinetics (presence and absence of cells and/or percentage of cells)</measure>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse events and abnormal laboratory variables as assessed according to the NCI-CTCAE version 4.0</measure>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">37</enrollment>
  <condition>Multiple Myeloma and Plasma Cell Neoplasm</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>gamma-secretase/Notch signalling pathway inhibitor RO4929097</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>melphalan</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>laboratory biomarker analysis</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>autologous hematopoietic stem cell transplantation</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>hematopoietic stem cell mobilization</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>peripheral blood stem cell transplantation</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        DISEASE CHARACTERISTICS:

          -  Patients must have a diagnosis of multiple myeloma as defined below with staging
             based on the International Staging System:

               -  Meets all of the following criteria for multiple myeloma*:

                    -  Monoclonal plasma cells in the bone marrow ≥ 10% and/or presence of a
                       biopsy-proven plasmacytoma

                    -  Monoclonal protein present in the serum and/or urine^†

                    -  Myeloma-related organ dysfunction (1 or more)^‡:

                         -  Calcium elevation in the blood (serum calcium &gt; 10.5 mg/L or upper
                            limit of normal)

                         -  Renal insufficiency (serum creatinine &gt; 2 mg/dL)

                         -  Anemia (hemoglobin &lt; 10 g/dL or 2 g &lt; normal)

                         -  Lytic bone lesions or osteoporosis** NOTE: *These criteria identify
                            stage IB and stages II and III A/B myeloma by Durie/Salmon stage.
                            Stage IA becomes smoldering or indolent myeloma.

        NOTE: †If no monoclonal protein is detected (non-secretory disease), then ≥ 30% monoclonal
        bone marrow plasma cells and/or biopsy-proven plasmacytoma is required.

        NOTE: ‡A variety of other types of end-organ dysfunctions can occasionally occur and lead
        to a need for therapy. Such dysfunction is sufficient to support classification as myeloma
        if proven to be myeloma-related.

        NOTE: **If a solitary (biopsy-proven) plasmacytoma or osteoporosis alone (without
        fractures) are the sole defining criteria, then &gt; 30% plasma cells are required in the
        bone marrow.

          -  Patients must have measurable disease

               -  Patients with non-secretory multiple myeloma will be eligible only if the
                  baseline serum free light chain level is elevated (≥ 10 mg/dL)

          -  For therapeutic treatment with RO4929097, patients must have peripheral blood stem
             cell collection of ≥ 4.0 x 10^6 cells/kg (patient ideal body weight)

          -  Patients are enrolled into 1 of 2 groups:

               -  Group 1:

                    -  Enrolled pre-transplant

                    -  Patients in remission after an autologous stem cell transplant will not
                       proceed with registration for the therapeutic treatment arm, will not
                       receive any study drug, and will be taken off-study

               -  Group 2

                    -  Missed the time-point of enrollment pre-transplant but will be able to
                       enroll post-transplant at Day 100

                    -  Patients with residual/persistant disease who meet all of the eligibility
                       criteria at the time of registration for the therapeutic treatment arm
                       (after disease-reassessment post autologous transplant of stem cells) will
                       begin study treatment

        PATIENT CHARACTERISTICS:

          -  ECOG performance status ≤ 2, Karnofsky ≥ 60%

          -  Estimated life expectancy of at least 12 weeks

          -  Absolute neutrophil count ≥ 1,500/mcL

          -  Platelets ≥ 100,000/mcL

          -  Hemoglobin ≥ 9.0 g/dL

          -  NOTE: Patients should not require chronic supportive growth factor administration or
             transfusions to meet treatment eligibility criteria (e.g., G-CSF for ANC eligibility)

          -  Serum creatinine ≤ 2.0 mg/dL OR a measured creatinine clearance by 24-hour urine
             collection ≥ 40 mL/min (a calculated creatinine clearance by Cockcroft-Gault formula
             is acceptable in lieu of a measured value)

          -  Total bilirubin within normal institutional limits

          -  AST (SGOT)/ALT SGPT) &lt; 2.5 X institutional ULN

          -  Patients with uncontrolled electrolyte abnormalities including hypocalcemia,
             hypomagnesemia, hyponatremia, hypophosphatemia, or hypokalemia, defined as less than
             the lower limit of normal for the institution despite adequate electrolyte
             supplementation, are excluded from this study

          -  Not pregnant or nursing

          -  Negative pregnancy test

          -  Fertile patients must use two forms of contraception (i.e., barrier contraception and
             one other method of contraception) at least 4 weeks prior to study entry, for the
             duration of study participation, and for at least 12 months post-treatment

          -  No requirement for routine use of hematopoietic growth factors (including granulocyte
             colony-stimulating factor, granulocyte-macrophage colony-stimulating factor, or
             interleukin-11) or platelet transfusions to maintain absolute neutrophil counts or
             platelet counts above the required thresholds for study entry

               -  Use of erythropoietin-stimulating agents and red cell transfusions are also not
                  permitted prior to initiation of RO4929097

          -  Patient must meet the institutional standard criteria for undergoing high-dose
             chemotherapy and autologous stem cell transplant

          -  No serious concomitant systemic disorders (including active infections) that would
             compromise the safety of the patient or compromise the patient's ability to complete
             the study, at the discretion of the investigator

          -  No uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to:

               -  Ongoing or active infection

               -  Symptomatic congestive heart failure

               -  Unstable angina pectoris

               -  A history of torsades de pointes

               -  Cardiac arrhythmia other than chronic, stable atrial fibrillation

               -  Psychiatric illness/social situations that would limit compliance with study
                  requirements

          -  No baseline QTcF &gt; 450 msec (male) or QTcF &gt; 470 msec (female)

          -  Patients with malabsorption syndrome, disease significantly affecting
             gastrointestinal function, or resection of the stomach or small bowel are excluded

               -  Subjects with ulcerative colitis, inflammatory bowel disease, or a partial or
                  complete small bowel obstruction are also excluded

          -  No condition (e.g., gastrointestinal tract disease resulting in an inability to take
             oral medication or a requirement for IV alimentation, prior surgical procedure
             affecting absorption, or active peptic ulcer disease) that impairs the ability to
             swallow and retain RO4929097

          -  Patients who have active hepatitis B or C, or have a history of liver disease, other
             forms of hepatitis, or cirrhosis are ineligible

          -  HIV-positive patients on combination antiretroviral therapy are ineligible

          -  No second primary malignancy except most situ carcinoma (e.g., in situ carcinoma of
             the of the cervix, adequately treated non-melanomatous carcinoma of the skin) or
             other malignancy treated at least 3 years previously with no evidence of recurrence

          -  No history of allergic reactions attributed to compounds of similar chemical or
             biologic composition to RO4929097or other agents used in the study

        PRIOR CONCURRENT THERAPY:

          -  See Disease Characteristics

          -  There are no limitations on type and amount of prior therapy with the following
             exception: patients who have had a prior autologous stem cell transplant or solid
             organ transplant are ineligible

               -  Acute toxicities of prior therapy must have resolved to the NCI-CTCAE version
                  4.0 grade 1 or less (with the exception of alopecia)

          -  Patients taking medications with narrow therapeutic indices that are metabolized by
             cytochrome P450 (CYP450), including warfarin sodium (Coumadin®) are ineligible

          -  No concurrent medications that are strong inducers/inhibitors or substrates of CYP3A4

          -  No concurrent drugs, food, supplements, or over-the-counter medications that may
             interfere with the metabolism of RO4929097, including ketoconazole and fresh-squeezed
             grapefruit juice

          -  Patients may not be receiving any other investigational agents

          -  Patients may not be receiving antiarrhythmics or other medications known to prolong
             QTc

          -  No other investigational or commercial agents or therapies may be administered with
             the intent to treat the patient's malignancy

          -  No patients who have had any chemotherapy or radiotherapy post-autologous stem cell
             transplant prior to entering the therapeutic arm of the study or those who have not
             recovered from the high-dose melphalan and autologous stem cell transplant

          -  For therapeutic treatment with RO4929097, the acute toxicities of the high-dose
             melphalan therapy must have resolved to the NCI-CTCAE version 4.0 Grade 1 or less
             (with the exception of alopecia)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mecide Gharibo, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Cancer Institute of New Jersey</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cancer Institute of New Jersey at UMDNJ - Robert Wood Johnson Medical School</name>
      <address>
        <city>New Brunswick</city>
        <state>New Jersey</state>
        <zip>08903</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Clinical Trials Office - Cancer Institute of New Jersey</last_name>
      <phone>732-235-8675</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://cancer.gov/clinicaltrials/CINJ-011003</url>
    <description>Clinical trial summary from the National Cancer Institute's PDQ® database</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>August 2011</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>August 16, 2011</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 30, 2010</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Mecide Gharibo</name_title>
    <organization>Cancer Institute of New Jersey at UMDNJ - Robert Wood Johnson Medical School</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>refractory multiple myeloma</keyword>
  <keyword>stage I multiple myeloma</keyword>
  <keyword>stage II multiple myeloma</keyword>
  <keyword>stage III multiple myeloma</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Multiple Myeloma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms, Plasma Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Plasmacytoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Melphalan</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
</clinical_study>
