<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="229">
  <!-- This xml conforms to:  http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>Information obtained from ClinicalTrials.gov on October 20, 2011</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01259713</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>GS-EU-131-0247</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2010-019562-91</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01259713</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Prevention of Invasive Fungal Infections in Subjects Receiving Chemotherapy for Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia</brief_title>
  <acronym>AmBiGuard</acronym>
  <official_title>A Phase 3, Double-Blind, Multicenter, Randomized, Placebo-Controlled Study to Assess the Efficacy, Safety and Tolerability of Prophylactic Liposomal Amphotericin B (AmBisome®) for the Prevention of Invasive Fungal Infections (IFIs) in Subjects Receiving Remission-Induction Chemotherapy for Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia (ALL)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Gilead Sciences</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Gilead Sciences</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Argentina: Administracion Nacional de Medicamentos, Alimentos y Tecnologia Medica</authority>
    <authority>Austria : Federal Ministry for Labour, Health, and Social Affairs</authority>
    <authority>Belgium: Federal Agency for Medicinal Products and Health Products</authority>
    <authority>Brazil: Ministry of Health</authority>
    <authority>France: Afssaps - French Health Products Safety Agency</authority>
    <authority>Germany: Federal Institute for Drugs and Medical Devices</authority>
    <authority>Greece: Ministry of Health and Welfare</authority>
    <authority>Italy: National Institute of Health</authority>
    <authority>Portugal: National Pharmacy and Medicines Institute</authority>
    <authority>Spain: Agencia Española de Medicamentos y Productos Sanitarios</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The study aims to investigate whether prophylaxis with AmBisome can reduce the incidence of
      invasive fungal infections (IFIs) in patients with Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia (ALL) who
      are undergoing their first remission induction.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation:  Randomized, Intervention Model:  Parallel Assignment, Masking:  Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose:  Prevention</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>proportion of subjects with proven or probable invasive fungal infections</measure>
    <time_frame>during remission induction chemotherapy for ALL (up to 12 weeks)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Proportion of subjects diagnosed with proven or probable IFIs during remission induction chemotherapy for ALL. Diagnoses of proven or probable IFIs will be assessed according to EORTC/MSG criteria by an independent data review board (IDRB) who will be blinded to subject treatment assignment.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>pulmonary infiltrates</measure>
    <time_frame>during remission-induction chemotherapy (up to 12 weeks)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The proportion of subjects with pulmonary infiltrates</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>subjects requiring antifungal treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>during remission-induction chemotherapy (up to 12 weeks)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The proportion of subjects requiring antifungal treatment according to the protocol guidelines prior to starting consolidation chemotherapy</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>subject death due to fungal infection</measure>
    <time_frame>during remission-induction chemotherapy (up to 12 weeks)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The proportion of subjects who die due to fungal infection; causality as assessed by the IDRB or Investigator</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>proven or probable IFIs by investigator</measure>
    <time_frame>during remission-induction chemotherapy (up to 12 weeks)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The proportion of subjects diagnosed with proven or probable IFIs, according to the EORTC/MSG criteria as assessed by the investigator.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">354</enrollment>
  <condition>Invasive Fungal Infection</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>AmBisome</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Blinded AmBisome 5 mg/kg twice weekly administered by IV route over 2 hours twice weekly (each dose separated alternately by 2 and 3 days each week).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Blinded placebo twice weekly administered by IV route over 2 hours twice weekly (each dose separated alternately by 2 and 3 days each week).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Liposomal amphotericin B</intervention_name>
    <description>5 mg/kg twice weekly administered by IV route over 2 hours twice weekly (each dose separated alternately by 2 and 3 days each week during induction chemotherapy</description>
    <arm_group_label>AmBisome</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>AmBisome</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Blinded placebo twice weekly administered by IV route over 2 hours twice weekly (each dose separated alternately by 2 and 3 days each week) during induction chemotherapy</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Newly diagnosed ALL receiving an ALL chemotherapy regimen that typically induces at
             least 10 days of neutropenia

          -  Age equal or greater than 18 years

          -  Able to have all screening tests performed quickly to ensure results can be obtained
             and evaluated before randomization so that the first dose of randomized study drug
             for IFI prophylaxis can be administered within 5 days of first remission-induction
             chemotherapy

          -  Ability to understand and sign a written informed consent form, which must be
             obtained prior to initiation of any study procedures

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Known hypersensitivity to amphotericin B or AmBisome, the metabolites or formulation
             excipients, in particular known history of anaphylactic reaction to amphotericin B or
             AmBisome or any of its metabolites or formulation excipients

          -  Known hypersensitivity to the excipients of the placebo formulation

          -  Current fever (≥38°C) unless explained by noninfectious causes

          -  Subjects with proven, probable or possible IFI (according to EORTC/MSG criteria) at
             screening or in subject history

          -  Pulmonary infiltrates

          -  Concomitant or previous treatment with an antifungal drug within the previous 30 days
             unless the plasma level is below the limit of detection or at least 5 half-lives of
             the antifungal has elapsed since the treatment was given

          -  Serum creatinine &gt; 2 x the upper limit of the normal range (ULN)

          -  Grade 3 Liver function test results: alanine aminotransferase or aspartate
             aminotransferase &gt; 5 x ULN; total bilirubin &gt; 2.5 x ULN

          -  Any severe co morbidity other than underlying hematological  disease (ALL), which in
             the investigator's judgment may interfere with study evaluations or affect the
             subject's safety

          -  Subjects who have taken any investigational drug in the last 30 days prior to
             screening, with the exception of ALL chemotherapy investigational products being used
             as part of the subject's current ALL treatment protocol

          -  Pregnant or nursing females
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mike Hawkins, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Gilead Sciences</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jacqueline Ewan</last_name>
    <phone>+44 122389</phone>
    <phone_ext>7416</phone_ext>
    <email>Jacqueline.Ewan@gilead.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Gilead Sciences</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cambridge</city>
        <zip>CB21 6GT</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2011</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>September 20, 2011</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>December 10, 2010</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Mike Hawkins</name_title>
    <organization>Gilead Sciences</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Ambisome</keyword>
  <keyword>ALL</keyword>
  <keyword>invasive fungal infection</keyword>
  <keyword>prophylaxis</keyword>
  <keyword>liposomal amphotericin B</keyword>
  <keyword>Invasive fungal infection prophylaxis</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Leukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Lymphoid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Precursor Cell Lymphoblastic Leukemia-Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Mycoses</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Amphotericin B</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Liposomal amphotericin B</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
</clinical_study>
