<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="27">
  <!-- This xml conforms to:  http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>Information obtained from ClinicalTrials.gov on October 20, 2011</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01174108</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>100154</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>10-H-0154</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01174108</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Allogeneic Hematopoietic Stem Cell Transplantation for Severe Aplastic Anemia and Other Bone Marrow Failure Syndromes Using G-CSF Mobilized CD34+ Selected Hematopoietic Precursor Cells Co-Infused With a Reduced Dose of Non-Mobilized Donor T-cells</brief_title>
  <official_title>Allogeneic Hematopoietic Stem Cell Transplantation for Severe Aplastic Anemia and Other Bone Marrow Failure Syndromes Using G-CSF Mobilized CD34+ Selected Hematopoietic Precursor Cells Co-Infused With a Reduced Dose of Non-Mobilized Donor T-Cells</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

        -  Stem cell transplants from related donors (allogenic stem cell transplants) can be used
           to treat individuals with certain kinds of severe blood diseases or cancers, such as
           severe anemia. Allogenic stem cell transplants encourage the growth of new bone marrow
           to replace that of the recipient. Because stem cell transplants can have serious
           complications, researchers are interested in developing new approaches to stem cell
           transplants that will reduce the likelihood of these complications.

        -  By reducing the number of white blood cells included in the blood taken during the stem
           cell collection process, and replacing them with a smaller amount of white blood cells
           collected prior to stem cell donation, the stem cell transplant may be less likely to
           cause severe complications for the recipient. Researchers are investigating whether
           altering the stem cell transplant donation procedure in this manner will improve the
           likelihood of a successful stem cell transplant with fewer complications.

      Objectives:

      - To evaluate a new method of stem cell transplantation that may reduce the possibly of
      severe side effects or transplant rejection in the recipient.

      Eligibility:

        -  Recipient: Individuals between 8 and 80 years of age who have been diagnosed with a
           blood disease that can be treated with allogenic stem cell transplants, and who have a
           related donor to provide the stem cells.

        -  Donor: Individuals between 2 and 80 years of age who are related to the recipient and
           are eligible to donate blood.

      Design:

        -  All participants will be screened with a physical examination and medical history.

        -  DONORS:

        -  Donors will undergo an initial apheresis procedure to donate white blood cells.

        -  After the initial donation, donors will receive injections of filgrastim to release
           bone marrow cells into the blood.

        -  After 5 days of filgrastim injections, donors will have apheresis again to donate stem
           cells that are present in the blood.

        -  RECIPIENTS:

        -  Recipients will provide an initial donation of white blood cells to be used for
           research purposes only.

        -  From 7 days before the stem cell transplant, participants will be admitted to the
           inpatient unit of the National Institutes of Health Clinical Center and will receive
           regular doses of cyclophosphamide, fludarabine, and anti-thymocyte globulin to suppress
           their immune system and prepare for the transplant.

        -  After the initial chemotherapy, participants will receive t...
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell transplantation (aHSCT) can cure patients with a variety
      of bone marrow failure syndromes (BMFS) including severe aplastic anemia (SAA), paroxysmal
      nocturnal hematuria (PNH), and refractory anemia (RA) myelodysplastic syndrome (MDS)
      associated with cytopenias. Patients with BMFS have traditionally been transplanted with
      bone marrow (BM) as a stem cell source. Although chronic graft versus host disease (cGVHD)
      occurs less commonly with BM compared to G-CSF mobilized peripheral blood stem cell (PBSC)
      transplants, BM allografts have lower CD34+ progenitor cell numbers, which increases the
      risk of graft rejection in heavily transfused BMFS patients to 15-20 percent. To overcome
      this risk, our group developed a novel transplant approach for patients at high risk for
      graft rejection that utilized cyclophosphamide, fludarabine and ATG conditioning followed by
      infusion of a CD34+ cell rich, T-cell replete G-CSF mobilized PBSC allograft. Remarkably, in
      56 consecutive BMFS patients who had multiple risk factors for graft rejection who underwent
      this transplant approach graft rejection did not occur, with all patients achieving complete
      donor lymphohematopoietic chimerism. Unfortunately, recipients of G-CSF mobilized PBSC had a
      higher incidence of chronic GVHD than has historically been observed with BM transplantation
      (72 percent vs. 50 percent cumulative incidence of cGVHD at 1 year respectively). G-CSF
      mobilized PBSC transplants contained approximately a 20 fold higher dose of T-cells that had
      undergone a TH- 2 type cytokine polarization, a factor which likely contributed to this high
      incidence of cGVHD.

      In this protocol, we attempt to prevent graft failure and to reduce the incidence of cGVHD
      by transplanting high numbers of CD34+ selected PBSC co-infused with a reduced dose of
      non-mobilized donor T-cells that have not undergone a TH-2 cytokine polarization.

      Subjects with BMFS at high risk for graft rejection will undergo allogeneic stem cell
      transplantation from an HLA identical sibling using the identical conditioning regimen
      utilized in protocol 99-H-0050. Using the Miltenyi ClinicMACs system, recipients will
      receive an allograft on day 0 containing donor CD34+ cells that have been positively
      selected and T-cell depleted following G-CSF mobilization (goal CD34+ cell dose of 5 times
      10(6) CD34+ cells /kg recipient) combined with 2 times 10(7) cells/kg of non-mobilized CD3+
      T-cells previously collected and cryopreserved from the same donor by apheresis prior to
      G-CSF mobilization.

      Primary objective: To evaluate whether administering a CD34+ selected, T-cell depleted
      peripheral blood stem cell graft with a concomitant infusion of non-mobilized donor T-cells
      at a dose that matches the T-cell dose that is infused in historical bone marrow transplant
      cohorts will reduce the incidence of cGVHD at 1 year to that observed with a conventional
      bone marrow transplant (50 percent) without increasing the risk of graft failure. This trial
      design will allow the trial to stop early if it is unlikely that we have reduced the
      proportion of one year cGVHD to 50 percent or if the combined event rate for failed donor
      engraftment or treatment related mortality (TRM) at day 100 exceeds 20 percent.

      The primary endpoint of this study will be cGVHD at day 365.

      Secondary end points include transplant related mortality, engraftment, degree of donor-host
      chimerism, incidence of acute and chronic graft versus host disease (GVHD), transplant
      related morbidity and overall survival.  Health related quality of life will also be
      assessed as a secondary outcome measure pre-transplant, 30 and 100 days post transplant and
      every 6 months until 5 years post transplant.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation:  Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification:  Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model:  Single Group Assignment, Masking:  Open Label, Primary Purpose:  Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Primary endpoint of this study is chronic GVHD by one year.</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Transplant related mortality, engraftment, degree of donor-host chimerism, incidence of acute and chronic graft versus host disease (GVHD), transplant related morbidity and overall survival.</measure>
    <time_frame>Cumulative</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">110</enrollment>
  <condition>Severe Aplastic Anemia</condition>
  <condition>MDS (Myelodysplastic Syndrome)</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Miltenyi CD34 Reagent System</intervention_name>
    <description>N/A</description>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Donor derived G-CSF mobilized PBC</intervention_name>
    <description>N/A</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Recipient:

        Patients diagnosed with one of the following hematologic diseases which are associated
        with reasonable longevity, shown to be curable by allogeneic BMT but where concern for a
        high procedural mortality with conventional BMT may delay or prevent such treatment:

          1. Paroxysmal nocturnal hemoglobinuria (PNH) associated with life-threatening
             thrombosis, and/or cytopenia, and/or transfusion dependence and/or recurrent and
             debilitating hemolytic crisis

          2. Aplastic anemia or pure red cell aplasia (acquired or congenital) associated with
             transfusion dependence and/or neutropenia in patients who are not candidates for, or
             who have failed immunosuppressive therapy

          3. Refractory anemia (RA) or RARS MDS patients who have associated transfusion
             dependence and/or neutropenia.

             Ages 8 to 80

             Availability of HLA identical or single HLA locus mismatched family donor

             EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

             Recipient: any of the following

             Major anticipated illness or organ failure incompatible with survival from PBSC
             transplant

             Diffusion capacity of carbon monoxide (DLCO) less than 40 percent predicted

             Left ventricular ejection fraction less than 40 percent (evaluated by ECHO) or less
             than 30 percent (evaluated by MUGA)

             Serum creatinine greater than 2.5mg/dl or creatinine clearance less than 50 ml/min by
             24 hr urine collection

             Serum bilirubin greater than 4 mg/dl, transaminases greater than 5 times the upper
             limit of normal

             Pregnant or lactating

             Fanconi's anemia

             ECOG performance status of 3 or more

             Other malignant diseases liable to relapse or progress within 5 years, with the
             exception of a separate hematologic malignancy where allogeneic stem cell transplant
             has been shown to be potentially curative.

             Inability to comprehend the investigational nature of the study and provide informed
             consent. The procedure will be explained to subjects age 8 -17 years with formal
             consent being obtained from parents or legal guardian.

             INCLUSION CRITERIA:

             Donor:

             HLA identical or single HLA mismatched family donor

             Age greater than 2 up to 80 years old

             Weight 19 kg or more

             EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

             Donor: any of the following

             Pregnant or lactating

             Unfit to receive filgrastim (G-CSF) or undergo apheresis (history of stroke, MI,
             unstable angina, uncontrolled hypertension, severe heart disease or palpable spleen)

             HIV positive (donors who are positive for HBV, HCV or HTLV-I/II, T.cruzi (Chagas) may
             be used at the discretion of the investigator following counseling and approval from
             the recipient)

             Sickling hemoglobinopathies including HbSS or HbSC. Donors with HbAS are acceptable

             Inability of donor or guardian of donor to comprehend the investigational nature of
             the study and provide informed consent.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>8 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Patient Recruitment and Public Liaison Office</last_name>
    <phone>(800) 411-1222</phone>
    <email>prpl@mail.cc.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>TTY</last_name>
    <phone>1-866-411-1010</phone>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_2010-H-0154.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Young NS, Barrett AJ. The treatment of severe acquired aplastic anemia. Blood. 1995 Jun 15;85(12):3367-77. Review. No abstract available.</citation>
    <PMID>7780125</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Young NS, Maciejewski J. The pathophysiology of acquired aplastic anemia. N Engl J Med. 1997 May 8;336(19):1365-72. Review. No abstract available.</citation>
    <PMID>9134878</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zoumbos NC, Gascon P, Djeu JY, Trost SR, Young NS. Circulating activated suppressor T lymphocytes in aplastic anemia. N Engl J Med. 1985 Jan 31;312(5):257-65.</citation>
    <PMID>2981406</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2011</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>June 8, 2011</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>July 31, 2010</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Richard W. Childs, M.D./National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute</name_title>
    <organization>National Institutes of Health</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Myelodysplastic Syndrome (MDS)</keyword>
  <keyword>Severe Aplastic Anemia</keyword>
  <keyword>Pure Red Cell Aplasia</keyword>
  <keyword>Paroxysmal Nocturnal Hemoglobinuria (PNH)</keyword>
  <keyword>Miltenyi CD34 Reagent System</keyword>
  <keyword>Allogeneic Stem Cell Transplant</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Anemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Anemia, Aplastic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myelodysplastic Syndromes</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Preleukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pancytopenia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hemoglobinuria, Paroxysmal</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
</clinical_study>
