<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="68">
  <!-- This xml conforms to:  http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>Information obtained from ClinicalTrials.gov on October 20, 2011</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01176006</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>100174</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>10-C-0174</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01176006</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pilot Study of Reduced-Intensity Hematopoietic Stem Cell Transplant of DOCK8 Deficiency</brief_title>
  <official_title>Pilot Study of Matched Related and Unrelated Donor Hematopoietic Stem Cell Transplant of DOCK8 Deficiency</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      - DOCK8 deficiency is a genetic disorder that affects the immune system and can lead to
      severe recurrent infections and possible death from blood poisoning or certain types of
      cancers, including blood cancers. Stem cell transplants from matching or closely related
      donors (allogenic stem cell transplants) may be a life-saving treatment for this condition.
      However, stem cell transplants can have serious complications, because they tend to be
      performed with very high doses of chemotherapy and/or radiation. Reduced-intensity stem cell
      transplants use smaller doses of radiation and chemotherapy to weaken but not completely
      eliminate the recipient's stem cells and immunity. Researchers are exploring whether
      reduced-intensity stem cell transplants in people with DOCK8 deficiency may decrease the
      chance of graft rejection and the overall side effects of the transplant.

      Objectives:

      - To evaluate the safety and effectiveness of reduced-intensity allogeneic stem cell
      transplant as a treatment for DOCK8 deficiency.

      Eligibility:

        -  Donors: Healthy individuals between 4 and 60 years of age who are matched with a
           recipient.

        -  Recipient: Individuals between 15 and 60 years of age who have DOCK8 deficiency, have
           suffered two or more life-threatening infections, have either low white blood cell
           levels or have had certain types of cancer (lymphoma or squamous cell carcinoma), and
           have a stem cell donor.

      Design:

        -  All participants will be screened with a physical examination and medical history.

        -  DONORS:

        -  Donors will receive injections of filgrastim to release stem cells into the blood.
           After 5 days of filgrastim injections, donors will have apheresis to donate stem cells
           and white blood cells that are present in the blood.

        -  Donors who are not eligible to receive filgrastim will provide the stem cells through
           bone marrow donation.

        -  RECIPIENTS:

        -  From 7 days before the stem cell transplant, recipients will be admitted to the
           inpatient unit of the National Institutes of Health Clinical Center and will receive
           regular doses of cyclophosphamide, fludarabine, and radiation to suppress their immune
           system and prepare them for the transplant.

        -  From 3 days before the stem cell transplant, recipients will receive the drugs
           tacrolimus and sirolimus to help prevent complications from the transplant.

        -  After the initial chemotherapy and radiation, recipients will receive the donated stem
           cells as a single infusion. Recipi...
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background

      Mutations in the dedicator of cytokinesis-8 (DOCK8) gene are responsible for a newly
      described immunodeficiency disease characterized by a constellation of signs: severe
      cutaneous and sinopulmonary infections with bacterial organisms; severe cutaneous viral
      infections with Herpes simplex, Herpes zoster, Molluscum contagiosum, and Human Papilloma
      Virus; a marked elevation in serum IgE levels and eosinophilia; and homozygous or compound
      heterozygous mutations in the dedicator of cytokinesis 8 (DOCK8) gene. Patients with this
      syndrome die from bacterial sepsis, squamous cell carcinomas, or hematological malignancies.
      Hematopoietic stem cell transplantation (HSCT) represents a potentially life-saving
      treatment for immunodeficiency diseases due to stem cell defects, such as DOCK8 deficiency.
      In this pilot study we propose to evaluate the efficacy and safety of allogeneic HSCT for
      DOCK8 deficiency. We are particularly interested in determining whether allogeneic HSCT
      reverses the lethal disease phenotype in DOCK8 deficiency by reconstituting normal host
      defense. The development of lethal squamous cell carcinomas and lymphomas arising from the
      immunodeficiency in DOCK8 deficiency supports therapeutic intervention before malignancy
      arises.

      Objectives

        -  To determine whether allogeneic HSCT reconstitutes T-lymphocyte and B-lymphocyte cells
           and myeloid cells with normal donor cells at Day +100 and reverses the clinical
           phenotype of severe recurrent infections in patients with DOCK8 deficiency.

        -  To determine the safety of this allogeneic transplant regimen in DOCK8 deficiency by
           assessing transplant related toxicity, the incidence of acute and chronic
           graft-versus-host disease, immune reconstitution, overall survival, and disease-free
           survival

      Eligibility

      Patients 15-60 years old with DOCK8 deficiency who have suffered two or more
      life-threatening infections, or who have developed lymphoma or squamous cell carcinoma, and
      have either a 10/10 matched related donor, or a 10/10 matched unrelated donor.

      Design

      DOCK8 deficiency patients with a matched related or unrelated donor will receive a
      pretransplant conditioning regimen consisting of fludarabine 40 mg/m2/day on days -6, -5,
      -4, and -3, Busulfex 3.2 mg/kg IV every day for four days on -6, -5, -4, and -3. In addition
      DOCK8 deficiency patients receiving unrelated donor transplants will receive equine ATG 30
      mg/kg IV on days -5, -4, -3, and HSCT will be on day 0. Post-transplant immunosuppression
      for graftversus- host-disease (GVHD) prophylaxis will consist of methotrexate 5 mg/m2 IV on
      days +1, +3, +6, and +11 and tacrolimus daily from day -3 until day +180. If there is no
      evidence of graftversus- host disease and patients have achieved full donor chimerism,
      Tacrolimus will be tapered off after day +180.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation:  Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification:  Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model:  Single Group Assignment, Masking:  Open Label, Primary Purpose:  Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To determine whether reduced-intensity allogeneic (HSCT) reconstitutes T-lymphocyte, B-lymphocyte, and NK cell populations with normal donor cells and reverses the clinical phenotype of severe recurrent in patients with DOCK8.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To determine the safety of this allogeneic transplant regimen in DOCK8 by assessing transplant related toxicity, the incidence of acute and chronic GVHD, immune reconstitution, overall survival, and disease-free survival.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">10</enrollment>
  <condition>DOCK8 Deficiency</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fludarabine</intervention_name>
    <description>N/A</description>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Allogeneic HSC transplant</intervention_name>
    <description>N/A</description>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cyclophosphamide</intervention_name>
    <description>N/A</description>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Total Body Irradiation (TBI)</intervention_name>
    <description>N/A</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Recipient:

          1. Patient age of 15-60 years.

          2. DOCK8 deficiency (documentation of DOCK 8 mutation acceptable from an outside
             Laboratory) with the two criteria listed below:

               1. Clinical history of two or more episodes of life-threatening or severely
                  disfiguring infection with opportunistic organisms, including severe recurrent
                  cutaneous and sinopulmonary infections with bacterial or fungal infection, or
                  viral infections with herpes simplex, herpes zoster, Molluscum contagiosum, or
                  human papilloma virus.

               2. Homozygous or compound heterozygous mutations in the DOCK8 gene.

          3. Available 10/10 HLA-matched related donor, or 8/8 matched unrelated donor

          4. Left ventricular ejection fraction &gt;  50%, preferably by 2-D echo, or by MUGA, or
             shortening fraction &gt; 28% by ECHO, obtained within 28 days of enrollment.

          5. Pulmonary Function Tests: Adult patients: Corrected DLCO diffusion capacity and FEV1
             &gt;  40% of expected value obtained within 28 days of enrollment. Pediatric patients:
             DLCO corrected for hemoglobin and alveolar volume greater than or equal to 40% of
             predicted.

          6. Creatinine: Adult patients: less than or equal to 2.0 mg/dl and creatinine clearance
             greater than or equal to 30 ml/min/1.73 m(2).

             Pediatric patients (less than 18 years old): Creatinine less than or equal to 1.5 and
             a creatinine clearance greater than or equal to 30 mL/min/1.73 m(2).

          7. Serum total bilirubin &lt;  2.5 mg/dl; serum ALT and AST less than or equal to 5 times
             upper limit of normal.

          8. Adequate central venous access potential.

          9. Written informed consent/assent obtained from patient/parent or legal guardian.

        Matched Related Donor

          1. Related donor matched at HLA-A, B, C, DR, and DQ loci by high resolution typing
             (10/10 antigen/allele match) are acceptable donors.

          2. Ability to give informed consent; for donors less than 18 years of age, he/she must
             be the oldest eligible donor, their legal guardian must give informed consent, the
             donor must give verbal assent, and he/she must be cleared by social work and mental
             health specialist to participate.

          3. Age 4-60 years, and weight of greater than or equal to 15 kilograms.

          4. Normal flow cytometry profile on peripheral blood leukocytes is required with normal
             numbers of NK cells, B-lymphocytes, and T-lymphocytes.

          5. At least one normal DOCK8 allele by DNA sequencing by GeneDx.

          6. Adequate venous access for peripheral apheresis, or consent to use a temporary
             central venous catheter for apheresis.

          7. Donors must be HIV negative, hepatitis B surface antigen negative, and hepatitis C
             antibody negative.

        g) A donor who is lactating must be willing and able to interrupt breast-feeding or
        substitute formula feeding for her infant during the period of filgrastim administration
        and for two days following the final dose.

        Matched Unrelated Donor

          1. Unrelated donor matched at HLA-A, B, C, and DR, loci by high resolution typing (8/8
             antigen/allele match) are acceptable donors.

          2. The evaluation of donors shall be in accordance with existing NMDP Standard Policies
             and Procedures.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Recipient

          1. HIV infection.

          2. Chronic active hepatitis B.  Patient may be hepatitis B core antibody postitive.

          3. History of psychiatric disorder which may compromise compliance with transplant
             protocol, or which does not allow for appropriate informed consent..

          4. Active infection that is not responding to antimicrobial therapy.

          5. Active CNS involvement by malignancy (patients with known posititve CSF cytology or
             parenchymal lesions visible by CT or MRI).

          6. Pregnant or lactating.

          7. Sexually active individuals capable of becoming pregnant who are unable or unwilling
             to use effective form(s) of contraception during the time enrolled on the study and
             for 1 year post-transplant.

          8. Presence of active malignancy in another organ system other than the hematopoietic
             system.

          9. No available 10/10 HLA-matched related donor, 8/8 matched unrelated donor, or 4/6 (or
             greater) matched UCB unit(s) with a total dose of greater than or equal to 3.5 x10(7)
             TNC/kg.

        Matched Related Donor

          1. History of severe cutaneous viral infections with herpes simplex, herpes zoster, or
             molluscumm contagiosum.

          2. Hyper IgE &gt;  3 times the upper limit of normal.

          3. HIV infection.

          4. Chronic active hepatitis B.  Donor may be hepatitis core antibody postitive.

          5. History of psychiatric disorder which in the opinion of the PI may compromise
             compliance with transplant protocol, or which does not allow for appropriate informed
             consent.

          6. History of hypertension that is not controlled by medication, stroke, or severe heart
             disease.

          7. Other medical contraindications to stem cell donation

          8. History of prior malignancy.

          9. Donors must not be pregnant.

         10. Thrombocytopenia (platelets less than 150,000 per microl) at baseline evaluation.

         11. Donors receiving experimental therapy or investigational agents.

         12. Sensitivity to filgrastim or to E. coli-derived recombinant protein products.

         13. History of autoimmune disorders, including rheumatic diseases and thyroid disorders.

         14. History of documented deep vein thrombosis or pulmonary embolism.

        Matched Unrelated Donor- Failure to qualify as an NMDP donor
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>15 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>NCI Referral Office</last_name>
    <phone>1-888-NCI-1937</phone>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_2010-C-0174.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Anasetti C, Beatty PG, Storb R, Martin PJ, Mori M, Sanders JE, Thomas ED, Hansen JA. Effect of HLA incompatibility on graft-versus-host disease, relapse, and survival after marrow transplantation for patients with leukemia or lymphoma. Hum Immunol. 1990 Oct;29(2):79-91.</citation>
    <PMID>2249952</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Anderlini P, Korbling M, Dale D, Gratwohl A, Schmitz N, Stroncek D, Howe C, Leitman S, Horowitz M, Gluckman E, Rowley S, Przepiorka D, Champlin R. Allogeneic blood stem cell transplantation: considerations for donors. Blood. 1997 Aug 1;90(3):903-8.</citation>
    <PMID>9242518</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Antin JH, Kim HT, Cutler C, Ho VT, Lee SJ, Miklos DB, Hochberg EP, Wu CJ, Alyea EP, Soiffer RJ. Sirolimus, tacrolimus, and low-dose methotrexate for graft-versus-host disease prophylaxis in mismatched related donor or unrelated donor transplantation. Blood. 2003 Sep 1;102(5):1601-5. Epub 2003 May 1.</citation>
    <PMID>12730113</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2011</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>August 30, 2011</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 4, 2010</firstreceived_date>
  <keyword>DOCKS</keyword>
  <keyword>Molluscum</keyword>
  <keyword>Transplant</keyword>
  <keyword>Immunodeficiency</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cyclophosphamide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fludarabine monophosphate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fludarabine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
</clinical_study>
