<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="61">
  <!-- This xml conforms to:  http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>Information obtained from ClinicalTrials.gov on October 20, 2011</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01158118</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>10-1154 / 201108083</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01158118</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Plerixafor and Sargramostim (GM-CSF) for Mobilization of Allogeneic Sibling Donors</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase II Trial Evaluating the Safety and Efficacy of Plerixafor and Sargramostim (GM-CSF) for the Mobilization of Peripheral Blood Stem Cells (PBSC) From Normal, HLA-Matched Allogeneic Sibling Donors</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Washington University School of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Washington University School of Medicine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will gather information about the combination the drugs plerixafor with
      sargramostim in donors of blood-forming cells (stem cells).  These stem cells will be
      collected from the donor and transplanted into their sibling.  The investigators believe
      that the two drugs together will provide enough stem cells for transplantation and may also
      reduce the risk of graft versus host disease.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The main purpose of this study is to gather information about the combination the drugs
      plerixafor with sargramostim in donors of blood-forming cells (stem cells).  Stem cells can
      be taken from the bone marrow of the pelvic bones or from the blood following treatment with
      drugs called growth factors; sargramostim is such a drug.  Once stem cells leave the bone
      marrow and circulate in the blood, they are called peripheral blood stem cells (PBSCs).
      These cells can be collected through a routine procedure called apheresis, which involves
      placing two IVs into the arm which are connected to an apheresis machine; the machine then
      takes blood from the body, removes the stem cells, and returns the blood to the body.

      Normally, a growth factor called filgrastim is given to donors in order to collect the stem
      cells used for transplantation.  However, when stem cells collected using filgrastim are
      transplanted in patients, a possible unpredictable complication is graft versus host
      disease.  It's thought that using a different growth factor such as sargramostim might
      reduce the occurrences of graft versus host disease in patients.  However, sargramostim
      alone does not provide as many stem cells for transplantation as other growth factors.
      Plerixafor is another drug that can increase the number of PBSCs in a donor, but like with
      sargramostim, plerixafor alone does not always provide enough stem cells.  This is why
      sargramostim and plerixafor are being combined in this study: the investigators believe that
      the two drugs together will provide enough stem cells for transplantation and may also
      reduce the risk of graft versus host disease.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2011</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2011</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification:  Efficacy Study, Intervention Model:  Single Group Assignment, Masking:  Open Label, Primary Purpose:  Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Reduce the number of donors requiring a second collection</measure>
    <time_frame>5 days donor and 30 days recipient</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The primary endpoint is to reduce the number of donors treated with GM-CSF who require a second collection to obtain a minimum CD34/Kg (2 x 106) necessary for allogeneic stem cell transplantation when compared to historic controls mobilized with GM-CSF or plerixafor alone. A reduction in failed first leukapheresis from 40% to less than 10% as seen with G-CSF alone would be considered clinically meaningful.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Donor toxicity</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>To estimate the 95% confidence intervals of the proportion of HLA-identical sibling donors who experience grade 3-4 infusion toxicity.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Donor stem cell collection in 1 or 2 apheresis</measure>
    <time_frame>5 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>To estimate the 95% confidence intervals of the proportion of HLA-identical sibling donors who mobilize ≥ 2x106 CD34+ cells/Kg recipient weight safely following one or two aphereses and to estimate the 95% confidence intervals the proportion of HLA-identical sibling donors who reach 5x106 CD34+cells/Kg recipient weight in 1 or 2 aphereses.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Kinetics of stems cell, lymphocyte and dendritic cell mobilization</measure>
    <time_frame>5 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>To determine the kinetics of stem cell, lymphocyte and dendritic cell mobilization using IV plerixafor and GM-CSF and to determine if peripheral blood stem cell products collected after mobilization with IV plerixafor can be used safely for hematopoietic cell transplantation in HLA-matched recipients as measured by neutrophil engraftment by day +21.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics and pharmacodynamics</measure>
    <time_frame>5 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Determine the pharmacokinetics and pharmacodynamics of GM-CSF on IV plerixafor.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Engraftment post transplant</measure>
    <time_frame>100 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Determine the kinetics of immune reconstitution measured by engraftment of neutrophils, platelets, lymphocyte subsets, TREC analysis, and quantitative immunoglobulins after transplantation.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of acute and chronic Graft vs. Host Disease (GvHD)</measure>
    <time_frame>100 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Determine the rate of acute GvHD and chronic GvHD in recipients who receive GM-CSF + IV plerixafor mobilized peripheral blood stem cells.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Transplant related mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>100 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Determine transplant related mortality at day +100</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Relapse, disease progression and death of any cause</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Determine relapse, disease progression and death of any cause</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">34</enrollment>
  <condition>Leukemia, Myeloid, Acute</condition>
  <condition>Myelodysplastic Syndromes</condition>
  <condition>Lymphoma, Non-Hodgkin</condition>
  <condition>Hodgkin Disease</condition>
  <condition>Leukemia, Lymphocytic, Chronic, B-Cell</condition>
  <condition>Multiple Myeloma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sargramostim and plerixafor</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Days 1 thru 4 Sargramostim, Day 5 IV Plerixafor followed by leukopheresis</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sargramostim and plerixafor</intervention_name>
    <description>Days 1 thru 4 Sargramostim 5 mcg/kg/day subcutaneously, Day 5 plerixafor intravenous plerixafor at 320 mcg/kg followed by leukopheresis
If not enough stem cells are collected through the apheresis procedure on Day 5, another injection of sargramostim at 5 mcg/kg/day subcutaneously followed by an IV infusion plerixafor at 320 mcg/kg on followed by leukopheresis Day 6.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sargramostim and plerixafor</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>GM-CSF, Leukine</other_name>
    <other_name>AMD3100, Mozobil</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Donor Eligibility

          -  Donor is 18 to 65 years of age inclusive.

          -  If female and of child-bearing age, donor must be non-pregnant, not breastfeeding,
             and agree to use adequate contraception.

          -  Donor is a 6/6 HLA-matched sibling willing to donate PBSC for transplant.

          -  Donor has adequate cardiac function with no history of congestive heart failure and
             no history of atrial fibrillation or ventricular tachyarrhythmia.

          -  Donor has adequate renal function as defined by a calculated serum creatinine
             clearance of ≥56 ml/min for females and ≥64 ml/min for males.

          -  Donor has adequate hepatic function as defined by a total bilirubin &lt;2x normal or
             absence of hepatic fibrosis/cirrhosis.

          -  Donor has adequate neurologic function as defined by NO evidence of a severe central
             or peripheral neurologic abnormality.  No history of cerebrovascular accident or
             seizure disorder requiring anticonvulsant medication.

          -  Donor must be HIV-1&amp;2 antibody and HTLV-I&amp;II antibody sero-negative, by FDA licensed
             test.

          -  Donor must have an ECOG performance status of 0 or 1.

          -  Donor must demonstrate ability to be compliant with study regimen.

          -  Donor must not have an active infection at the time of study entry.

          -  Donor does not have active alcohol or substance abuse within 6 months of study entry.

          -  Donor is not currently enrolled on another investigational agent study.

          -  Donor does not have any medical condition, which, in the opinion of the clinical
             investigator, would interfere with his/her evaluation.

          -  Ability of the donor to understand and the willingness to sign a written informed
             consent document.

        Recipient Eligibility

          -  Recipient must have available the successful collection of a GM-CSF + plerixafor
             mobilized product.  When an adequate collection cannot be obtained, G-CSF will be
             used and some recipients may need to receive a combined product of mobilized cells
             with plerixafor + GM-CSF and G-CSF mobilized cells. Recipients who receive less than
             2.0 X 106 CD34+ cells/kg/actual recipient weight after six days of GM-CSF and two
             days of IV plerixafor will not be considered &quot;eligible&quot; but followed per protocol for
             safety purposes only.

          -  Recipient is 18 to 65 years of age inclusive.

          -  Recipient is willing and has a 6/6 HLA-matched sibling willing to donate PBSC for
             transplant.

          -  Recipient must provide signed informed consent.

          -  If female and of child-bearing age, recipient must be non-pregnant, not
             breastfeeding, and using adequate contraception.

          -  Recipient must have one of the following diagnoses:

          -  Acute myelogenous leukemia (AML) in 1st or subsequent remission or in relapse,

          -  Acute lymphoblastic leukemia (ALL) in 1st or subsequent remission or in relapse,

          -  Myelodysplastic syndrome either intermediate 1 or 2, or high risk by the
             International Prognostic Scoring System,

          -  Chronic myelogenous leukemia (CML) in accelerated or second chronic phase,

          -  Non-Hodgkin's lymphoma (NHL) or Hodgkin's disease (HD) in 2nd or greater complete
             remission, partial remission, or refractory relapse,

          -  Chronic lymphocytic leukemia (CLL), Rai Stage 2-4, failing at least 2 prior regimens,
             OR

          -  Multiple myeloma (MM), Stage 2-3.

          -  Myeloproliferative disorder or neoplasm

          -  Recipient must have adequate cardiac function with a left ventricular ejection
             fraction ≥ 40%.

          -  Recipient must have adequate pulmonary function defined as NO severe or symptomatic
             restrictive or obstructive lung disease, and formal pulmonary function testing
             showing an FEV1 ≥50% of predicted and a DLCO ≥40% of predicted, corrected for
             hemoglobin.

          -  Recipient must have adequate renal function as defined by a serum creatinine
             clearance of ≥75% of normal (Cockcroft-Gault equation).

          -  Recipient must have adequate hepatic function as defined by a total bilirubin &lt;2x
             normal or absence of hepatic fibrosis/cirrhosis.

          -  Recipient must have adequate neurologic function as defined by NO evidence of a
             severe central or peripheral neurologic abnormality.  Patients with a history of
             previous CNS tumor involvement are eligible provided they are without symptoms or
             signs and the CNS is now free of disease on lumbar puncture and CT scan of the brain.

          -  Recipient must have no evidence of active infection at the time of the transplant
             preparative regimen or at time of transplantation.

          -  Recipient must be HIV-1&amp;2 antibody and HTLV-I &amp; II antibody sero-negative, by FDA
             licensed test.

          -  Recipient has an ECOG performance status of 0 or 1.

          -  Recipient must demonstrate ability to be compliant with medical regimen.

          -  Recipient must not have active alcohol or substance abuse within 6 months of study
             entry.

          -  Recipient must not be enrolled on another investigational agent concurrently.

          -  Recipient must not have any medical condition, which, in the opinion of the clinical
             investigator, would interfere with the evaluation of the patient.

          -  Recipient must have a life expectancy of greater than 4 weeks.

          -  Both men and women and members of all races and ethnic groups are eligible for this
             trial.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Donor Exclusion Criteria in addition to that stated above

          -  Donor may not be receiving any other investigational agents.

          -  Donor may not have a history of allergic reactions attributed to compounds of similar
             chemical or biologic composition to plerixafor or GM-CSF, or known hypersensitivity
             to yeast-derived products or any component of the product.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mark Schroeder, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Washington University School of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Mark Schroeder, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>314-454-8304</phone>
    <email>mschroed@dom.wustl.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Washington University School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>St. Louis</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>63110</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Mark Schroeder, M.D.</last_name>
      <phone>314-454-8304</phone>
      <email>mschroed@dom.wustl.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>John DiPersio, M.D., Ph.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Camille Abboud, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Kenneth Carson, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Amanda Cashen, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Todd Fehniger, M.D., Ph.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Michael Rettig, Ph.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Keith Stockerl-Goldstein, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Michael Tomasson, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Geoffrey Uy, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ravi Vij, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Peter Westervelt, M.D., Ph.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>David Mansur, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.siteman.wustl.edu</url>
    <description>Alvin J. Siteman Cancer Center at Barnes-Jewish Hospital and Washington University School of Medicine</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>September 2011</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>September 22, 2011</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>July 6, 2010</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Precursor Cell Lymphoblastic Leukemia-Lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Leukemia, Myelogenous, Chronic, BCR-ABL Positive</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hodgkin Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Lymphocytic, Chronic, B-Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Lymphoid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myeloid, Acute</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myeloid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, Non-Hodgkin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Multiple Myeloma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms, Plasma Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myelodysplastic Syndromes</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Preleukemia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>JM 3100</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
</clinical_study>
