<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="31">
  <!-- This xml conforms to:  http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>Information obtained from ClinicalTrials.gov on October 20, 2011</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01183728</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>TerCel001</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>Eudra-CT 2009-017405-11</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>Protocol Code</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01183728</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Treatment of Knee Osteoarthritis With Autologous Mesenchymal Stem Cells</brief_title>
  <acronym>KDD&amp;MSV</acronym>
  <official_title>Regeneration of Articular Cartilage in Grade II, III and IV Knee Osteoarthritis by Intraarticular Injection of Autologous Bone Marrow Stem Cells Expanded ex Vivo With a GMP Procedure Developed by IBGM-Valladolid (MSV)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Red de Terapia Celular</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Fundacion Teknon, Centro Medico Teknon, Barcelona</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Instituto de Biologia y Genetica Molecular (IBGM), University of Valladolid</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Scientific Park Foundation, University of Valladolid</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Centro en Red de Medicina Regenerativa de Castilla y Leon</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Institut de Terapia Regenerativa Tissular</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>EGARSAT Suma Intermutual, Barcelona, Spain</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>CETIR Sant Jordi, Barcelona, Spain</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Red de Terapia Celular</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Spain: Spanish Agency of Medicines</authority>
    <authority>Spain: Ministry of Health and Consumption</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In this prospective study we aim to evaluate the feasibility and safety of the implantation
      of 40 millions MSV in knees with osteoarthritis of grade II-IV (Kellgren and Lawrence). The
      working hypothesis proposes that MSV antiinflammatory effect will help healing of articular
      cartilage degeneration to a grade enough to be objectivized by questionnaires and imaging
      procedures. The study of quantitative changes in structure and composition of cartilage
      determined by T2-weighted MRI (Cartigram ) will be performed at 6, 12 and 24 months. Pain
      will be assessed by visual analogue scale (VAS), Oswestry disability index and evaluation of
      the quality of life by Short Form 36 questionnaire (SF-36) completed at 3, 6,12 and 24
      months.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Knee osteoarthritis is the most common form of arthritis. Treatments involve high costs in
      terms of social and economic, are palliative and do not contemplate healing by regenerative
      therapy. It has been shown recently, that mesenchymal stem cells (MSC) can be expanded &quot;in
      vitro&quot; and may regenerate several damaged or injured tissues. In addition its has
      demonstrated that MSC are able to modulate immune responses and to control inflammation
      through its action on T lymphocytes. Preliminary studies in animal models, including one
      carried out in an equine by our research group, confirms feasibility, safety and efficacy
      evidence proposed treatment protocol. Our research group has also experience in preparing
      clinical-grade MSC from bone marrow for other clinical trials and has all the necessary
      facilities and permissions to comply with GMPs imposed by recent EU legislation. Finally,
      our clinical team has a wide experience in regenerative therapies in several previous
      clinical trials for bone and cartilage.

      We present here an alternative proposal, aiming to anti-inflamación and regeneration by
      injection of single dose of mesenchymal stem cells expanded from autologous bone marrow by
      the GMP-complying IBGM-Valladolid procedure (MSV). Treatment involves two non-invasive
      surgical procedures with low morbidity: obtaining bone marrow under local anesthesia and
      sedation, and 4 weeks later, articular injection of the cell product (20 millions MSVs). The
      injection of cells does not even require anesthesia and obtaining bone marrow requires an
      outpatient admission two hours following safety criteria.

      Patients will be evaluated clinically, including pain score (VSA), disability index
      (Oswestry) and life quality (SF-36), and by radiologic and MRI procedures no contrast and
      allowing quantification of morphological and structural changes of the cartilage region
      studied (T2-weighted imaging).

      The design of the study is an open-label prospective, multicenter study. It will recruit 12
      patients with osteoarthritis of II-IV Kellgren and Lawrence grades, Patients will be
      evaluated clinically by previous studies imaging (X-rays and MRI). If they are eligible for
      the study we shall provide them information about the clinical trial with the &quot;Patient
      Information Sheet, quoting them for the Inclusion Visit. In the &quot;Inclusion Visit&quot; if the
      patient decides to participate in the test should sign the Informed Consent Document and a
      schedule for MRI and X-rays will be scheduled. The results of this exploration will be
      considered the standard to which compare any given change in the controls at 6 and 12
      months. On this visit, routine preoperative examinations are performed (EKG, chest X-ray AP,
      basic analytic coagulation tests and identification of HIV, Lues and hepatitis B and C and
      the valuation by the Internal Medicine Service).

      During the visit V0 we shall verify that all inclusion criteria persist and not exclusion
      criteria have appeared, and we shall program V1 (to obtain bone marrow) and provide a
      preliminary date for MSV injection 4 week later (V2). After application, the patients will
      have follow-up schedule at 8 days (V3), 3 (V4), 6 (V5), 12 (V6) and eventually 24 months
      (V7) as detailed below.

      V0: Eligibility. Clinical History. Analysis, Imaging test. Programming of the following
      visits V1 (day 0): Bone marrow aspiration under local anesthesia and sedation V2 (day 23).
      MSV Implantation. V3 (+8 days from Implantation): Security evaluation. V4 (+3 months from
      Implantation): Security evaluation. VAS, ODI, SF-36 questionnaires.

      V5 (+6 months from Implantation): Security evaluation. VAS, ODI, SF-36 questionnaires, RX,
      RNM.

      V6 (+12 months from Implantation): Security evaluation. VAS, ODI, SF-36 questionnaires, RX,
      RNM.

      V7 (+24 months from Implantation): Security evaluation. VAS, ODI, SF-36 questionnaires, RX,
      RNM.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation:  Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification:  Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model:  Single Group Assignment, Masking:  Open Label, Primary Purpose:  Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate the feasibility and safety of the implementation of MSV in the treatment of osteoarthritis of the knee.</measure>
    <time_frame>0, 3, 6, 12 and 24 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Clinical review, questionaires (VAS, Oswestry disbility index, sf36 life quality)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Indication of efficacy</measure>
    <time_frame>0, 3, 6, 12, 24 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Clinical exploration, questionaires (VAS, Oswestry, SF-36 life quality) at all the periods. To evaluate effectiveness through development of criteria for quantitative MRI (Cartigram) denoting regeneration of articular cartilage at 6, 12 and 24 months after the implantation of MSV</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">12</enrollment>
  <condition>Knee Degenerative Disease</condition>
  <condition>Knee Arthrosis</condition>
  <condition>Knee Osteoarthritis</condition>
  <condition>Osteoarthritis, Knee</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>MSV autologous transplantation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Bone marrow collected from patient will be used for mesenchymal stem cells isolation and expansion under GMP conditions at IBGM-Valladolid (MSV). Autologous MSV implanted in knee by articular injection</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Autologous bone marrow mesenchymal stem cells (MSV)</intervention_name>
    <description>Bone marrow collection from patient, mesenchymal cells isolation and expansion under GMP conditions following the IBGM-Valladolid protocol (MSV). Autologous MSV implantation by articular injection.</description>
    <arm_group_label>MSV autologous transplantation</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>MSV, mesenchymal stem cells by IBGM-Valladolid protocol.</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Knee osteoarthritis grade II, III and IV of Kellgren and Lawrence assessed by two
             observers.

          -  Chronic knee pain with mechanical characteristics.

          -  No local or systemic septic process.

          -  Haematological and biochemical analysis without significant alterations that
             contraindicate treatment.

          -  Informed written consent of the patient.

          -  The patient is able to understand the nature of the study

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Age over 75 or under 18 years or legally dependent

          -  Any sign of infection

          -  Positive serology for HIV-1 orHIV-2, Hepatitis B (HBsAg, Anti-HCV-Ab), Hepatitis C
             (Anti-HCV-Ab) and syphilis.

          -  Congenital or acquired malformation resulting in significant deformity of the knee
             and leading to problems in application or evaluation of results.

          -  Overweight expressed as body mass index (BMI) greater than 30.5 (obesity grade II).
             BMI estimated as mass (kg) / corporal surface (m2).

          -  Women who are pregnant or intend to become pregnant or breast-feeding

          -  Neoplasia

          -  Immunosuppressive states

          -  Participation in another clinical trial or treatment with a different investigational
             product within 30 days prior to inclusion in the study.

          -  Other pathologic conditions or circumstances that difficult participation in the
             study according to medical criteria
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>76 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Luis Orozco, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Fundacion Teknon</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ana Sanchez, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>IBGM, University of Valladolid</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Robert Soler, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Institut de Teràpia Regenerativa Tissular, Centro Médico Teknon</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Javier Garcia-Sancho, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>IBGM, University of Valladolid</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Luis Orozco, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>0034 933 933</phone>
    <email>lluis.orozco@itrt.es</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Ana Sanchez, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>0034 983 184121</phone>
    <email>asanchez@ibgm.uva.es</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Teknon Medical Center, ITRT</name>
      <address>
        <city>Barcelona</city>
        <zip>08022</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Luis Orozco, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>0034 933 933 159</phone>
      <email>lluis.orozco@itrt.es</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Robert Soler, MD</last_name>
      <phone>0034 933 933 159</phone>
      <email>robert.soler@itrt.es</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Luis Orozco, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Robert Soler, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Francesc Soler, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Marina Huguet Huguet, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Instituto de Biologia y Genetica Molecular (IBGM), University of Valladolid</name>
      <address>
        <city>Valladolid</city>
        <zip>47003</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ana Sanchez, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>0034 983 184830</phone>
      <email>asanchez@ibgm.uva.es</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Javier Garcia-Sancho, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>0034 983 184830</phone>
      <email>jgsancho@ibgm.uva.es</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ana Sanchez, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Javier Garcia-Sancho, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Mercedes Alberca, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Spain</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://red-tercel.com</url>
    <description>Spanish Cell Therapy Network</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.itrt.es</url>
    <description>Cell application, ITRT-Centro Médico Teknon</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.ibgm.med.uva.es</url>
    <description>Cell production, Instituto de Biologia y Genetica Molecular (IBGM) University of Valladolid</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/mesh/68010003</url>
    <description>osteoarthritis, knee</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>September 2010</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>September 8, 2010</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 13, 2010</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Luis Orozco, MD, PhD, Principal Investigator</name_title>
    <organization>Fundacion Teknon, Centro Medico Teknon</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Knee degenerative disease</keyword>
  <keyword>osteoarthritis</keyword>
  <keyword>gonarthrosis</keyword>
  <keyword>stem cell</keyword>
  <keyword>cellular therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>regenerative therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Mesenchymal stem cells</keyword>
  <keyword>Bone marrow</keyword>
  <keyword>musculoskeletal Diseases</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Joint Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Osteoarthritis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Osteoarthritis, Knee</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
</clinical_study>
