<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="22">
  <!-- This xml conforms to:  http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>Information obtained from ClinicalTrials.gov on October 20, 2011</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01189786</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>27251-EXCESS</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>EXCESS</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01189786</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Ex Vivo T-Cell Depletion of Mobilized Peripheral Blood Stem Cells Via CD34-Selection</brief_title>
  <acronym>EXCESS</acronym>
  <official_title>Ex Vivo T-Cell Depletion of Mobilized Peripheral Blood Stem Cells Via CD34-Selection (EXCESS)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Baylor College of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Texas Children's Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The Methodist Hospital System</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Center for Cell and Gene Therapy, Baylor College of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Baylor College of Medicine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Patients who are asked to participate in this study receive a stem cell transplant for
      treatments of their disease. Unfortunately, there is not a perfectly matched stem cell donor
      and the patients disease does not permit enough time to identify another donor or another
      suitable donor has not been identified. However, a close relative of the patients has been
      found with stem cells that are not a perfect match, but can be used.

      Alternatively, the patient may have already received a stem cell transplant but has evidence
      of mixed chimerism which may lead to an increased risk of relapse. Or, the patient may have
      all donor cells but their bone marrow is not working very well, which may lead to frequent
      blood or platelet transfusions or infection.

      Regardless of the reason, it may be necessary to isolate stem cells from a haploidentical
      (half-match) donor in order to provide bone marrow function. Because the stem cells from the
      donor are only half-matched to the patient, the risk of graft-versus-host disease (GvHD) is
      very high. It is important that the donor's blood cells are specially treated to minimize
      cells that are most likely to attack tissue. This is done by using a special device to
      capture the CD34+ stem cells from the donor's stem cell product prior to giving the cells to
      patient. This method minimizes the donor T cells, which are responsible for causing GvHD.

      Purpose of this study: To estimate the rate of stable engraftment, early post SCT toxicity
      and incidence of GvHD in recipients of G-CSF mobilized peripheral blood stem cells depleted
      of T cells by positive selection for the CD34 antigen
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This protocol is for patients requiring allogeneic stem cell transplant (SCT) or following
      allogeneic SCT and requiring additional cellular therapy

      The stem cell donors are HLA-haploidentical family members. They will receive G-CSF at
      10mcg/kg/day for 5-6 consecutive days to mobilize peripheral blood stem cells with
      monitoring of CD34+ cell counts prior to stem cell collection. Apheresis will be performed
      when the CD34 count reaches 10/μL and continue until preferably at least 5x10^6 CD34+
      cells/kg recipient weight has been collected after CD34+ selection. If the CD34+ count does
      not reach 10/μL by Day 6, the donor will be deemed to have failed mobilization.

      Stem Cell Enrichment and T-cell Depletion: Donor cells will be separated on a CD34+
      enrichment device, to produce a minimum of 3 logs T-cell depletion, using the CliniMACS CD34
      Reagent system. Donor cells will be collected and cryopreserved before conditioning begins,
      if patient is to receive conditioning. If CD3+ cells exceed 5x10^4 cells/kg, consideration
      will be given to using GvHD prophylaxis at the discretion of the primary investigator.

      Graft Facilitation: After receiving CD34+ selected PBSCs, G-CSF may be administered as
      clinically indicated to facilitate neutrophil engraftment, as defined as sustained absolute
      neutrophil count greater than 500 cells/uL.

      Conditioning Regimens: For patients receiving CD34+ stem cells for allogeneic SCT,
      conditioning regimens will be given to patients at the discretion of the treating physician,
      recognizing that a variety of regimens can be utilized.

      For patients receiving CD34+ stem cells as a &quot;topoff,&quot; whether to use a conditioning regimen
      prior to the topoff is at the discretion of the treating physician.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification:  Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model:  Single Group Assignment, Masking:  Open Label, Primary Purpose:  Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To estimate the rate of stable engraftment</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>To estimate the rate of stable engraftment, early post SCT toxicity and incidence of GvHD in recipients of G-CSF mobilized peripheral blood stem cells depleted of T cells by positive selection for the CD34 antigen</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Haploidentical Stem Cell Transplant</condition>
  <condition>CD34+ Selection</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CD34+ PBSC Selection</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The donor cells will be separated on a CD34+ enrichment device, to produce a minimum of 3 logs T-cell depletion, using the CliniMACS CD34 Reagent system.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CliniMACS CD34 Reagent system</intervention_name>
    <description>HLA-haploidentical family member donors will receive G-CSF at 10mcg/kg/day for 5-6 consecutive days to mobilize peripheral blood stem cells with monitoring of CD34+ cell counts prior to stem cell collection. Apheresis will be performed when the CD34 count reaches 10/μL and continue until preferably at least 5x106 CD34+ cells/kg recipient weight has been collected after CD34+ selection.
Donor cells will be separated on a CD34+ enrichment device, to produce a minimum of 3 logs T-cell depletion, using the CliniMACS CD34 Reagent system as per CAGT SOP. Donor cells will be collected and cryopreserved before conditioning begins, if patient is to receive conditioning.</description>
    <arm_group_label>CD34+ PBSC Selection</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  The following must be answered YES for a patient to eligible to participate in study:

               -  Patient requiring allogeneic SCT or following allogeneic SCT requiring
                  additional cellular therapy

               -  Age between birth and 70 years

               -  Patient and/or responsible person able to understand and sign consent

          -  If patient has already received SCT, he or she must have evidence of at least ONE of
             the following:

               -  Evidence of mixed chimerisms (less than 95% donor cells)

               -  Evidence of poor bone marrow function (bone marrow cellularity less than 50%
                  with at least one cytopenia)

               -  Relapsed disease

        Exclusion Criteria:

        -The following must be answered NO for a patient to be eligible to participate in study:

          -  Active, acute GvHD &gt; grade II or extensive, chronic GvHD

          -  Severe life, threatening infection

          -  Pulmonary dysfunction (FEV1, FVC or DLCO 40% of predicted or 3 SD below normal)

          -  Cardiac dysfunction (LVSF less than 25%)

          -  Psychiatric disturbance

          -  Lansky or Karnofsky score &lt; 50%

          -  Total bilirubin &gt; 1.5mg/dL

          -  ALT &gt; 5x normal

          -  Creatinine &gt; 3x normal
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Alana Kennedy-Nasser, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Texas Children's Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Alana Kennedy-Nasser, MD</last_name>
    <phone>832-824-4807</phone>
    <email>aakenned@txccc.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Methodist Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Alana Kennedy-Nasser, MD</last_name>
      <phone>832-824-4807</phone>
      <email>aakenned@txccc.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Carlos Ramos, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Rammurti Kamble, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>George Carrum, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Helen Heslop, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Texas Children's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Alana Kennedy-Nasser, MD</last_name>
      <phone>832-824-4807</phone>
      <email>aakenned@txccc.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Helen E Heslop, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Robert A Krance, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Malcolm Brenner, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Caridad Martinez, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Kathryn Leung, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Carlos Ramos, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Adrian Gee, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Alana Kennedy-Nasser, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2011</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>August 12, 2011</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 25, 2010</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Helen Heslop, M.D</name_title>
    <organization>Center for Cell and Gene Therapy</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Haploidentical Stem Cell Transplant</keyword>
  <keyword>CD34+ Selection</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
</clinical_study>
