<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="233">
  <!-- This xml conforms to:  http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>Information obtained from ClinicalTrials.gov on October 20, 2011</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01159028</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2003-0578 (v) 08-4</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01159028</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Clinical Trial of L-Grb-2 Antisense Oligonucleotide in CML, AML, ALL &amp; MDS</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I Clinical Trial to Study the Safety, Pharmacokinetics, and Efficacy of BP-100.1.01 (L-Grb-2 Antisense Oligonucleotide) in Patients With Refractory or Relapsed Acute Myeloid Leukemia, Philadelphia Chromosome Positive Chronic Myelogenous Leukemia, or Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia, and Myelodysplastic Syndrome</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Bio-Path Holdings, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Bio-Path Holdings, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this clinical research study is to find the highest safe dose of a liposomal
      Growth Factor Receptor Bound Protein-2 antisense oligodeoxynucleotide (L-Grb2 AS) that can
      be given as treatment for patients with Philadelphia Chromosome positive CML, AML, CLL and
      MDS. The trade name of this drug is BP-100-1.01. The response of the leukemia to this
      treatment will also be studied. In addition, the time needed for the body to process this
      drug will be evaluated.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The Philadelphia Chromosome is an unusual genetic trait found in 90-95% of patients with
      CML. The protein created by this unusual trait causes normal cells within the body to become
      cancer cells, and then causes these cells to grow and divide at a rapid rate. Researchers
      think that the protein Growth Factor Receptor Bound Protein-2 (Grb-2) is necessary to the
      growth of these cancerous cells. The drug under study may be able to prevent the cells from
      making this protein. Researchers hope that without this protein, the leukemia cells will
      die.

      Between 18 and 30 patients are expected to be enrolled on this study. Between 3 and 6
      patients will be treated at each dose level. Each new group will be treated at a dose higher
      than the previous group. If the highest safe dose of the study drug is not found after the
      completion of this study, additional doses or another study may be considered.

      The study drug is an antisense molecule complementary to the mRNA (messenger RNA) code for
      the cell's expression of the protein Grb-2.  The study drug is incorporated into lipid (fat)
      particles known as liposomes. This incorporation process is part of the manufacturing
      procedure and is done before the drug is administered. The liposomes (which carry the study
      drug) will then be injected into a vein twice a week for at least 28 days.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2010</start_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification:  Safety Study, Intervention Model:  Single Group Assignment, Masking:  Open Label, Primary Purpose:  Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Evaluate the patient tolerance to this cancer drug</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Efficacy</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Measure the reduction in leukemic blast cells</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">18</enrollment>
  <condition>Safety and Pharmacokinetics of L-Grb-2 in Treating CML, AML, CLL and MDS</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>BP-100-1.01 (Liposomal Grb-2)</intervention_name>
    <description>5 mg/meter squared, dose is constituted in normal saline, administered by IV.  Treatment given twice a week for four weeks.</description>
    <other_name>Liposomal Grb-2</other_name>
    <other_name>L-Grb-2</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  4.1.1 Male or female patients 18 years of age or older 4.1.2 A diagnosis of
             refractory or relapsed acute myeloid leukemia, or Ph+ CML, in chronic, accelerated or
             blast phase, or acute lymphoblastic leukemia, or myelodysplastic syndrome.

        One of the following parameters is required to meet criteria for accelerated phase CML:

          -  Blasts in Peripheral Blood or Bone Marrow ≥15%

          -  Promyelocytes and Blasts in Peripheral Blood or Bone Marrow ≥30%

          -  PB or BM basophils ≥20%

          -  Thrombocytopenia &lt;100 x 103/ml, not resulting from therapy

        Blast phase is defined as ≥30% blasts in peripheral blood or bone marrow, or presence of
        extramedullary disease, except for liver or spleen.

        4.1.2.1 Patients with CML must have demonstrated resistance and/or intolerance to therapy
        with at least 2 tyrosine kinase inhibitors (TKI) 4.1.2.2 AML and Ph+ ALL should have
        received at least one prior treatment regimen and either failed to achieve response or
        relapsed on treatment.

        4.1.2.3 MDS patients should have failed prior therapy with a hypomethylating agent or, if
        associated with a 5q- chromosomal abnormality, lenalidomide. Patients with 5q- unable to
        receive or intolerant to lenalidomide are also eligible.

        4.1.3 Patients must have clinically adequate hepatic and renal functions as defined by:

        ALT&lt;2x ULN Serum creatinine concentration &lt;2x ULN Serum bilirubin &lt;2x ULN 4.1.4 Patients
        must sign an informed consent. 4.1.5 Women of childbearing age must have a negative serum
        or urine pregnancy test prior to the initiation of study drug.

        4.1.6 Barrier contraceptive precautions are to be used throughout the trial by all study
        participants of child bearing potential.

        4.1.7 Patients must be off anti-cancer therapy for at least two weeks prior to study
        entry, with the exception of hydroxyurea or anagrelide (24 hours), TKI (5 days), and
        interferon (two weeks).

        4.1.8 Patients with ECOG Performance of 0-2

        Exclusion Criteria:

        4.2.1 Serious intercurrent medical illnesses, which would interfere with the ability of
        the patient to carry out the treatment program.

        4.2.2 Pregnant or breastfeeding women 4.2.3 Patients who have uncontrolled active
        infection 4.2.4 Patients who have received another Investigational product within the
        longer of 14 days or 5 half-lives of the previous product.

        -
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jorge Cortes, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jorge Cortes, MD</last_name>
    <phone>713-794-5783</phone>
    <email>jcortes@mdanderson.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>M. D. Anderson Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jorge Cortes, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2010</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>July 8, 2010</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>July 7, 2010</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Peter Nielsen, President &amp; CEO</name_title>
    <organization>Bio-Path Holdings, Inc.</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Liposomal Grb-2 treatment of CML</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Precursor Cell Lymphoblastic Leukemia-Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myeloid, Acute</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myelogenous, Chronic, BCR-ABL Positive</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myelodysplastic Syndromes</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Philadelphia Chromosome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
</clinical_study>
