<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="166">
  <!-- This xml conforms to:  http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>Information obtained from ClinicalTrials.gov on October 20, 2011</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01193868</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CDR0000684242</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>MDA-2009-0649</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01193868</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>RO4929097 in Treating Patients With Advanced Non-Small Cell Lung Cancer Who Have Recently Completed Treatment With Front-Line Chemotherapy</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase II/Pharmacodynamic Study of the Gamma-Secretase Inhibitor RO4929097 in Patients Who Have Recently Completed Front-Line Chemotherapy for Advanced Non-Small Cell Lung Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Unspecified</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      RATIONALE: RO4929097 may stop the growth of tumor cells by blocking some of the enzymes
      needed for cell growth.

      PURPOSE: This phase II trial is studying how well RO4929097 works in treating patients with
      advanced non-small cell lung cancer who have recently completed treatment with front-line
      chemotherapy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      OBJECTIVES:

      Primary

        -  To assess clinical activity of the gamma-secretase inhibitor RO4929097 (RO4929097) in
           patients with advanced non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC) who have recently completed
           front-line chemotherapy.

        -  To assess whether percent change in tumor size at 6 weeks after initiation of RO4929097
           correlates with tumor expression of Notch pathway markers, stem cell markers, and/or
           patient genotype polymorphisms for selected components of the Notch pathway.

      Secondary

        -  To assess whether response and time to treatment failure (TTF) correlate with tumor
           expression of Notch pathway markers, stem cell markers, and/or patient genotype
           polymorphisms for selected components of the Notch pathway.

        -  To compare tumor expression of Notch pathway and stem cell markers in these patients
           with the expression of these markers in tumor samples, from a tumor bank, from
           chemo-naïve patients with NSCLC.

        -  To correlate expression of Notch pathway markers with expression of stem cell markers.

        -  To correlate patients' genotype polymorphisms for selected components of the Notch
           pathway and other stem cell pathways with tumor expression of Notch pathway and stem
           cell markers.

        -  To correlate the presence of tumor EGFR-activating mutations with Notch expression,
           stem cell marker expression, and response to RO4929097.

        -  To assess change in expression of Notch pathway markers and stem cell markers over the
           3 days of therapy in a subset of patients and to correlate this with response to
           therapy and TTF, changes of each marker with changes in the other markers of interest,
           with changes in level of tumor cell apoptosis by TUNEL assay.

        -  To compare the expression of Notch pathway and stem cell markers in patients' tumor
           tissue samples, if available, before and after chemotherapy.

      OUTLINE: Patients receive oral gamma-secretase inhibitor RO4929097 once daily on days 1-3,
      8-10, and 15-17. Courses repeat every 21 days in the absence of disease progression or
      unacceptable toxicity.

      Blood and tumor tissue samples are collected for pharmacogenetic, pharmacodynamic, and
      biomarker studies by IHC, FISH, and TUNEL assay.

      After completion of study therapy, patients are followed up periodically.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2010</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2011</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Masking:  Open Label, Primary Purpose:  Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Objective response rate as assessed by RECIST criteria</measure>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to treatment failure as assessed by RECIST criteria</measure>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percent change in tumor size at 6 weeks after initiation of RO4929097</measure>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Comparison between tumor Notch  and stem cell markers expression and patients with or without genotype polymorphism, EGFR-activating mutations, response, and tumor progression by 2.7 months</measure>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Comparison between patients' tumor Notch  and stem cell markers expression with   the chemo-naive patients from the tumor bank</measure>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation between tumor expression of Notch pathway markers with expression of stem cell markers</measure>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Comparison between  the expression of Notch pathway and stem cell markers before and after therapy</measure>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Lung Cancer</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>gamma-secretase/Notch signalling pathway inhibitor RO4929097</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Genetic</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>fluorescence in situ hybridization</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>immunohistochemistry staining method</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>laboratory biomarker analysis</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>pharmacogenomic studies</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>pharmacological study</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        DISEASE CHARACTERISTICS:

          -  Histologically or cytologically confirmed advanced non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC)
             meeting the following criteria:

               -  Stage IV, malignant effusion, or recurrent disease

               -  Received prior front-line cytotoxic chemotherapy (combination or single-agent
                  with or without the addition of targeted agents) for advanced NSCLC

                    -  Patients will be eligible whether or not they have had a response or stable
                       disease or progression of tumor on the front-line cytotoxic therapy, and
                       whether or not they have tumor progression in the interval between their
                       front-line therapy and initiation of therapy on this study

                    -  Patients will also be eligible if they have received maintenance cytotoxic
                       chemotherapy (e.g., pemetrexed) following completion of the front-line
                       chemotherapy, provided there had not been tumor progression between the end
                       of the front-line chemotherapy and the initiation of the maintenance
                       chemotherapy

          -  Measurable disease defined as ≥ 1 lesion that can be accurately measured in ≥ 1
             dimension (longest diameter to be recorded) as &gt; 10 mm by CT scan with cuts at 2.5 or
             5 mm

          -  Tumor amenable to core biopsy (or to incisional, excisional, or punch biopsy)

          -  Patients with asymptomatic or minimally symptomatic brain metastases allowed provided
             it is not anticipated that they will require any of the following:

               -  Corticosteroids for control of cerebral edema

               -  Enzyme-inducing anticonvulsants

               -  Radiotherapy, surgery, or other local therapy for the brain metastases

        PATIENT CHARACTERISTICS:

          -  ECOG performance status (PS) 0-2 (Karnofsky PS 60-100%)

          -  WBC ≥ 3,000/mm³

          -  ANC ≥ 1,000/mm³

          -  Platelet count ≥ 100,000/mm³

          -  Total bilirubin normal

          -  AST and ALT ≤ 3 times upper limit of normal (ULN)

          -  Creatinine ≤ 1.5 times ULN

          -  Hemoglobin ≥ 9 g/dL

          -  INR ≤ 1.7 times ULN

          -  Fertile patients must use 2 forms of effective contraception for ≥ 4 weeks before,
             during, and for ≥ 2 months after completion of study therapy

          -  Negative pregnancy test

          -  Not pregnant or nursing

          -  Able to swallow tablets

          -  No history of allergic reactions attributed to compounds of similar chemical or
             biologic composition to gamma-secretase inhibitor RO4929097 or other agents used in
             this study

          -  No malabsorption syndrome or other condition that would interfere with intestinal
             absorption

          -  No diarrhea &gt; grade 1 despite appropriate therapy

          -  No serologically positivity for hepatitis A, B, or C

          -  Patients with &gt; grade 1 (by CTCAE criteria) hyponatremia or hypocalcemia (based on
             measurement of ionized calcium), despite appropriate medical management are excluded
             from this study, as are patients with hypophosphatemia (serum phosphate below the
             lower limit of normal for the institution), hypomagnesemia, (serum magnesium below
             the lower limit of normal), hypokalemia, or hyperkalemia (serum potassium outside
             normal limits) despite appropriate medical management

          -  No uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to, any of the
             following:

               -  Ongoing or active infection requiring systemic therapy (with antibiotic or
                  antiviral or antifungal agents)

               -  Symptomatic congestive heart failure

               -  Unstable angina pectoris

               -  Angina at rest

               -  Potentially life-threatening cardiac arrhythmias

                    -  Chronic, stable atrial fibrillation, premature atrial or ventricular
                       contractions, sinus tachycardia (provided the rate is controlled at &lt; 115
                       per minute), or sinus bradycardia (provided the rate is &gt; 50 per minute)
                       allowed

               -  History of torsades des pointes

               -  Myocardial infarction within the past 3 months

               -  Psychiatric illness and/or social situations that would limit compliance with
                  study requirements

          -  No baseline QTcF &gt; 450 msec (male) or &gt; 470 msec (female)

        PRIOR CONCURRENT THERAPY:

          -  See Disease Characteristics

          -  No NCI CTCAE toxicities &gt; grade 2

          -  At least 3 weeks since prior front-line therapy or maintenance therapy (6 weeks for
             nitrosourea or mitomycin C)

               -  No more than 8 weeks since completion of prior chemotherapy or maintenance
                  therapy and initiation of study therapy

          -  Prior adjuvant chemotherapy or chemoradiotherapy with curative intent (followed by
             tumor recurrence or progression) before front-line therapy for advanced disease
             allowed

          -  More than 1 week since prior aspirin or Coumadin®

          -  More than 24 hours since therapeutic dose of a heparin product

          -  Patients requiring drugs that are known to cause Torsades des pointes and/or
             prolonged QTc intervals are excluded

               -  Patients requiring drugs with a possible but unproven association with Torsades
                  des pointes and/or QTc prolongation may be eligible, but will require additional
                  electrocardiogram assessments

          -  No other concurrent investigational agents

          -  No concurrent medications with narrow therapeutic indices that are metabolized by
             cytochrome P450 (CYP450), including warfarin sodium (Coumadin®)

          -  No concurrent medications that are strong inducers/inhibitors or substrates of CYP3A4

          -  No concurrent combination antiretroviral therapy for HIV-positive patients

          -  No other concurrent anticancer agents or therapies

          -  No concurrent ketoconazole or grapefruit juice
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>George R. Blumenschein, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>M. D. Anderson Cancer Center at University of Texas</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030-4009</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Clinical Trials Office - M. D. Anderson Cancer Center at the U</last_name>
      <phone>713-792-3245</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://cancer.gov/clinicaltrials/MDA-2009-0649</url>
    <description>Clinical trial summary from the National Cancer Institute's PDQ® database</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>September 2011</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>September 15, 2011</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>September 1, 2010</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>David James Stewart</name_title>
    <organization>M. D. Anderson Cancer Center at University of Texas</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>recurrent non-small cell lung cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>stage IIIB non-small cell lung cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>stage IV non-small cell lung cancer</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Non-Small-Cell Lung</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lung Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
</clinical_study>
